<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The examiner defended, in a fair and sober answer to the two and twenty questions which lately examined the author of Zeal examined, in this answer are (not unseasonably) touched, Christ's interest in this and all nations. Christ's interest, and the Commonweals, as to the present affairs. The true nature of all civil states. The nature of all civil magistracie, and of the civil sword. The title of Christian magistrate. National churches and covenants. The world of religions ... The permission due to conscience ... Idolatry, and the kindes of it. The spiritual and civil sword, ... The forms of worship. The causes of destruction in nations. The violence to the souls of men; ... The dangerous consequence of such violences, ... Christ Jesus himself, ... The crying guilt of soul-rapes ... The light of nature in spirituals. The acts of Asa, Artaxerxes, &amp;c. The fast of Nineveh. The conscientious differences ... The justice and prudence of state-provision against all uncivilities both of popish and protestant ranters.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 218 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84229</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3732</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E675_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206745</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865852</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865852</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118103</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84229)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118103)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 104:E675[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The examiner defended, in a fair and sober answer to the two and twenty questions which lately examined the author of Zeal examined, in this answer are (not unseasonably) touched, Christ's interest in this and all nations. Christ's interest, and the Commonweals, as to the present affairs. The true nature of all civil states. The nature of all civil magistracie, and of the civil sword. The title of Christian magistrate. National churches and covenants. The world of religions ... The permission due to conscience ... Idolatry, and the kindes of it. The spiritual and civil sword, ... The forms of worship. The causes of destruction in nations. The violence to the souls of men; ... The dangerous consequence of such violences, ... Christ Jesus himself, ... The crying guilt of soul-rapes ... The light of nature in spirituals. The acts of Asa, Artaxerxes, &amp;c. The fast of Nineveh. The conscientious differences ... The justice and prudence of state-provision against all uncivilities both of popish and protestant ranters.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 95, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by James Cottrel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: The examiner examined. 1652.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Septemb. 14".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Examiner examined.</term>
               <term>Spiritual life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Idolatry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Discipline --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Religion and state --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Worship --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118103:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Examiner defended, IN A Fair and Sober ANSWER TO The Two and twenty QUESTIONS which lately examined the Author of <hi>Zeal Examined.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this ANSWER are (not unſeaſonably) touched,
<list>
                  <item>Chriſt's intereſt <hi>in this and all Nations.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Chriſt's intereſt, <hi>and the</hi> Commonweals, <hi>as to the preſent affairs.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The true nature of all</hi> Civil States.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The nature of all</hi> Civil Magiſtracie, <hi>and of the</hi> Civil Sword.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Title of</hi> Chriſtian Magiſtrate.</item>
                  <item>National Churches <hi>and</hi> Covenants.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The</hi> world <hi>of</hi> Religions <hi>and</hi> Conſciences <hi>thorowout the world.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The</hi> permiſſion <hi>due to</hi> Conſcience <hi>in (meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly)</hi> Spirituals, <hi>all the world over.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Idolatry, <hi>and the kindes of at.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The</hi> Spiritual <hi>and</hi> Civil <hi>Sword, and the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of them, in</hi> Spirituals.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The</hi> Forms <hi>of</hi> Worſhip.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The cauſes of</hi> deſtruction <hi>to Nations.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The</hi> Violence <hi>to the Souls of men; and of</hi> Intereſt <hi>the cauſe of it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The dangerous</hi> conſequence <hi>of ſuch</hi> Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences, <hi>experimented in ſo many Nations.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The</hi> difference <hi>of the Land of</hi> Canaan, <hi>and the</hi> Kings <hi>thereof, from</hi> all Lands <hi>and</hi> Kings <hi>beſides.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Chriſt Jeſus <hi>himſelf, and his</hi> followers, <hi>ever accounted and puniſhed, as the greateſt</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, Blaſphemers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The crying guilt of</hi> Soul-Rapes <hi>and</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional hypocriſie <hi>in Worſhip.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The light of</hi> Nature in <hi>Spirituals.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The acts of</hi> Aſa, Artaxerxes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Fast of</hi> Nineveh.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The</hi> Conſcientious differences <hi>of the moſt</hi> Conſcientious <hi>in the world, about</hi> God's Worſhip.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The</hi> juſtice <hi>and</hi> prudence <hi>of</hi> State-proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>againſt all</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ncivilities <hi>both of</hi> Popiſh <hi>and</hi> Proteſtant Ranters.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>James Cottrel.</hi> 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:118103:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118103:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Pious Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Wo</hi> honorable Gentlemen <hi>(as is ſaid) have ſo far (lately) honoured</hi> Chriſt Jeſus <hi>and their</hi> honorable ſtations,<note place="margin">The occaſion of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</note> 
               <hi>and</hi> them ſelves, <hi>as to try by the Sword of</hi> God's Spirit (<hi>the</hi> Word of God) <hi>whether the</hi> World, <hi>and the</hi> Civil States <hi>and</hi> Nations <hi>thereof, may permit</hi> Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, Hereticks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The firſt of theſe</hi> Two Worthies <hi>publiſhed his</hi> Zeal Examined: <hi>The ſecond attempts upon the former with</hi> Two and twenty Queſtions, <hi>under this Title;</hi> The Examiner Examined.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It was deſired that the</hi> Examiner of Zeal <hi>might have examined</hi> theſe Queſtions <hi>alſo. But finding an indiſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of</hi> health <hi>upon his</hi> perſon, <hi>and</hi> multiplicity <hi>of</hi> Publike affairs <hi>engaging his</hi> hours <hi>and</hi> minutes; <hi>I have been humbly bold to look up to</hi> heaven, <hi>and to beg the</hi> finger <hi>of God's</hi> moſt holy <hi>and</hi> gracious Spirit, <hi>for the</hi> diſſolving <hi>and</hi> untying <hi>of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:118103:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>It was a</hi> truely-gallant <hi>and</hi> heavenly <hi>ſpeech of the</hi> Author <hi>of theſe</hi> Queſtions,<note place="margin">An heavenly ſpeech.</note> 
               <hi>(whoſoever he be) in his</hi> Epiſtle <hi>or</hi> Preface: [I profeſs my ſelf a <hi>lover</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> whereſoever I finde it, though in an heap of <hi>Errours:</hi> for I know well, that it is the high-way to be given up to <hi>ſtrong deluſions,</hi> not to <hi>receive the love of the Truth,</hi> yea, an <hi>univerſal</hi> love of all truth.] <hi>But I had almoſt ſaid,</hi> (<hi>not onely, What</hi> Saint, <hi>what</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel, <hi>but</hi>) <hi>What</hi> man <hi>will not ſay,</hi> Vincat Veritas? <hi>We know who ſaid,</hi> Amicus Plato, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> magis Amica Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas. <hi>Such counſel is like our</hi> common counſel <hi>of</hi> Phyſick <hi>to</hi> others, <hi>but not ſo</hi> pleaſing <hi>and</hi> practical <hi>in our</hi> own diſtempers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And Oh how many are the</hi> Skreens, <hi>the</hi> Veils, <hi>the</hi> Hoods, <hi>the</hi> Vizards <hi>the</hi> Curtains, <hi>the</hi> Hangings, <hi>the</hi> Clo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ks, <hi>the</hi> Clouds, <hi>and</hi> Colours, <hi>by which the</hi> luſtre <hi>and</hi> ſhining <hi>of that which we call</hi> Truth, <hi>is hidden and eclipſed from us!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For inſtance:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Truth ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected for a Novelty.</note> This cannot be <hi>Truth,</hi> it is a <hi>Novelty.</hi> What will this babler ſay? (<hi>ſaid the famous</hi> Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mians <hi>of</hi> Athens) he feemeth to be a ſetter forth of new Gods; <hi>though all the</hi> old <hi>were</hi> falſe, <hi>and indeed but</hi> new, <hi>and therefore</hi> falſe; <hi>becauſe not the</hi> Alpha <hi>and</hi> Omega,<note place="margin">Quod antiquiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimum optimum.</note> 
               <hi>the</hi> Firſt <hi>and the</hi> Laſt. <hi>Thus cry the</hi> Papiſts <hi>againſt the</hi> Proteſtants, <hi>and the</hi> Proteſtants <hi>againſt</hi> each other: New Doctrines, New Men, New Lights, New Chriſts, New Gods, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is no room in the</hi> Inne <hi>for</hi> Chriſt Jeus <hi>&amp; his</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">2. Commonly Truth is out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly poor.</note> 
               <hi>ovely among the</hi> beaſts <hi>in the</hi> ſtable, <hi>in the</hi> Manger: <hi>A poor</hi> Carpenters ſon, <hi>whence hath be ſuch</hi> learning? <hi>How ſhould ſuch baſe and unlikely Medicines as</hi> Clay <hi>and</hi> Spittle, <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>? How ſhould the</hi> dry <hi>and</hi> lowe <hi>tree be fruitful? How poor</hi> Fiſher-men, Tent-makers,
<pb facs="tcp:118103:3"/>Mechanicks, <hi>know and preach</hi> Chriſt Jeſits? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He takes away our</hi> Hogs (<hi>ſay the</hi> Gadarenes) <hi>and therefore beſeech him to depart from us.</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. Truth is coſtly.</note> 
               <hi>By this</hi> Trade (<hi>ſaith</hi> Demetrius <hi>and his</hi> Crafts men) <hi>we have our</hi> living, <hi>&amp;c. our</hi> Popedoms, Biſhopricks, Benefices. <hi>If we believe this Doctrine, the</hi> Romanes <hi>will come and take away our</hi> place <hi>and</hi> nation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How can you believe (<hi>ſaith</hi> Chriſt Jeſus) who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive honour from one another,<note place="margin">4. Truth is in diſgrace.</note> and not that honor which comes from God alone? <hi>How many had been</hi> convinced <hi>and</hi> perſwaded <hi>that</hi> Chriſt Jeſus <hi>was the</hi> Son <hi>of</hi> God, <hi>but that they loved the</hi> praiſe of men, <hi>more then the</hi> praiſe of God?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Howſoever ſometimes it hath pleaſad God to take off the</hi> Rod <hi>and</hi> Plough <hi>of the</hi> wicked,<note place="margin">5. Truth is perſecuted.</note> 
               <hi>from the</hi> back <hi>of the</hi> righteous; <hi>yet the general</hi> Rule <hi>is That</hi> All that will live godly in Chriſt Jeſus, muſt be hunted. <hi>The great</hi> Lord General, Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>carried his</hi> Croſs <hi>and</hi> Gallows; <hi>and profeſſath it impoſsible for any to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low</hi> him, <hi>without a</hi> denying <hi>of</hi> himſelf <hi>and</hi> taking up his Croſs, <hi>or</hi> Gallows <hi>alſo. Thus are we</hi> (<hi>ſaith</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid <hi>and</hi> Paul) <hi>as</hi> ſheep for the ſhambles all the day long. <hi>Thus muſt thoſe</hi> bleſſed Petitioners <hi>under the</hi> Altar <hi>wait, until the reſt of their</hi> fellow-brethren <hi>and</hi> ſervants <hi>were</hi> ſlain <hi>alſo. Hence</hi> (<hi>though</hi> Chriſt's fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers <hi>have ever found the</hi> ſweeteſt enjoyments <hi>of</hi> God <hi>and</hi> Chriſt, <hi>and the</hi> holy Spirit, <hi>in</hi> ſufferings, <hi>yet</hi>) <hi>how harſh is this</hi> Alarm <hi>to</hi> fleſh <hi>and</hi> blood <hi>which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore rather ſeeks a thouſand</hi> ſhifts, <hi>to</hi> ſwear, <hi>to</hi> ſubſcribe, <hi>to</hi> conform, <hi>(upon the point) to</hi> deny Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Can there any good thing come out of <hi>Nazareth?</hi>
               <note place="margin">6. Truth is prejudiced.</note> 
               <hi>Can</hi> Micaiah <hi>ever ſpeak good to me, who never yet ſpake good to me? And</hi> Haſt thou found me, O mine
<pb facs="tcp:118103:4"/>enemy (<hi>ſaid</hi> A had <hi>to</hi> two Prophets.) <hi>This</hi> Stone <hi>the</hi> builders <hi>have abready refuſed,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>This may be</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bovah<hi>'s miraculous work, to chuſe the ſtones caſt by,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but</hi> fleſh <hi>and</hi> blood <hi>cannot got over this</hi> mountain.</p>
            <p>Do any of the Rulers believe in him? <hi>Do the</hi> learned Scribes,<note place="margin">7. Truth is followed with ſew wiſe, great, learned.</note> 
               <hi>the</hi> Reverend Clergie, <hi>the</hi> King, <hi>the</hi> Queen, <hi>the</hi> Parliament, <hi>the</hi> Counced, <hi>the</hi> Univerſity, <hi>the</hi> Convocation, <hi>the</hi> Aſſembly, <hi>the</hi> Synod? <hi>Oh how</hi> thick <hi>is this</hi> Choud, <hi>that the eyes of the</hi> wiſeſt <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not pierce it! for it is</hi> God<hi>'s</hi> deſigne, <hi>that</hi> few wiſe <hi>and piencing eyes are</hi> choſen, <hi>to ſee</hi> Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>and his</hi> deſpiſed Truths <hi>and</hi> Myſteries.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How many whom Chriſt invites, ſend Chriſt this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer:</hi>
               <note place="margin">8. Truth findes few at leaſure.</note> 
               <hi>I have not ſuch</hi> time <hi>to</hi> ſearch the Scriptures, <hi>as the</hi> Bereans <hi>had: So many are my</hi> diſtractions, <hi>ſo neoeſſary are my</hi> occaſions, <hi>about my</hi> Farm; <hi>about my</hi> Oxen, <hi>about my</hi> Merchandiſe, <hi>about my</hi> Marriage. Go thy way, Paul, (<hi>and</hi> Peter, <hi>and</hi> Chriſt, <hi>and</hi> God) <hi>ſaith</hi> Feſtus, <hi>until I have a</hi> more convenient time, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is the voice of my Beloved, <hi>ſaith the ſoul,</hi> Cant. 1. <hi>yea,</hi> Martha <hi>knows 'tis</hi> Chriſt<hi>'s</hi> voice; <hi>but</hi> dinner <hi>muſt be dreſt; and 'tis for</hi> Chriſt himſelf <hi>alſo,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This Jeſus <hi>(ſay the Jews)</hi> cannot be He: <hi>This man is a</hi> Glutton, <hi>a</hi> Drunkard, <hi>a</hi> Company-keeper. <hi>And juſt as,</hi> John, <hi>becauſe</hi> auſtere <hi>and</hi> harſh, <hi>came from</hi> hell, <hi>and had a</hi> devil, <hi>was</hi> Jeſus <hi>a</hi> Glutton, <hi>&amp;c. becauſe of a mire</hi> loving <hi>and</hi> ſociable, <hi>of a more</hi> merciful <hi>and</hi> piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>diſpoſition and cenverſation. I acknowledge, the</hi> followers <hi>of</hi> Chriſt Jeſus,<note place="margin">The lives of Gods children, cauſing his name to be blaſphemed, like to kindle Fares of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</note> 
               <hi>by</hi> unchriſtian courſes, <hi>may cauſe the</hi> Name <hi>of Chriſt to be</hi> blaſphemed (<hi>as que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionſeſs the</hi> lives <hi>of many</hi> Papiſts <hi>and</hi> Proteſtants <hi>cauſe both</hi> Jews, <hi>and</hi> Turks, <hi>and</hi> Pagans, <hi>to</hi> ſtumble <hi>at him; and therefore, were there no</hi> ſlaughter <hi>of</hi> Witneſſes <hi>in
<pb facs="tcp:118103:4"/>queſtion, I cannot but ſuſpect a</hi> ſtorm, a fire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtraight <hi>impending, which ſhall bring forth a more</hi> refined <hi>and</hi> purer Edition <hi>of</hi> Chriſtianity <hi>to the whole world;</hi>) <hi>yet ſince the</hi> devil <hi>in Engliſh, is an</hi> Accuſer ſtanderes <hi>&amp;c. it is but</hi> deviliſh <hi>to</hi> reproach, <hi>and it is but</hi> fooliſh <hi>to</hi> ſtumble <hi>at</hi> reproaches.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is another, of a</hi> finer ſpun <hi>and</hi> thread;<note place="margin">10. Our ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſences may deceive us.</note> 
               <hi>which</hi> damps <hi>the ingennous ſearchings after,</hi> Truth; <hi>and that is</hi> (<hi>like unto</hi> deceptio viſus) <hi>a</hi> Deluſion <hi>from our very</hi> Senſes, <hi>and from our very</hi> experiments <hi>of our good can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Truth kept out by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</note> 
               <hi>Thus</hi> (<hi>not onely</hi> ignorant ſouls <hi>plead for the</hi> old Religion, <hi>and the</hi> Jews <hi>for their</hi> cakes to the Queen of heaven; then 'twas better, <hi>&amp;c. but</hi>) <hi>what</hi> rejoycing <hi>findes the</hi> heart <hi>of,</hi> David <hi>himſelf, and ſo wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> thouſands <hi>of</hi> Iſrael <hi>with him, even in a</hi> falſe <hi>carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the</hi> Ark, <hi>the</hi> ſigne <hi>of</hi> God<hi>'s moſt holy</hi> preſence? <hi>Yea, is it not one of the</hi> unkindeſt Anſwers <hi>that ever was given to ſo</hi> dear <hi>a</hi> Saviour, (<hi>Cant</hi> 5.) My feet are waſhed, how ſhall I defile them? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">11. Hatred of Truth the higheſt wall againſt it.</note> 
               <hi>What trembling calls for that moſt black and horrid</hi> ſackcloth <hi>of</hi> hell <hi>it ſelf</hi> (<hi>to the weaving of which many of the</hi> former <hi>contribute</hi>) <hi>to wit, a</hi> malicious ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred <hi>of the very</hi> purity <hi>and</hi> holineſs <hi>of the</hi> Son <hi>of</hi> God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is a twofold hatred of</hi> Chriſt Jeſus.<note place="margin">Two walls of hatred of Truth.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Natural. <hi>The</hi> wiſdom <hi>of the</hi> fleſh, <hi>is</hi> enmity <hi>with</hi> God. <hi>But this wall is</hi> ſaltable <hi>and</hi> breakable, <hi>and bleſſedly gives way in</hi> Gods choſen, <hi>to</hi> reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>and</hi> leagues <hi>of</hi> eternal loves <hi>with</hi> Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſecond, is a wall ſo</hi> high <hi>and</hi> ſtrong, <hi>as it ſtands for ever. This is a</hi> malice <hi>and</hi> hatred <hi>after</hi> light. <hi>Such (probably) was</hi> Saul<hi>'s againſt</hi> David <hi>the</hi> ſhadow, <hi>and the</hi> Phariſees <hi>againſt</hi> Chriſt Jeſus <hi>himſelf: They</hi> hated <hi>him, and ſaid,</hi> He ſhall not raign over us. <hi>Thus, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb facs="tcp:118103:5"/>the many hundreds of</hi> falſe Prophets, <hi>there is one more ſaith</hi> Ahab, Micaiah; but I hate him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The reſult of</hi> all theſe (<hi>gentle</hi> Reader) <hi>is too often even in the heart of the</hi> greateſt lover <hi>of</hi> Truth <hi>in the world, a ſeeret</hi> prejudice,<note place="margin">Reſolutions againſt truth.</note> 
               <hi>a</hi> barricado, <hi>a</hi> reſolution <hi>againſt ſome</hi> Truths <hi>of God. Such a</hi> reſolution <hi>was that of the</hi> Captains, <hi>conſulting</hi> Jeremiah <hi>about their ſtay in</hi> Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea, <hi>yet ſecretly reſolved to go down to</hi> Egypt <hi>Thus, like thoſe fourty reſolved to kill</hi> Paul, <hi>they pretend to enquire ſomething</hi> more perfectly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The truth is,</hi> Truth <hi>is a priſoner upon</hi> ſuſpition. <hi>How many</hi> millions <hi>are the</hi> conſpirators <hi>againſt the</hi> life <hi>of it? And yet, let's examine the</hi> priſoner, <hi>call</hi> Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, Claſſes, Synods, Councels, <hi>&amp;c. appoint</hi> Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations, Conferences, <hi>&amp;c. But before the</hi> priſoner <hi>come to the</hi> Governour, <hi>the</hi> Parliament, <hi>the</hi> Councel, &amp;c. <hi>ſtab it, kill it. Yet God forbid we ſhould wound the</hi> Truth, <hi>but the</hi> Heretick, <hi>the</hi> Seducer, <hi>the</hi> Diſturber, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My humble prayer therefore is preſented to the</hi> Father of lights, (<hi>who is</hi> light, <hi>and</hi> love, <hi>and</hi> truth) <hi>that theſe honorable</hi> Examiners, <hi>and all thoſe noble</hi> Bereans <hi>who candidly ſhall pleaſe to examine</hi> them <hi>and</hi> this, <hi>may cry with</hi> David, <hi>ſenſibly and cordially,</hi> (Pſal. 119.) I am a ſtranger in the earth: O hide not thy command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from me.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 10. read <hi>ſhadowing rocks and trees.</hi> p. 27. l. 4. put out <hi>but.</hi> p. 41. for <hi>Religions,</hi> r. <hi>religious.</hi> p. 42. for <hi>ought they,</hi> r. <hi>ought they not.</hi> p. 54. l 24. for <hi>height and prudence,</hi> r. <hi>high prudence.</hi> p. 56. l. 29. for <hi>Whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> r. <hi>Whether.</hi> p 57. l. 12. for <hi>Sorms,</hi> r. <hi>Storme,</hi> p. 61. l. 2. r. <hi>Canaan.</hi> p. 74. in the margin, r. <hi>whether the piſhops.</hi> p. 76. for <hi>the Idolatry,</hi> r. <hi>Idolatry.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118103:5"/>
            <head>The EXAMINER <hi>DEFENDED.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Ship</hi> of the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> (like that gallant<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, <hi>or</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth.</note> Ship now going forth, ſo called) muſt ſhare her <hi>weals</hi> and <hi>woes</hi> in <hi>common.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As the <hi>one,</hi> ſo the <hi>other</hi> hath its dangers of <hi>Rocks</hi> and <hi>Sands,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Common Woes</note> 
               <hi>Storms</hi> and <hi>Tempeſts, Want</hi> of <hi>Proviſions, Sickneſſes</hi> and <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes,</hi> treacherous and profeſſed <hi>enemies, Fires, Leaks, Mutinies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">and</note> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I humbly beg of God, and wiſh to both, their <hi>Fair Windes</hi> and <hi>Weathers, Plentiful proviſions, Unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity</hi> and <hi>Peace, Preſervations, Victories, Boon Voyages,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Weals.</note> and joyful <hi>Anchoring</hi> in their deſired <hi>Ports</hi> and <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</hi> Such <hi>woes</hi> and <hi>weals</hi> are common to all that ſail in either.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:118103:6"/>
            <p>Now in a Ship there is the <hi>whole,</hi> and there is each <hi>private Cabbin.</hi> A <hi>private good</hi> engageth our deſires for the <hi>publike,</hi> and raiſeth <hi>cares</hi> and <hi>fears</hi> for the due prevention of <hi>common evils.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence is it,<note place="margin">Common Duty.</note> that in a <hi>Ship</hi> all agree (in their <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding orders,</hi> and <hi>obeying ſtations</hi>) to give and take the <hi>Word,</hi> to ſtand to the <hi>Helm</hi> and <hi>Compaſs,</hi> to the <hi>Sails</hi> and <hi>Tackling,</hi> to the <hi>Guns</hi> and <hi>Artillery.</hi> This is, this muſt be done in <hi>Artificial,</hi> and in each <hi>Civil Ship</hi> and <hi>Commonweal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence, not to <hi>ſtudy,</hi> and not to <hi>endeavour</hi> the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good,</hi> and to exempt our ſelves from the ſenſe of <hi>common evil,</hi> is a <hi>treacherous Baſeneſs,</hi> a <hi>ſelfiſh Monopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> a kinde of <hi>Tyranny,</hi> and tendeth to the deſtruction both of <hi>Cabin</hi> and <hi>Ship,</hi> that is, of <hi>private</hi> and <hi>publike ſafety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I hope it will not therefore be offenſive,<note place="margin">Chriſts Interest the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weals.</note> that into the <hi>great</hi> and <hi>common treaſury</hi> I caſt my <hi>mite,</hi> and ſay, <hi>Chriſts intereſt</hi> is the <hi>Commonweals. Chriſts intereſt</hi> is that Sheat-<hi>Anchor,</hi> at which this <hi>Ship</hi> hath rid, and can onely ride in ſafety. All <hi>power</hi> in <hi>heaven</hi> and <hi>earth</hi> is his. If <hi>England</hi> make <hi>peace</hi> with him, <hi>ally</hi> with him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> though every <hi>duſt</hi> of the field were an <hi>army,</hi> and every <hi>drop</hi> of the Ocean ſprung up a <hi>Navy</hi> againſt us; yet our <hi>tranquillity</hi> ſhould not be ſhortned, our <hi>Commonweal,</hi> our <hi>Parliament,</hi> our <hi>Peace</hi> ſhould flouriſh.</p>
            <p>But where is that man whoſe <hi>Caſe</hi> is not <hi>right?</hi> Where is the conſcientious <hi>Papiſt,</hi> or <hi>Prelatiſt,</hi> or <hi>Presbyterian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Every Chriſt but one (the true) calls for the Civil ſword and mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</note> or <hi>Independent,</hi> that aſſumes not thus; [<hi>Chriſts intereſt</hi> is <hi>mine?</hi>] And (in ſome ſenſe) I verily believe they all ſay true; plainly thus. As no <hi>Religion</hi> in the world can juſtly chalenge the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118103:6"/>drawing of the <hi>ſword</hi> for its defence; ſo, leaſt of all deſires it that which is, of all, the beſt (and onely true) the <hi>Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know each <hi>Sect</hi> is apt to plead, Mine intereſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Christs,</hi> the <hi>Purſe</hi> and <hi>Sword</hi> of the <hi>State</hi> is not onely <hi>mine,</hi> but 'tis <hi>Christs</hi> due: But,</p>
            <p>I alſo maintain, that 'tis not true <hi>Civility,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chriſts Intereſt in any Nation, is ſoul-free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</note> not true <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> that draws the Sword for one or other. <hi>Chriſts Intereſt</hi> in this <hi>Commonweal</hi> (or any) is the <hi>freedom</hi> of the <hi>ſouls</hi> of the People. I confeſs that all <hi>Nations,</hi> all <hi>Peoples, Kings, Princes, Iudges,</hi> &amp;c. ought to <hi>kiſs the Son,</hi> to be <hi>nurſing fathers</hi> and <hi>mothers</hi> to <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> and his followers. But what a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful miſtake is this, that no people muſt live but <hi>Christians?</hi> That the many millions of millions in our own and other <hi>Nations</hi> of the world, muſt either at the ſhaking of a <hi>ſword</hi> fall down before <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or with the edge of it be cut off for <hi>Idolaters, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, Blaſphemers</hi> (or evil ſpeakers) againſt <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Religion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hath not the God of heaven, <hi>the Father of lights,</hi> written it with the beams of the noon-day-ſun, that (notwithſtanding <hi>pretences</hi>) the truth is, That the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and the <hi>Religion</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Parliament and the Religion of <hi>England,</hi> have ever fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the Sword of <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> hath ever followed the <hi>Sword</hi> of <hi>England?</hi> Was not the <hi>Parliament</hi> and the <hi>Religion</hi> of <hi>England</hi> all <hi>Popiſh</hi> in <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh's days? But in his ſon's, <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, the <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> divided, and turned half <hi>Popiſh,</hi> half <hi>Proteſtant.</hi> In <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth his three children's days, what <hi>turns,</hi> what <hi>wonders?</hi> Was not the <hi>Parliament</hi> and the <hi>Religion</hi> all <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> in that moſt hopeful <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi>'s ſpring? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and as altogether <hi>Popiſh,</hi> when
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118103:7"/>the Sword-fell into the hands of that bloody <hi>Mary?</hi> And when <hi>Gods providence</hi> and <hi>vengeance</hi> wrung the <hi>Sword</hi> from the paw of that <hi>Lioneſs,</hi> and reacht it to the hands of that tender <hi>Lamb Elizabeth;</hi> how hath the <hi>Parliament</hi> and the <hi>Religion</hi> of <hi>England</hi> (ſince her time) carried the <hi>face,</hi> and hung out the <hi>flag</hi> of all <hi>Proteſtants?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In theſe late <hi>Earthquakes</hi> and <hi>Combuſtions</hi> (which the late King begun, by <hi>impoſing</hi> upon the <hi>conſciences</hi> of the <hi>Scotch Presbyters,</hi> in favour of his <hi>Prelates</hi>) how dreadfully hath a <hi>naked Arm</hi> from heaven ſnatcht away the Sword from <hi>both,</hi> and fixt it in a hand more merciful (I hope) to the ſouls of all men, <hi>Iews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who ſees not this to be the <hi>deſigne</hi> and the <hi>decree</hi> of Heaven,<note place="margin">Gods preſent deſigne in <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> To bring into the <hi>light,</hi> and to break to pieces the more-then-iron <hi>Yokes</hi> and <hi>Chains</hi> upon the <hi>ſouls</hi> and <hi>conſciences</hi> of men? Who ſees not, with holy <hi>fear</hi> and <hi>wonder,</hi> that this his <hi>Decree</hi> hath begun to break the <hi>arms</hi> and <hi>necks</hi> of all both <hi>Popiſh</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant perſecutore?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What eye ſo weak, but may obſerve how <hi>little</hi> and how <hi>ſeldom</hi> it pleaſed the <hi>God of heaven</hi> to go out with our Armies,<note place="margin">The Goings of God in the late Wars.</note> until this intereſt of the Son of God <hi>(ſoul-freedom.)</hi> begun to be <hi>ſeen</hi> and <hi>ſerved</hi> by our Armies, and that they fought not for one <hi>ſect</hi> or <hi>conſcience,</hi> but (as to <hi>Religion</hi>) againſt <hi>tyranny,</hi> and <hi>perſecution</hi> of <hi>any conſcience?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Till then, the <hi>Balance</hi> turned not, and our <hi>Armies</hi> could hardly be ſaid to <hi>proſper:</hi> And ever ſince, they never did <hi>but proſper;</hi> and, I verily believe, <hi>ſtill</hi> ſhall, and the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and the <hi>Parliament</hi> thereof ſtill <hi>flouriſh,</hi> till that <hi>fatal hour,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:118103:7"/>when they ſhall ceaſe to <hi>break the yokes,</hi> (<hi>ſoul-yokes</hi> eſpecially) and to let the <hi>oppreſſed go free.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One of the greateſt <hi>Knots</hi> this day in <hi>England,</hi> concerns the <hi>riſing</hi> of <hi>this</hi> Parliament, and the <hi>ſitting</hi> of the <hi>next.</hi> I confeſs, <hi>Alexander</hi>'s <hi>ſword</hi> will cut all <hi>Gordian</hi> knots, but none but the <hi>finger</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>intereſt</hi> will untie them. There was none in heaven, nor earth, nor under the earth, that could <hi>open the ſeals;</hi> but the <hi>Lamb</hi> did. The ſame bleſſed <hi>Lamb of God,</hi> and the <hi>intereſt</hi> of <hi>ſoul-freedom</hi> to <hi>all men,</hi> can,<note place="margin">One of the greateſt knots this day in <hi>England,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied.</note> and can onely maintain this <hi>Commonweal</hi> in the <hi>free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> of it: for,</p>
            <p>Who but <hi>ſoul-oppreſſors</hi> can be unwilling that mens <hi>Conſciences</hi> be free to ſee with their own <hi>eyes,</hi> and themſelves be <hi>judges</hi> of the <hi>path</hi> they chuſe, in which they hope to finde <hi>eternal life</hi> and <hi>Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who but <hi>Tyrants</hi> and <hi>Oppreſſors</hi> can be grieved, that the <hi>ſouls</hi> of men ſhould chuſe whom to <hi>hear,</hi> what and with whom to <hi>pray,</hi> whom and how to <hi>pay</hi> and <hi>maintain,</hi> according to their Abilities and Conſciences?</p>
            <p>Who but ſuch as <hi>buy</hi> and <hi>ſell</hi> Chriſt Jeſus, and make a <hi>trade</hi> and <hi>living</hi> of Heaven and Hell, can cry out, <hi>Great is Diana,</hi> for hours and yeers toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</p>
            <p>Will not <hi>all</hi> the people of the Nation ſtand ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged,<note place="margin">The onely woy (according to God) of obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the people of this Nation to the preſent Government and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours.</note> as <hi>one man,</hi> to live and die with ſuch <hi>Saviours</hi> and <hi>Deliverers,</hi> and to elect and chuſe ſuch <hi>Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> of their <hi>ſpiritual Freedoms?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How will <hi>all men</hi> be enforced (either from the freedom of their <hi>conſciences,</hi> or from the freedom of their <hi>purſes</hi> (which is their due) I ſay, be obliged
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118103:8"/>and enforced to ſend ſuch Repreſentatives as have ſtood for, and may maintain the Common Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and Liberties (eſpecially the <hi>ſoul</hi>-freedoms) of the <hi>Commonweal</hi> of <hi>England?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againſt many <hi>Objections,</hi> I briefly oppoſe my <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer</hi> to theſe two and twenty <hi>Questions:</hi> onely to one <hi>Objection,</hi> thus,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> That I <hi>anſwer</hi> with <hi>Quections.</hi> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Firſt, it was frequent with our <hi>Founder,</hi> Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in <hi>juſtice,</hi> this <hi>Re-examiner</hi> cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe his <hi>own coyn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I confeſs, my Principle of <hi>Soul-freedom</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands me to <hi>applaud</hi> and <hi>honour</hi> this <hi>ſearching</hi> and <hi>propoſing</hi> from the holy Scripture: yet ſince the <hi>Sun of righteouſneſs</hi> is riſen ſo high (as to <hi>ſoul-freedom</hi>) and darts the <hi>beams</hi> of his Light upon the very eyes of all that love his Name (eſpecially) I plead for a more gentle cenſure, if in any <hi>line</hi> or <hi>letter</hi> I ſpeak too loud to ſuch a moſt <hi>unſeaſonable ſleeper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſum of the firſt Queſtion.</p>
            <p>Whether the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>1</label> who knows the Doctrine of Salvation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be not bound, as a <hi>nurſing father,</hi> to provide <hi>ſaving food</hi> for the people, and to provide that <hi>poyſon</hi> be kept from them?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I anſwer,<note place="margin">The prophecie of Kings and Queens nurſing fathers and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note> and ask, firſt, Whether this Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Queens</hi> being <hi>nurſing fathers and nurſing mothers</hi> to the Saints, be not (as many wiſe and godly take it) a <hi>peculiar</hi> prophecie and promiſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118103:8"/>to that <hi>peculiar</hi> and <hi>distinct</hi> Nation and People of God, the Jews: And whether theſe words (verſ. 22 of that 49 of <hi>Iſaiah</hi>) <hi>I will lift up mine band to the Gentiles,</hi> &amp;c. be not a <hi>character</hi> fixing this Prophecie unto that (yet) beloved people?</p>
            <p>And ſo conſequently, Whether all thoſe bloody Perſecutors (Papiſts and Proteſtants) who have uſed to draw this <hi>ſhaft</hi> out of this <hi>Quiver</hi> of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, whereby to pierce the tender <hi>heart</hi> of Chriſt Jeſus; yea and all that give a power to the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate</hi> in <hi>Spirituals</hi> from this Scripture, Have not moſt ignorantly profaned this Prophecie, and that to <hi>uſurpation</hi> over the <hi>Temple of God,</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of Gods own people; and to bloody <hi>vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence</hi> againſt their Bodies, although under a cloak of providing <hi>wholeſome food</hi> for their children, and prohibiting <hi>poyſon?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ask, Whether there be not two ſorts of Nurſes, <hi>literal</hi> and <hi>myſtical;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fathers, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Nurſes, distinguiſhed.</note> and again of <hi>myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> two ſorts, <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Spiritual?</hi> as alſo, Whether there be not the ſame diſtinction of <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Mothers,</hi> who are diſtinct from <hi>Nurſes?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And whether theſe <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Queens</hi> (in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.) yea and ſuppoſe all other lawful Magiſtrates, muſt needs be underſtood to be <hi>ſpiritual Nurſes,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Paul</hi> (who was no <hi>King,</hi> &amp;c.) profeſſeth himſelf to be, being a <hi>Meſſenger</hi> of Chriſt Jeſus to the <hi>Theſſalonians;</hi> and ſpiritual <hi>fathers</hi> and <hi>mothers,</hi> ſuch as he profeſs'd he was to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> and <hi>Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or, Whether here is not propheſied and promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to this People; or rather, whether is there not here propheſied and promiſed to theſe Saints (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118103:9"/>
               <hi>literal</hi> or <hi>ſpiritual Iews</hi>) that <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Queens</hi> ſhall put off their <hi>Lion-like</hi> and <hi>Lion ſs-like</hi> nature towards Gods people, and ſhall be (as the <hi>Poets</hi> uſed to write good Kings ought to be) ſhepherds of the people, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If this be not the true meaning, I aske why is it ſaid,<note place="margin">Wonderful ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour that Kings and Queens ſhall yeeld to the Sain's.</note> verſe 23, That theſe Kings and Queens, ſhall <hi>bow down</hi> to theſe <hi>Iewes</hi> with their <hi>Face</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the <hi>Earth,</hi> and like the <hi>duſt</hi> of their <hi>feet?</hi> which <hi>poſture</hi> and <hi>practice</hi> ſeems not to imply a diſrobing themſelves of their civil <hi>Dignities</hi> and <hi>Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> (for that is it by which they ſhew ſuch kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the Saints) but rather, their high eſteem unto theſe Saints, in heavenly and <hi>ſoul</hi> matters; and that in <hi>ſpiritual</hi> reſpects they are ſo far from chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenging to be <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Iudges</hi> of what is whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome <hi>food</hi> and <hi>poyſon,</hi> that they bow downe and kiſſe the feet of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> in his Saints, far more ſuperiour in <hi>ſpirituals</hi> then themſelves.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">Kings and Queens, and all Magiſtrates <hi>eſſentially Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,</hi> and as a Maſter of a Ship, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> I aske whether the Office of Kings and Queens, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be not (in the <hi>ſhip</hi> of all Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weals in the world) meerly and eſſentially <hi>Civil,</hi> juſt as the Office of a Captain, or Maſter of a Ship at Sea, who ought of all his Paſſengers to be honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and reſpected, paid and rewarded for his <hi>ſervice:</hi> But as to the <hi>Conſciences</hi> of the Paſſengers, whether Jews, Turks, Perſians, Pagans, Papiſts, Proteſtants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whom he tranſports from Port to Port upon a <hi>civil</hi> account of <hi>payment</hi> and <hi>recompence;</hi> I ask whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he go not beyond the Sphere of his <hi>Activity,</hi> if he act by any authoritative <hi>reſtraining</hi> them from their <hi>own Worſhip,</hi> or <hi>conſtraining</hi> them to <hi>his?</hi> And whether he have any more to do, but a ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118103:9"/>kindneſs and countenance, according to the quality and temper of his owne <hi>Beliefe</hi> and <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, I ask,<note place="margin">Idolatrous and Popiſh Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates as law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful as, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Whether all <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> in the world (of what <hi>quality</hi> and <hi>conſcience</hi> ſoever) be not as true and lawful <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> as he that is moſt truly <hi>Godly</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> like as Idolatrous and <hi>Pagan Fathers, Husbands, Masters,</hi> are as truly ſuch in their Relations, <hi>&amp;c?</hi> Whether doth not the holy Teſtament of <hi>Christ Ieſus</hi> acknowledge this? the <hi>Lord Ieſus,</hi> both by his word and practice, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding <hi>obedience, honour, maintenance,</hi> for their Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil relations and work ſake?</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Whether Kings and Queens,<note place="margin">The People of each Nation the fountain of the Government of it.</note> and other Princes, receive not all their <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Anthority</hi> from the ſeveral and reſpective <hi>Peoples</hi> who call them and impower them to their ſeveral and reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive <hi>Services?</hi> Accordingly, Whether it have not been declared by the <hi>Parliament,</hi> that the <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> and <hi>original</hi> of all <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Rule,</hi> is the <hi>People,</hi> conſenting and agreeing in their ſeveral <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binations,</hi> by <hi>themſelves</hi> or their <hi>Deputies,</hi> for their better ſubſiſtence in <hi>Peace?</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">Power of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Spirituals detected to be but uſurpation in Kings and Queens, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> And conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Whether have the Nations and People of the world, in their meer <hi>natural</hi> and <hi>national</hi> capacities, any one jot of <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Divine</hi> power, with which to betruſt their Magiſtrates and Officers? And if, upon due weighing in the <hi>Balance of the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary,</hi> it be found that they have not, Is not this chalenging of Spiritual power to judge and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine what is <hi>ſoul-food</hi> and <hi>ſoul-peyſon,</hi> (I mean, in a <hi>coercive</hi> way binding <hi>all</hi> ſouls, and the very ſouls of <hi>them that ſent them,</hi> and who neither did nor could
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118103:10"/>commit <hi>ſuch</hi> Power unto them) Is not this, I ſay, a <hi>ſoul-rape,</hi> and <hi>tyranny,</hi> and a meer <hi>policy</hi> of Satan, deceiving (too often) honeſt and zealous mindes, but moſt commonly acting the ſubtil <hi>Ieroboams</hi> and <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> of the world, to erect their <hi>State-Calves</hi> and <hi>Images?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Admit ſome Kings &amp; Queens thus to have been impower'd by God, in ſome juncture of time, either for the Jews ſake,<note place="margin">Few Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates in the world (ſaving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) know Christ Jeſus.</note> or any of his people, upon ſome eſpecial and extraordinary account; yet I ask, What is this to all Kings, and Queens, and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates in the world, that it ſhould be their <hi>charge, duty,</hi> and <hi>calling,</hi> impoſed upon them from Heaven? when the <hi>counſel of God</hi> is revealed, that as his flock is a <hi>little flock,</hi> and that he appointed <hi>ſpiritual Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Shepherds</hi> for the feeding of them; ſo his holy purpoſe was to call <hi>few wiſe, few noble, few mighty,</hi> to the ſaving knowledge of Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, If the counſel of Chriſt Jeſus had been otherwiſe, and that he had committed (as is pleaded) the <hi>judging</hi> of <hi>ſoul-food</hi> and <hi>poyſon,</hi> to the Kings and Queens,<note place="margin">Chriſt Jeſus rarely ſends godly Kings, Queens, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſince he wanted not <hi>power,</hi> (for <hi>all power in heaven and earth</hi> was his) nor <hi>love</hi> and <hi>faithfulneſs,</hi> (for <hi>he laid down his life,</hi> and <hi>poured out his heare-blood</hi> for his;) I ask, Why in the firſt three hundred yeers (under the <hi>Romane Emperours</hi>) nor in the ſecond and third three hundred, (under <hi>Emperours</hi> and <hi>Popes</hi>) nor ever ſince, he hath not been pleaſed to furniſh the world with <hi>ſuch Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds,</hi> but rather permitted <hi>Wolves,</hi> and <hi>Lions?</hi> &amp;c. notwithſtanding that he is pleaſed ſometimes (after long and ſharp <hi>perſecutions,</hi> to ſtir up ſome bleſſed <hi>inſtruments,</hi> as Rocks and Trees, Fathers, Mothers,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118103:10"/>Nurſes, to refreſh, and ſhade, and comfort, and countenance his ſervants.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, When it hath pleaſed him graciouſly to <hi>call</hi> and <hi>change,</hi> by his Word and Spirit, any of the <hi>Wiſe,</hi> and <hi>Noble,</hi> and <hi>Mighty of the world;</hi> I ask, Whether their Regeneration and New-birth hath made any addition to their Civil Magiſtracie and Authority; and more eſpecially (as <hi>Popiſh</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Rabbins</hi> have taught us) that now the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Magiſtrate</hi> he muſt judge in <hi>ſpiritual matters</hi> more then <hi>all</hi> the Magiſtrates in the world beſide; who though (ſay they) they have equal <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Duty,</hi> yet they ought to ſuſpend acting in Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuals (ſaith M. <hi>Cotton</hi>) until they be <hi>rightly informed,</hi> that is, upon the point, until they be of <hi>his Church</hi> and <hi>Conſcience?</hi> And if ſo,<note place="margin">A Magiſtrate is not more or leſs a Magiſtrate, by being a Chriſtian or Antichriſtian.</note> that by this profeſſing <hi>Christianity,</hi> they receive this addition of <hi>Magiſterial</hi> power in <hi>Spirituals;</hi> I ask if it do not clearly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that (according to that moſt <hi>dangerous</hi> and <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious</hi> doctrine of ſome Papiſts and Proteſtants) ſuch Magiſtrates who <hi>change</hi> their judgements and way of Worſhip, muſt loſe their <hi>Headſhip</hi> in Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuals, and conſequently be found unfit at laſt to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern in Civils alſo?</p>
            <p>And will not this doctrine extend to <hi>all other</hi> Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Officers, both at Land and Sea; yea, even to all <hi>Fathers, Husbands, Maſters;</hi> and ſo at laſt confound all <hi>Relations,</hi> and tear up by the roots all <hi>Civility,</hi> and all <hi>Order,</hi> and the <hi>world</hi> out of the <hi>world?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ninthly, As to the <hi>matter of fact,</hi> do not all <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories</hi> and all <hi>experience</hi> demonſtrate, that moſt of all thoſe Kings, and Queens, and Princes, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates (Popiſh and Proteſtant) that have pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118103:11"/>to this power of judging of <hi>ſaving food</hi> and <hi>poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">All Magiſttrates pretending pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in ſpirimals, have ever forced down poyſon in ſsead of food.</note> have groſly miſtaken the poyſon of <hi>Satans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertions, Superſtitions, Will-worſhips,</hi> &amp;c. for that <hi>wholeſome</hi> and <hi>heavenly food</hi> pretended; and with bloody hands have <hi>forced</hi> this <hi>poyſon</hi> down the throat of thouſands and millions, or elſe forced and fired them out of the world with <hi>barbarous perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> if any have been enlightned by <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> to diſcern this poyſon, and to refuſe it?</p>
            <p>Hath not Chriſt Jeſus, in theſe laſt times, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it, that neither <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> nor the <hi>good Emperors</hi> before the <hi>Popes</hi> roſe, nor <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Kings, Queens, and Magiſtrates departing from the Pope unto this day, but have been ſtill miſtaken moſt groſly (either in <hi>Doctrine</hi> or <hi>Diſcipline</hi>) and that in great quantities (ſometimes) of <hi>dangerous poyſon,</hi> for <hi>ſaving</hi> and <hi>wholeſome food?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What man,<note place="margin">From <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> to the laſt Presbyterian Magiſtrate.</note> but may furniſh himſelf with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, even down to the very <hi>Presbyterian Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy?</hi> And whoever ſhall next pretend to judge between this <hi>poyſon</hi> and <hi>food,</hi> and put forth a <hi>reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> or a <hi>Conſtraining Sword</hi> accordingly, How is it poſſible but they muſt alſO daſh upon thoſe Rocks, whereon the very <hi>Tyde</hi> of ſuch a practice doth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily inforce ſo many <hi>gallant Sbips</hi> miſcarriage? Therefore (laſtly) ſince that typical land of <hi>Canaan</hi> is aboliſhed, the <hi>Partition-wall</hi> broken down, and <hi>in every nation</hi> (not <hi>Whole nations</hi>) <hi>he that feareth God and worketh rirghteouſneſs, is accepted with him,</hi> Acts 10. ſince <hi>Magistracy</hi> is a meerly-<hi>Civil Ordinance,</hi> and the <hi>forms</hi> and <hi>ſword</hi> thereof derived from the <hi>People;</hi> and all <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> in the world (ſo derived) are law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and none can receive any <hi>addition</hi> to the power
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118103:11"/>of Magiſtracie, by his (<hi>ſpirituality</hi> or) <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> I ask, Whether this doctrine of Kings and Queens <hi>judging</hi> of <hi>ſoul-food</hi> and <hi>poyſon</hi> for all their ſubjects,<note place="margin">The doctrine of Kings &amp; queent being nurſing fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, the Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand of the world.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> hath not been (e!pecially in <hi>Popiſh</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Nations) the <hi>Fire-brand</hi> that hath kindled ſo many <hi>devouring flames</hi> of <hi>War?</hi> &amp;c. Yea, was not this the very Doctrine that coſt the late King <hi>Charles</hi> his <hi>Crown,</hi> and <hi>life?</hi> who being flattered and bewitched into this <hi>dream</hi> of a <hi>Nurſing father,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Ax that cut off the laſt King's head.</note> and a <hi>judge</hi> of <hi>wholeſome food</hi> and <hi>poyſon</hi> for his people; he forced <hi>poyſon</hi> for <hi>food</hi> upon the <hi>Scotch</hi> nation, and upon that occaſion was perſwaded to maintain his <hi>ſtew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> and <hi>cooks,</hi> the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> by commencing and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting thoſe <hi>fatal Wars,</hi> which (by a naked hand from heaven) juſtly pluckt up <hi>root and branch,</hi> both <hi>Ceremonles, Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>King</hi> together.</p>
            <p>The ſum of the ſecond Queſtion.</p>
            <p>Whether the magiſtrate be not bound to advance the doctrine of Grace, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>2. and 3.</label> which doth advance the peace and proſperity of a Nation?</p>
            <p>Of which nature is the third Queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether a Magiſtrate be not bound to advance that Godlineſs which giveth all good and happineſs to a nation?</p>
            <p>I anſwer, and ask, (as before) Whether, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> ſince Civil Magiſtracie is <hi>meerly civil,</hi> and the power thereof derived from the <hi>People,</hi> the <hi>fountain</hi> of it; it will not appear, that the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> can no more
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118103:12"/>judge authoritatively what is <hi>the doctrine of Grace,</hi> &amp; what is the <hi>doctrine</hi> of <hi>Godlineſs,</hi> no more (I ſay) then the people of each <hi>Nation,</hi> in its <hi>national</hi> and <hi>natural</hi> capacity, can be the primitive and original <hi>Iudges</hi> thereof, and may therefore rightly delegate ſuch a Spiritual power unto their <hi>Officers</hi> or <hi>Magiſtrates?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, I ask, Whether the propoſer of theſe Queſtions intendeth not, by the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the doctrine of <hi>Grace,</hi> and the doctrine of <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs,</hi> theſe two things:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A <hi>National</hi> profeſſion of the doctrine of <hi>Grace,</hi> and the doctrine of <hi>Godlineſs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The advancing of ſuch doctrines by the power of the <hi>civil Sword?</hi> And if ſo, (as the ſcope of all the <hi>Queſtions</hi> ſeem to imply) then,</item>
            </list>
            <p>Thirdly, Whether there be any ſuch thing to be found in the laſt Will and <hi>Teſtament</hi> of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> as a <hi>National Church;</hi> that is, whether (as the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> was a Land <hi>holy</hi> unto <hi>God,</hi> ſo) any <hi>Nation,</hi> as a Nation, may lawfully pretend to be the <hi>Spouſe,</hi> and <hi>Wife,</hi> and <hi>Body</hi> of Chriſt Jeſus, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his own holy Order and Appointment? Or rather,</p>
            <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">The world (and <hi>Eng and</hi> in a national reſpect) lies in wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</note> Whether, ſince <hi>the world lieth in wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, dead in ſins and treſpaſſes,</hi> &amp;c. ſince every Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the world is a part of it; ſince <hi>ſuch as fear God</hi> in a nation, are <hi>diſtinguiſhed</hi> from the Nation, (<hi>Act.</hi> 10) I ask, Whether this <hi>Nation,</hi> as a part of the <hi>World,</hi> lieth not in the ſame eſtate of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs alſo, more or leſs, and the <hi>body</hi> of the people eſtranged from the life of <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>godlineſs,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that this <hi>body</hi> be ſometimes clothed with the name of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> under (ſometimes) a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118103:12"/>
               <hi>Popiſh,</hi> and ſometimes a <hi>Proteſtant faſhion,</hi> as it pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth God to permit the <hi>Sword</hi> to pretend to and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance its way of doctrine of <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>godlineſs?</hi> And whether, beſide the <hi>common nature</hi> of mankind,<note place="margin">Four greatchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in abous <hi>12</hi> yeers ſpace, in <hi>Hen. 8. Edw. 6.</hi> Qu <hi>Mary,</hi> and Qu. <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
               </note> the wonderfull <hi>changes</hi> of Religion in <hi>other</hi> Nations, and in none more then in <hi>this,</hi> and that in the ſame individual perſons, in a few yeers, do not make this undeniably evident and demonſtrate?</p>
            <p>For illuſtration, I ask, ſhether the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Queens, Parliaments</hi> and <hi>princes</hi> of <hi>all nations,</hi> and of <hi>this,</hi> have not been the <hi>Gods</hi> of the Nations,<note place="margin">Kings <hi>&amp;</hi> Queens <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Gods of people; and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liegions their pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures in which themſelves are worſhipped.</note> whom they have werſhipped in and by the ſeveral <hi>Images</hi> and <hi>Repreſentations</hi> of their mindes and wills, which they have ſet up as ways of <hi>Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> to the Nations? Thus <hi>Ieroboam</hi> pretends the Name of the God of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> but, upon the point, <hi>Ieroboam</hi> was their God, and robb'd the <hi>true</hi> God of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, by the <hi>golen calves</hi> which <hi>Ieroboam</hi> had ſet up. Thus <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> pretends honour to his <hi>golden Image;</hi> but <hi>himſelf</hi> was really the <hi>Deity</hi> which all Nations worſhipped, through the <hi>golden Image</hi> which he had ſet up.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, I ask, Whether <hi>God people</hi> (that is, ſuch as fear <hi>God</hi> in every <hi>nation, Act.</hi> 10.) be not the true, and proper, and only <hi>Antitype</hi> of that ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pical <hi>Nation</hi> the <hi>Jewes,</hi> in that typical land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> according to 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. You are a choſen Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration (as <hi>Abraham</hi> and his off-ſpring in the <hi>Type</hi> were) a <hi>Kingly Prieſthood,</hi> and <hi>holy Nation? &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">A National Church is Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daiſm.</note> And therefore I aske, Whether, to modellize a Body or <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> with <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>National</hi> bounds and circuits (after the pattern of the <hi>typical</hi> Land of <hi>Canaan</hi>) be not to dwell in the old <hi>Levitical</hi> ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118103:13"/>in the A.B.C. and <hi>Horn-book</hi> of <hi>Judaiſm,</hi> and in the denial of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> to be yet come?</p>
            <p>To this end, I ask, Whether ſome <hi>Presbyterians</hi> (in forraign parts) come not neerer to the truth of the firſt <hi>Chriſtian worſhip,</hi> who admit not one of ten or twenty to be of their <hi>Churches:</hi> And the <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents</hi> yet neerer, who admit onely ſuch in their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties, in whom they hopefully ſee the Spirit of <hi>Regeneration</hi> and <hi>Holineſs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>sixthly, I ask, Whether there hath not been in all Ages of the world, and are at this day, many great and mighty <hi>Nations</hi> of the <hi>World</hi> (ſome of ſome hundreds, yea of ſome thouſands of years continuance and flouriſhing) in which the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Flouriſhing States of the World in which Chriſt Ieſus is not heard of, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> and the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Godlineſs</hi> hath not been (I am ſure not <hi>nationally</hi>) advanced? And notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that <hi>Godlineſs</hi> hath promiſes belonging to this life, as well as to the life approaching, and the <hi>God</hi> of heaven is pleaſed to imprint a <hi>Character</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> of his favour and love upon ſome <hi>Perſons</hi> and <hi>Actions,</hi> when his name is greatly engaged (as in <hi>Queen Elizabeth</hi> her daies againſt the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> and in our late <hi>Wars</hi> both againſt <hi>EngliſH, Scotch,</hi> and <hi>Iriſh,</hi> yet) whether it be not generally and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily true, that all that will live godly in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> muſt be perſecuted or hunted; and the more <hi>Godly,</hi> the more perſecuted? and according to the <hi>myſtery</hi> of the fifth Seal, the Souls under the <hi>Altar</hi> muſt reſt but until the reſt of their fellow-ſervants are ſlain, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is it not (upon the matter) a <hi>Turkiſh</hi> argument,<note place="margin">The peate and proſperity of Gods people in this world, is ſpiritual, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> We have conquered ſo many <hi>Nations, Kingdoms,</hi> &amp;c. Therefore <hi>Mahomes</hi> is above <hi>Chriſt?</hi> And alſo, is it
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118103:13"/>nota <hi>Popiſh</hi> plea, All <hi>Nations</hi> have bowed down to our <hi>Church,</hi> who ſits as a <hi>Queen;</hi> therefore it is the onely true, <hi>&amp;c. God</hi> hath given the <hi>Weſtern Mines</hi> of <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Silver</hi> to the <hi>Catholicks,</hi> not to the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants;</hi> and to the <hi>Spaniards</hi> before the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> (who had the firſt offer; therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Since then that <hi>National</hi> and <hi>typical holineſs,</hi> with all the annexed outward peace and proſperity, promiſed upon condition, is vaniſhed, and the <hi>Lord Ieſus,</hi> by his <hi>Birth</hi> in a <hi>ſtable</hi> and his <hi>Death</hi> on a <hi>Gallowes,</hi> hath taught all his followers to deſpiſe this <hi>Worlds Goods</hi> and this <hi>Worlds Evils;</hi> how ſhould his <hi>Saints</hi> ſtudy the difference between the Tenour of the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New Covenant,</hi> the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> and the <hi>Chriſtian Canaan,</hi> and at laſt finde out that peace and proſperity they ſpeak of, in thoſe ſpiritual <hi>pleaſures, Beauties, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, Riches, Ioyes,</hi> which are even in this preſent <hi>life</hi> un ſpeakable and full of <hi>Glory?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Eightly, Since the <hi>Throne</hi> is upholden by <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mercy to the perſecuted, the upholder of States.</note> 
               <hi>Prov.</hi> 20. and both the holy <hi>ſcriptures</hi> and <hi>Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> tell us how many <hi>Thrones</hi> of <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>States,</hi> that ſeemed to have been placed among the <hi>ſtars,</hi> are tumbled downe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I aske if it be not at laſt the <hi>wiſdome</hi> of this <hi>State,</hi> to tremble at the <hi>ſhipwracks</hi> and downfull of our <hi>Predeceſſors,</hi> and to learne not onely the ſong of <hi>judgement</hi> and <hi>Zeal</hi> (as we judge) for the doctrine of <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>godlineſs,</hi> but the ſong of <hi>mercy</hi> alſo to ſuch whoſe <hi>Conſciences</hi> (whether out of a <hi>ſlaviſh</hi> or <hi>child like awe</hi> of God, are (it my be) <hi>Antipodes</hi> to ours? To ſay nothing of all <hi>former examples,</hi> are not <hi>two</hi> moſt wonderful before our eyes and fee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>?</p>
            <p>Firſt, ſhat was it that within the memory of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118103:14"/>man hath ſo wonderfully (almoſt miraculouſly) raiſed and advanced from the low <hi>valleys,</hi> that poor <hi>fiſher-town</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> (now one of the gallanteſt of the <hi>Lady</hi> Cities of the world? I ſay, What was it but <hi>Mercy, Mercy</hi> which that poor <hi>Fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>town</hi> ſhewed to <hi>diſtreſſed</hi> and <hi>perſecuted conſciences,</hi> who fled from <hi>Enchuyſin</hi> and other <hi>perſecuting parts</hi> thither?</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">The riſe of this State and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monweal.</note> What was it (as before) that pluckt up the <hi>roots</hi> and <hi>foundations</hi> of <hi>ſo many Thrones</hi> of late a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our ſelves, and lift up and exalted our preſent <hi>State</hi> and <hi>States-men,</hi> but <hi>mercy</hi> to the long-oppreſſed ſouls of men, amongſt whom <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> (who will not ſuffer <hi>a cup of water,</hi> given to his, to paſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paid for) hath been favoured and relieved? <hi>Break off thy ſins by righteouſneſs, and thine iniquitiess by ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mercy to the poor, if it may be a lengthing to thy tranquility:</hi> For,</p>
            <p>Are not <hi>falſe Worſhips,</hi> as to <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Tyranny</hi> as to men, the two Generals, under whoſe bloody colours the moſt Sins and Plagues, in all the Nations of the <hi>World,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hollands great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſin as to Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and.</note> have ever marched? I queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on not, but <hi>Ambition</hi> and <hi>Pride, Covetuouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Greedtneſs Ingratitude</hi> and <hi>Unthanfulneſs Exceſs</hi> and <hi>Drunkenneſs,</hi> now lodge in the new-raiſ'd <hi>Towers</hi> of the aforeſaid <hi>Fiſher-Towne.</hi> But 'tis that Sin of <hi>Sodom,</hi> the not ſtrengthning the hand of the poor, the Poor oppreſſed in <hi>England,</hi> op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed both in their <hi>ſpiritual</hi> and <hi>temporal</hi> liberties, and their late notorious ſtrengthning the hand of Oppreſſours, the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Cavaliers</hi> that ſin (I ſay) if any, will ſtaine the pride of all their riſing <hi>Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:118103:14"/>
            <p>But are there not the <hi>cries</hi> of the <hi>oppreſſed</hi> aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the heavens againſt us alſo? (to ſay nothing of the many other particulars of Soul-<hi>Violence</hi> and <hi>Oppreſſion,</hi> which ſome have reckoned up yet ſtill in <hi>England</hi>) I ask, if ever ſuch cries went up to <hi>Heaven</hi> in the late <hi>Kings Reigne,</hi> or his <hi>Fathers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The oppreſſion of Tythes now greater in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> then for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, (I hope) before their downfal.</note> or all the long tyranny of <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Biſhops, from ſuch, whoſe either conſciences or neceſſities, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not permit them to practice that notorious <hi>Iudaiſm</hi> of <hi>Tythes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Nonconformers</hi> (it's true) were <hi>ſued,</hi> and <hi>caſt,</hi> and <hi>paid;</hi> but they were never ſo torn with the three-tooth'd <hi>Hook</hi> of <hi>Elies</hi> SOns, the <hi>Treble</hi> da ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and oppreſſions.</p>
            <p>I as therefore, ſhat <hi>Grace,</hi> what <hi>Godlineſs</hi> that is, that teacheth us, after all our our former ſins, and judgements, and deliverances, and vows, to ſtop our Eares from the oppreſſed, their Cries, their Teares, their Conſciences, and to imagine that our <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monweal,</hi> our <hi>parliament,</hi> our <hi>Counſel,</hi> our <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monweal,</hi> our <hi>parliament,</hi> our <hi>Counſel,</hi> our <hi>Army,</hi> our <hi>Navy</hi> muſt proſper, in our moſt knowne op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſings of <hi>Him,</hi> whoſe is all power in <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> the Son of <hi>God Christ Ieſus?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſum of the fourth Queſtion.</p>
            <p>Whether the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>4</label> he not bound to love God, and to advance his <hi>Glory,</hi> true worſhip and ſervice, and the good of his people, with all his <hi>might?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ask, Whether (as before) the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Civil officer</hi> of the People, hath any <hi>Might,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:118103:15"/>
               <hi>Authority,</hi> or <hi>Power,</hi> but what the People commit unto him? And Whether any People will or can betruſt ſuch a <hi>Power</hi> to the <hi>civil magiſtrate,</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel their Souls and <hi>conſciences</hi> unto his?</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">Spiritual wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons and carnal, compared.</note> Whether the <hi>Spirit of God</hi> ſpeak not expreſly that the Weapons of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are not <hi>Sword</hi> and <hi>Might,</hi> but the <hi>Spirit?</hi> and whether his <hi>Spiritual Weapons</hi> (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.) be not ſufficiently and abundantly able and <hi>mighty,</hi> to bring down every ſtrong <hi>hold,</hi> and every high <hi>thing,</hi> and every <hi>imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> and <hi>thought</hi> to the obedience of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt?</hi> And Whether ever any carnal <hi>might</hi> ever did or can effect ought in <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> but the ſtorming of the Nations into an <hi>Antichriſtian Hypocriſie</hi> and <hi>Compliance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">The woful ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of carnal weapons in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituals.</note> Whether this <hi>Principle</hi> of the <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates</hi> putting forth his <hi>carnal might</hi> in ſpirituals, hath not conſtantly occaſioned the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the miſtakes of his owne <hi>conſcience</hi>) to promote <hi>Superſtition</hi> and <hi>Idolatry;</hi> And alſo hath rendred the ſtrongeſt <hi>ſword</hi> to be the meaſure and ſtandard of all <hi>Religion</hi> in the <hi>World;</hi> and the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates</hi> thereof, the <hi>Nimrods</hi> and mighty <hi>Hunters</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Lord?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, I ask, Where <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> (the onely <hi>Law-giver</hi> to <hi>Christians</hi> hath appointed in his holy <hi>Teſtament,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chriſt Jeſus not forgetful to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh his kingdom with ſpiritual weapons.</note> the <hi>civil ſwrod</hi> the <hi>judge</hi> and <hi>defender</hi> of his <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Worſhip?</hi> And why he hath not furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his <hi>civil Magiſtrates</hi> of <hi>Iuſtice</hi> in the <hi>World</hi> with ſuch <hi>hearts</hi> and <hi>ſpirits,</hi> but contrarily hath call'd few of them to the profeſſion of his Name? And whether he hath not ever furniſhed, and doth, and will, his <hi>ſpiritual Miniſters</hi> and <hi>Meſſengers</hi> with
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118103:15"/>
               <hi>ſpiritual</hi> might and power, ſufficiently and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly efficacious for the propagating of his holy <hi>Name</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi> and for the confounding of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt</hi> and all <hi>Antichriſtians</hi> by the breath of his Mouth, that two edged Sword of his <hi>Spirit?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, Whether <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> did ever ſo flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh,<note place="margin">The ſirſt and laſt times of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> conſidered.</note> as when the people of <hi>God</hi> in the firſt 300 yers after <hi>Chriſt,</hi> had no might but that of Chriſts ſpiritual <hi>weapons?</hi> Ans when it pleaſed <hi>God</hi> to raiſe up <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> to give ſome reſt to his people from <hi>perſecution;</hi> whether <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> did moſt flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in the firſt time of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> when he with his Colleageue <hi>Licinius</hi> publiſhed the edict of Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Religion</hi> to hisſubjects; or in his after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, when he compell'd all the <hi>World</hi> to <hi>Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> but (as is confeſt by many) occaſioned the <hi>World</hi> to put on the bare and empty name of <hi>Chriſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I ask, Whether this <hi>Principle</hi> of the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates</hi> employing the carnal <hi>ſword</hi> or <hi>Might</hi> in <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituals,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Carnal ſword an Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuats, the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſo much bloodſhed in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and in our late Wars.</note> have not in all <hi>Hiſtories</hi> and <hi>Experience</hi> been the <hi>Firebrand</hi> which hath kindled ſuch devouring flames of <hi>War</hi> about <hi>Religion,</hi> in all both <hi>Popiſh</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Countries? And Whether it did not kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle our late <hi>Wars,</hi> and occaſion all the dreadfull <hi>Calamities,</hi> between the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and the <hi>Presbyters,</hi> which proved fatal to the both? And whether all theſe <hi>Experiences</hi> are not the voice of <hi>God</hi> out of the whirlwind, to waken all the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> to keep within the Civil ſphere of Civil <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> and <hi>Deminion?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:118103:16"/>
            <p>The ſum of the fifth Queſtion.</p>
            <p>Whether the people be not bound to pray for <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>5</label> that under them we may live a peaceable and quiet life in all <hi>Godlineſs</hi> and <hi>Honeſty</hi> and whether the Magiſtrate is not bound to do that for which the People pray? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. I ask, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> Whether (as ſome have urged) theſe words <hi>godlineſs</hi> and <hi>honeſty,</hi> be rightly tranſlated; but rather, upon a <hi>miſtake</hi> in the Tranſlation, weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made the <hi>ground</hi> for the Magiſtrates being the <hi>heeper</hi> of <hi>godlineſs</hi> in the <hi>firſt,</hi> and <hi>honeſty</hi> in the <hi>ſecond Table?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. I ask,<note place="margin">The puring and pre-eminence the firſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian times.</note> To <hi>whom</hi> this <hi>direction</hi> of <hi>praying</hi> for Magiſtrates was given? Whether they were not the <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>pureſt Saints,</hi> and thoſe times the moſt <hi>glorious,</hi> wherein the Saints enjoyed two ſuch <hi>helps</hi> as no Chriſtians ever ſince did?</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, the <hi>preſence</hi> of the holy <hi>Apoſtles</hi> or <hi>meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> of Chriſt Jeſus amongſt them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the wonderful <hi>effuſion</hi> of the holy <hi>Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God,</hi> in thoſe <hi>rare</hi> and <hi>miraculous gifts</hi> and <hi>ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations,</hi> (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.) Now to imagine that thoſe <hi>firſt</hi> Saints ſhould pray for the <hi>Civil ſword</hi> to defend (I ſpeak not of their perſons, but) their <hi>godlineſs,</hi> and ſuppreſs <hi>ungodlineſs,</hi> &amp;c. doth it not imply this twofold ſtrange and moſt unchriſtian <hi>Paradox?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">Two ſtrange Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raderes.</note> that thoſe Saints muſt imagine thoſe Civil Magiſtrates to have a clearer ſight in diſcerning,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118103:16"/>and an higher Authority in judging of <hi>Godlineſs</hi> and <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> then themſelves and the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> who are call'd expreſly the <hi>(Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial) Foundations</hi> of the <hi>Churches, Fpheſ.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That they being thus call'd of <hi>God,</hi> and indued with the Spirit of <hi>God</hi> ſo ſavingly, ſo miraculouſly, yet ſhould not be able to live in <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs</hi> and the pure profeſſion of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the help of a carnal ſword to preſerve them pure, eſtabliſh and reform them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, I ask therefore, Whether the ſcope of the holy Exhortation be not this;<note place="margin">The ſcope of <hi>1 Tim. 2.</hi> pray for Magiſtrates.</note> That thoſe firſt <hi>Believers,</hi> and all <hi>Believers</hi> in the Ages follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſhould be much in prayer with <hi>God,</hi> and not onely for themſelves, but for all men, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> the <hi>Chiefe</hi> of men?</p>
            <p n="1">1. That ſuch as were <hi>Gods Elect</hi> amongſt them might be called.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the peace of the <hi>Nation</hi> and <hi>Cities</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they lived; and ſo, conſequently, that <hi>God</hi> would gratiouſly guide the hearts of the <hi>Helms-men</hi> the <hi>Magistrates,</hi> that the ſhips of the ſeveral <hi>ſtates</hi> (wherein the Saints as <hi>Paſſengers</hi> were imbarqued) might Sail in peace and ſafety, that in the peace thereof they might have peace, (according to the command of <hi>God</hi> to his people in <hi>Babel, Ier.</hi> 29.) That ſo the Saints injoying <hi>civil peace,</hi> and alſo (if it may be the holy pleaſure of <hi>God</hi>) injoying reſt from perſecution (<hi>Act.</hi> 9.) might multiply, walking in the fear of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whatever the <hi>Religions</hi> fo the States or the magiſtrates there ſhould be, though <hi>Babylonian, Roman,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:118103:17"/>
            <p>fourthy, I ask, Whether the bleſſed <hi>Spirit</hi> of Life and Regeneration which is in all <hi>Gods</hi> people, be not abundantly ſufficient to preſerve them in <hi>Godlineſs</hi> and true <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> to preſerve them from falling, and to reform and reſtore them from all their <hi>Backſlidings</hi> and <hi>declenſions?</hi> I add, to preſerve them,<note place="margin">1 Iohn 3. Rom 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Iohn 5.</note> that ſin have no dominion over them; that they ſin not, and watch againſt the touching of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan;</hi> to preſerve them in the uſe of the <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>prayer,</hi> and all ſuch paths and meanes, which in <hi>Faith</hi> they are perſwaded of to be the commands of <hi>Chriſt ieſus?</hi>
               <note place="margin">The moſt holy and moſt pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal indwelling of Gods moſt holy Spirit in all Gods Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</note> All this, and more, the holy <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God</hi> works in <hi>Gods</hi> Children, although there ſhould not be a <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> in the <hi>World,</hi> yea although all the <hi>World</hi> and the whole <hi>World</hi> oppoſe them; yea although there were no <hi>Heaven</hi> nor <hi>Hell,</hi> no <hi>Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,</hi> no <hi>Iudgement,</hi> nor <hi>World</hi> to come, wherein they ſhould be rewarded or puniſhed, glorifyed or tormented; yea although they ſhould want all Spiritual helps and <hi>Teachers</hi> (which reſpectively are neceſſary) for they have received an <hi>Anointing,</hi> which teacheth them, and abident with them, and will abide with them for ever.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, I ask, Whether in the preſent ſtate and jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of affaires in <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The diviſions of the Clergie now, like that of the Friers in <hi>Chaucers</hi> tiem.</note> wherein (as <hi>Chaucer</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves of the four great differing Orders of <hi>Friers</hi> in his time) every <hi>Sect,</hi> every <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>conſcience</hi> pleads the integrity and purity of their way, and the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>God</hi> themſelves are ſo divided and different<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwaded, as of late (in the <hi>Scotch</hi> wars) to blood and dreadfull ſlaughters (I ſay) I ask, Whether we may pray, without prophaning of the holy Name of <hi>God,</hi> and the guilt of the breach of the <hi>civil
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118103:17"/>Peace</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> that <hi>God</hi> would ſend ſuch <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates,</hi> who ſhould authoritatively judge, whoſe <hi>Conſcience,</hi> whoſe <hi>Worſhip,</hi> whoſe <hi>Godlineſs</hi> is true,<note place="margin">What prayers ought to be put up for Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates?</note> and accordingly maintain that <hi>Godlineſs,</hi> defend that <hi>Faith,</hi> advance the <hi>Worſhip</hi> and ſervice of <hi>God, &amp;c.</hi> As alſo prohibite by his carnal <hi>Sword,</hi> all other <hi>Conſciences, Worſhips</hi> and <hi>Godlineſs,</hi> as <hi>Schiſmatical, heretical, Seditious, Blaſphemous?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>How much rather ought we to pray, that it may pleaſethe moſt holy and only wiſe <hi>Goe,</hi> to vouchſafe ſuch a <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Godlineſs</hi> and <hi>Wiſdomie</hi> to the <hi>Rulers</hi> of this <hi>Commonweal,</hi> that the <hi>civil Rights</hi> may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved and <hi>Civilities</hi> may flouriſh in <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Mercy,</hi> even in the midſt of ſo much ſpiritual <hi>Diviſion</hi> and <hi>Oppoſition,</hi> which are and muſt be grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and greater, in all <hi>Nations</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> when once the <hi>Chains</hi> and <hi>Yoaks</hi> of <hi>implicite Faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Soul Yoaks</note> believe as the <hi>Church</hi> believes, <hi>Decrees</hi> and <hi>Precepts</hi> of Men, <hi>Tradition</hi> of <hi>Elders, Cuſtomes, Antiquity,</hi> &amp;c. re torn off, and broke from the <hi>ſouls</hi> and <hi>necks</hi> of the People, and Inhabitants hereof?</p>
            <p>The ſum of the ſixth Queſtion.</p>
            <p>Whether <hi>Abraban,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>6</label> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers before the law, were not <hi>Magistrates</hi> in their Families, and commanded and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed their Families in matters of <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> or were meetly fello-Servants, with their Servants, as the Examiner ſaith?</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ask, Whether the <hi>Queſtionist</hi> hath dealt fairly with the <hi>Examiner,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> in bringing him in (ſ0
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118103:18"/>odiouſly) to ſay, that <hi>Abrahams</hi> and <hi>Jacobs</hi> Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds might command them, as well as <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> might command their Houſhoulds? And Whether or no did the Examiner once menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Iacob?</hi> It is true, he maintaineth, (and with expreſs words and clear light of holy Scripture well may) that in <hi>Religious</hi> matters the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> and <hi>Subject</hi> are fellow-Servants: but gave he any colour or appearance of <hi>Countenance</hi> to <hi>Servants</hi> to be inobſequious to their <hi>Maſters, Children</hi> to their <hi>Parents, Wives</hi> to their <hi>Husbands, people</hi> to <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> in all their civil ſpheres and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects?</p>
            <p>I ask further,<note place="margin">The diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates of Cods Iſrael, figurative and typical.</note> Is the conſequence fairly gathered, that becauſe <hi>Abraham, I ſaack,</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> and thoſe <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> of <hi>Families</hi> and <hi>Elder Brothers,</hi> thoſe <hi>Saviours, Judges, Governours,</hi> and <hi>Kings</hi> of the <hi>Iſrael</hi> and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>God,</hi> in thoſe <hi>ſigurative</hi> times and <hi>typical</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrations, commanded and puniſhed, even with a material and carnal <hi>ſword</hi> in <hi>ſpiritual</hi> matters; therefore every <hi>Maſter</hi> of a <hi>Family, Husband, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Elder brother, Judge, governour, King, Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate,</hi> hath the ſame <hi>Authority</hi> in <hi>ſpiritual</hi> matters now? And that therefore, according to <hi>Numb.</hi> 30. an <hi>Husbands</hi> or <hi>Father</hi> may now diſannul and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule the meerly Religious <hi>Vowes</hi> and <hi>Devotions</hi> of their <hi>Wives</hi> and <hi>Daughters?</hi> Or rather, ſince the <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> the ſubſtance of thoſe ſhadowes is come, Whether ti be not one expreſs end of his coming,<note place="margin">Great diviſcons in matters of Conſcience, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, &amp;c.</note> to ſet a man at variance which his <hi>Father,</hi> &amp; <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.) in a family of five perſons, to ſet two againſt three, and three againſt two; that is, in the matter of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> and <hi>Canſcience?</hi> And I ask, Whether the wife
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118103:18"/>(notwithſtanding in civil converſe ſhe ſubmit with all wife-like <hi>ſubmiſſion</hi> and <hi>affection,</hi> yet) as to <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> ought ſhe not to judge of her <hi>Husbands Beliefe</hi> or <hi>Unbelief</hi> in <hi>God?</hi> and may ſhe not joyn with him or ſeparate from him, labouring to be a Saviour to him? <hi>How knoweſt thou, O Wife, but that thou mayeſt ſave thy Husband?</hi> &amp;c. And ſo conſequently, the <hi>ſervant</hi> to his <hi>Maſter,</hi> the <hi>Child</hi> to his <hi>Parent,</hi> the <hi>ſubject</hi> and <hi>ſouldier</hi> to the higheſt <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> and <hi>Commander?</hi> For, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. <hi>there is neither Iew nor Greek, there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bond nor free, there is neither male nor female; for yea are all one in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, I ask, Whether it be not the deſigne of <hi>God</hi> (for the manifeſtation of his owne moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Brightneſs</hi>) to cary on the <hi>Myſtery</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> in the meaneſt and loweſt of <hi>Earthen Veſſels,</hi> according to that of <hi>Iames</hi> 2. <hi>Hath not God choſen the poor of this World, rich in Faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gods deſigne of chuſing men of low deeree, not many wiſe, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble nor mighty.</note> 
               <hi>and Heires of the Kingdom?</hi> Hence, in a moſt ſtupendious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcenſion, <hi>God</hi> manifeſteth himſelf in <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and that <hi>Fleſh</hi> muſt be taken from a poor <hi>Carpenters wife,</hi> and ſhe delivered of her bleſſed fruit in a <hi>ſtable</hi> amongſt <hi>Beaſts:</hi> And however he command thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand thouſands of thoſe moſt bleſſed <hi>Inviſible Spirots</hi> the <hi>Angels,</hi> yet, for his viſible attendants and Embaſſadours to the <hi>World,</hi> were they not (ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily) of a low Ranck and condition, even thoſe two <hi>Pillars</hi> whoſe names have ſo ſounded in all parts (eſpecially at <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>London</hi>) <hi>Peter</hi> the <hi>Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crman,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> the <hi>Tent-maker?</hi> Further, I ask, Whether that <hi>Rule</hi> be not conſtant in the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Profeſſion, Not many <hi>Wiſe,</hi> not many <hi>Noble,</hi> not many <hi>Mighty?</hi> And therefore, Whether it be
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118103:19"/>not againſt the purpoſe and deſigne of <hi>God,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aginſt his declared will and courſe, that his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants ſhould expect many <hi>Chriſtian</hi> great or noble perſons, many <hi>Chriſtian</hi> wife or learned men, many <hi>Chriſtian</hi> mighty men either for wealth or valour, many <hi>Chriſtian</hi> magiſtrates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence though we finde the Saints in <hi>Caeſars</hi> houſhold (<hi>Phil.</hi> 4.) yet I ask, How many <hi>Caeſars</hi> (<hi>Maſters</hi> of thoſe houſhoulds) do we finde believing in <hi>leſus,</hi> for three hundred years together? and therefore, ſhether the pooreſt <hi>Saint</hi> in the <hi>Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold</hi> or <hi>Court</hi> of theſe <hi>Caeſars,</hi> were not higher (in <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian</hi> reſpects) then thoſe <hi>Emper ours</hi> of the <hi>World</hi> themſelves?</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">A true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an who.</note> What is it that makes a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> but the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in a perſon, manifeſted in the profeſſion of his Name before the World? <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. <hi>Rom</hi> 10. And if ſo, I ask, Whether that more of the <hi>Grace</hi> and knowledge of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> render not perſons more and more eminent and glorious in <hi>Chriſtianity?</hi> And conſequently, Whether the pooreſt Subject or Servant, participating of more of the <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>ſpirit</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> be not inveſted with more of the <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">What Chriſtions the highneſt.</note> in his affaires and <hi>Kingdome,</hi> then the higheſt <hi>Magrſtrates</hi> or <hi>Superiours,</hi> that are not ſo indowed? According to that <hi>Honour</hi> of <hi>all his Saints,</hi> who (eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially) bind <hi>Kings</hi> in chains, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And that charge from <hi>Heaven, Iames</hi> 2.1. <hi>My Brethren, have not the Faith of our Lord Ieſus with reſpect of perſons; a Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,</hi> that being read out in the following words, ſeems, at firſt bluſh, to intrench upon civility and good manners, except it be granted, this in <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:118103:19"/>the greateſt reſpect is not given to greatneſs of <hi>Place, Birth, Wealth, Autherity, Braverie,</hi> &amp;c. but to the greatneſs of <hi>Humility</hi> and <hi>Grace</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> according to that of the <hi>Lord Ieſus</hi> (Match. 18.) <hi>Whoſoever ſhall humble himſelf as this little child, the ſame is the greateſt in the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We read of two mighty <hi>Princes</hi> profeſſing the name of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> meeting together in <hi>England, Charles</hi> the Fifthe <hi>Emperour</hi> of <hi>Germany,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Two mighty Princes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Hights in Chriſtianity.</note> and <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth of <hi>England:</hi> Their names then ſoar'd ſo high for <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> that they were both in <hi>Letters</hi> of <hi>Gold,</hi> ſet upon the very <hi>Gates</hi> of <hi>Guildhal</hi> in <hi>London, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolus Defenſor Eccleſiae, Henricus Fidei:</hi> yet when <hi>Luther,</hi> or the pooreſt follower of the truth of <hi>Chriſt ieſus</hi> witneſſed by <hi>Luther,</hi> were condemned and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted by that <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, the great defender of the <hi>Church;</hi> I ask, Who had the greateſt <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> in <hi>Chriſts</hi> affaires, the great <hi>Emperous Charles,</hi> or the pooreſt true <hi>Chriſtian?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Yet the pooreſt witneſs of any truth of Chriſt Jeſus above them.</note> And when that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious (pretended <hi>Defendour</hi> of the Faith) <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, with all his <hi>Nobles</hi> and <hi>Biſhops,</hi> ſat in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with ſo much <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Majeſty, Terrour</hi> and <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> in that famous Diſputation, and Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of that faithful witneſs of Chriſt Ieſus <hi>Iohn Lambert;</hi> I ask, where was in truth the true Autority and power of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> Whether in the ſtately aſſembly of <hi>Kings, Nobles</hi> and <hi>Biſhops,</hi> or in the two-edged Sword of the <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> in the mouth of that one ſingle, and yet moſt faithful witneſs of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay further, I ask,<note place="margin">The Authority of reproving in the name of Chriſt.</note> If that rule of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> (<hi>Luk.</hi> 17.) be not yet in force <hi>(If thy Brother ſin againſt thee, reprove him; if he repent, for give him)</hi> Conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118103:20"/>Whether a <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> (eminent in the grace and knowledge of Chriſt, yet) if a Brother in Chriſt be not to be reproved for ſIn, by his loweſt Groom or handmaid, and that by way of <hi>Authority</hi> in hte Name of Chriſt Jeſus? Yea and I add, Whether have not ſuch inferiour perſOns <hi>Authority</hi> from Chriſt upon <hi>Repentance,</hi> to grant a true <hi>pardon</hi> to ſuch a <hi>magiſtrates</hi> penitent Soul, then all the <hi>Popes</hi> and <hi>Prieſts</hi> in the World can affoard him? And in caſe of final <hi>obſtinacy, contradicting</hi> and <hi>blaſpheming;</hi> I ask, Whether ſuch a poor <hi>Believer</hi> in Chriſt Jeſus hath not a <hi>power</hi> and <hi>priviledge</hi> to ſeparate from ſuch a <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> (in ſpiritual reſpects) and refuſe to touch Spiritually ſUch a (Spiritually) unclean per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon?</p>
            <p>The ſum of the ſeventh Queſtion.</p>
            <p>Whether <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> and the K. of <hi>Nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veh,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>7</label> did well in making their decrees? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ask, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Whether theſe two <hi>Kings</hi> and the <hi>Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> be not ill coupled, for the one, <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> (<hi>Ezra.</hi> 7.) gave free liberty of <hi>conſcience</hi> to the <hi>Iewes;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Artaxerxes his decree exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</note> whereas the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Nineveh</hi> forced all his people to a poſitive Act of <hi>Faſting?</hi> But more particularly, as to <hi>Artaxerxes.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Was not an <hi>Idolatrous King,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A Terror of God ſometimes cauſeth dilaters to favour Gods people.</note> a ſtranger from the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> one that held the people of <hi>God</hi> in ſlavery, one that had no true love to the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> nor his people, but onely out of a fear of the wrath of the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſhe wed favour to his people, granted them free liberty of their <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> to go up to <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to worſhip?</item>
               <item>2. He bountifully incouraged and aſſiſted them.</item>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:118103:20"/>
               <item>3. He furniſhed them with a <hi>Decree,</hi> ſuiting to their <hi>National Eſtate,</hi> and mixt condition of Church and Comonweal.</item>
            </list>
            <p>But (Secondly) I ask, Did this <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel any of theſe <hi>Iewes</hi> to his owne <hi>Religion</hi> (which he believed to be the onely true) the <hi>Religion</hi> of the <hi>Perſians?</hi> Or did he compel the <hi>Perſians</hi> to the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> Or did he compel the <hi>Iewes</hi> themſelves, or any one man of them, to go up to the worſhip of their owne <hi>God</hi> at <hi>ieruſalem?</hi> but verſe 13. <hi>Let all which are minded of their owne free will go up,</hi> &amp;c. Therefore,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I ask,<note place="margin">Artaxerxes his edict freely made for ſoul freedom.</note> What Concluſion can be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered from thence, but that it ſometime pleaſeth <hi>God</hi> to affect the hearts of <hi>Idolatrous Kings</hi> with kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to his people, and forceth them to permit his people the liberty of their <hi>conſciences,</hi> yea and that with <hi>Countenance, Incouragements,</hi> and <hi>Authority?</hi> for which mercy (although the <hi>Nations</hi> where they live, and the <hi>Princes</hi> thereof, partake not of ſuch mercies themſelves, yet, ought <hi>Gods</hi> people to praiſe <hi>God,</hi> as <hi>Ezra</hi> doth.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, I ask, Whether this Inſtance of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxerxes,</hi> do not abſolutely condemn the forcing of all the people and <hi>conſciences</hi> in a <hi>Nation</hi> to one way of worſhip, whether <hi>Popiſh</hi> or <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> or to any particular ſect or way of either of them? And Whether it do not abſolutely make for <hi>Soul-Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> in ſpiritual matters, in that theſe very <hi>Iewes</hi> were not forced to their own <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> but as eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one was freely willing? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly As to the proclamation of the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Nineveh?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:118103:21"/>
            <p>Firſt, I ask, Whether all examples recorded in holy <hi>Scriptures,</hi> bind our <hi>conſciences</hi> in our <hi>worſhips</hi> and communion with <hi>God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In particular,<note place="margin">The King of Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neveh his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming a Faſt, examined.</note> muſt there be a <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Nobles</hi> in <hi>London</hi> to Proclaim a <hi>Fast,</hi> as we know there was in <hi>Nineveh?</hi> muſt the <hi>Beaſts</hi> alſo be kept from <hi>Food</hi> and <hi>Water,</hi> as there? muſt <hi>Man</hi> and <hi>Beaſt</hi> be covered with Sackcloth, as there? If one part of the <hi>Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> bind us, why not the other? Or if we ſay that ſuch practices were <hi>ceremonial</hi> and <hi>typical,</hi> how will that be proved amongſt the <hi>Ninevites,</hi> ſt angers to the true God and his Servant <hi>Moſes?</hi> although pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably they might light their Candle from the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample</hi> of that national Church of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which kept their National <hi>Faſts,</hi> ordinary and extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, &amp;c. And if example be Rule for <hi>Gods</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, I ask, Whether all <hi>Ship-maſters</hi> or <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates,</hi> in their reſpective ſtormes and tempeſts, may exhort their <hi>Paſſengers,</hi> and <hi>Sea-men,</hi> and <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> to ariſe and call upon their ſeveral <hi>Gods</hi> and <hi>Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> as the <hi>Ship-master</hi> deales with <hi>Ionah</hi> in the firſt Chapter?</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">No Warrant in Chriſts Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for a nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal (muchleſsm forced) worſhip</note> I ask, Whether in the <hi>New Testament</hi> of Chriſt Jeſus, by which the <hi>National Church,</hi> and the worſhip of that Church, was aboliſhed, there be any <hi>Example</hi> or <hi>Rule</hi> for any ſuch National wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, of one ſort or another, for what cauſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver?</p>
            <p>And although it may be ſaid, Chriſt Jeſus ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves the <hi>Action;</hi> yet I ask, Whether he ſpeakes one <hi>Tittle</hi> to the <hi>Decree</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Nobles,</hi> but onely to the <hi>Repentance</hi> of the People, at the preaching of <hi>Ionah?</hi> And upon the point, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:118103:21"/>the ſcope of the <hi>Lord Ieſus,</hi> was not to upbraid the hardneſs of our <hi>hearts,</hi> in not repenting at the threatnings of <hi>Gods judgements,</hi> as the <hi>Ninevites</hi> did?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I ask, Whether this example of the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Nineveh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Many various Conſciences; and more will be, in the Nations.</note> can be a proper and fit exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for the imitation of all the <hi>Nations</hi> in the <hi>World,</hi> whoſe Conſciences (like the various <hi>Meridians</hi> and <hi>Climates</hi> of Nations and places) may wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully differ in one and the ſame <hi>Commonweal</hi> and <hi>Kingdom;</hi> the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> (poſſibly) may be of one Conſcience, and all or the greateſt part of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: And (like as in a Ship) where ſeveral Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of <hi>Seamen</hi> and <hi>Paſſengers</hi> happen, how can there be an inforcing of all Conſciences unto one worſhip, without great Violence and Diſtraction, and ſometimes hazard of the whole, in breach of <hi>Peace</hi> by mutinies? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, I ask, Whether the holy Name of <hi>God</hi> hath not been mightily prophaned, and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Eyes of his <hi>Jealouſie</hi> mightily provoked in this <hi>Nation,</hi> by the <hi>Faſts</hi> and <hi>Thankſgivings,</hi> which the People of this <hi>Nation</hi> have been forced to obſerve, even againſt their hearts, and ſouls, and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences? How did the <hi>Parliament</hi> at firſt, inforce the People of this <hi>Nation</hi> to <hi>Faſt</hi> and <hi>Pray,</hi> for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of <hi>Religion, King, Parliament, Lawes, Liberties?</hi> And how did the <hi>King</hi> at the ſame time, command that party of the <hi>Nation</hi> under his command to <hi>Faſt</hi> and <hi>Pray,</hi> for his contrary Forces fighting upon the very ſame Grounds and Cauſes?</p>
            <p>How did the <hi>Parliament</hi> command the People to give Thanks to <hi>God</hi> for thoſe Victories, for
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:118103:22"/>which the <hi>King</hi> commanded the People to give thanks for, as his, got over and againſt the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How have thouſands been forced to pray for the <hi>Parliament,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The wonderful prophaning of the name of God, by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced Worſhipe of Prayer and Thankſgiving in this Nation.</note> whoſe hearts and courſes have ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther joyned with the <hi>King,</hi> againſt the <hi>Parliament;</hi> and thouſands, commanded by the <hi>King</hi> to pray and faſt for him, whoſe hearts and cauſes have more adhered to the <hi>Parliaments cauſe</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt?</hi> Yea as to the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> whoſe cauſe of violence this was (and therefore, O that their Souls may ſee it as from <hi>God,</hi> juſt upon them) how have they been forced to ſuch publike Actions of <hi>pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> and <hi>thankſgivings</hi> (and eſpecially, in reference to the <hi>Scotch Nation</hi> and cauſe) the which their Soules and Conſciences have much abhorred? O the infinite and unſearchable Treaſure of the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of <hi>God,</hi> to ſuch <hi>Worſhips,</hi> ſuch <hi>Violences! &amp;c:</hi> and therefore,</p>
            <p>Laſtly,<note place="margin">The duty of the Magiſtrates ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending Gods Judgements.</note> I ask, Whether the <hi>Governour</hi> of Ships, artificial at Sea, or myſtical, <hi>Commonweales</hi> on ſhore, in their ſeveral ſtormes and tempeſts, can do any more rightly and <hi>Chriſtianly,</hi> by the Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſt Jeſus, then,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Humble themſelves in ſuch waies of <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> and with ſuch Societies and Communions, wherein they have fellowſhip with <hi>God</hi> and one with another, and to ſtand in the Gap by <hi>Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation,</hi> by <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Mercy? Daniel</hi> 4.27. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Uſe all poſſible perſwaſions and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations, to the ſeveral <hi>Paſſengers</hi> under their ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil care and charge, to turn to <hi>God,</hi> to pray unto
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:118103:22"/>him. Thus <hi>Peter</hi> exhorteth <hi>Simon Magus</hi> (fearing <hi>Gods judgements</hi>) to turne unto <hi>God</hi> by repentance, and then to call upon him; And thus <hi>Paul,</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Terour of the <hi>Lord,</hi> 2 Cor. 4. perſwades men to be reconciled to God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> implying this to be the way for the prevention both of <hi>Temporal</hi> and <hi>Eternal Iudgements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">The Duty of good Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Calamities.</note> Intreat the Prayers and Supplications of ſuch, whom they believe to be the People of <hi>God,</hi> whoſe Prayers he profeſſeth to be his <hi>Delight,</hi> and hath promiſed to hear them, while the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the wicked is an <hi>Abomination,</hi> and therefore more provokes him.</p>
            <p>Thus ſome good <hi>Emperours</hi> have uſed to deſire the Interceſſions of <hi>Gods</hi> People, in times of danger and diſtreſs. Yea and <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, ſo high in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour with <hi>God,</hi> and ſo full of the Grace and Spirit of <hi>God,</hi> yea and ſo ful of the Spirit of prayer (as next to the <hi>Lord Ieſus,</hi> we read of no man more in the the <hi>New Teſtament</hi>) yet no man do we read of, that ſo frequently and earneſtly begs the prayers of <hi>Gods</hi> people.</p>
            <p>The eighth Queſtion.</p>
            <p>Whether any of the <hi>Prophets</hi> or <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>6</label> yea our <hi>Saviour</hi> himſelf, did ever except againſt the <hi>Magiſtrates Authority,</hi> for queſtioning them in matters of <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, I ask, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Whether the <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Christ Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> are here ſo fitly joyned in this
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:118103:23"/>
               <hi>Witneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The diſpenſation of the Prophets before Chriſt.</note> ſince the Prophets before Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, were under the diſpenſation of ſhadowes and figures, in that National and typical <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> and onely propheſied of that great <hi>High-Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>Prophet</hi> to come, <hi>Chriſt Ieſus?</hi> The Law and the Prophets were until <hi>Iohn</hi> (ſaith <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi>) and their actions (as relating to a <hi>National Church</hi>) cannot be brought as witneſſes with <hi>Iohn</hi> or <hi>Ieſus?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, I ask, Did not all the Prophets fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel of this moſt abſolute and independent <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Law-giver</hi> to his People, the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Kings,</hi> and <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>Lords,</hi> by whom onely <hi>God</hi> hath ſpoken in theſe laſt times?<note place="margin">Chriſt Jeſus the onely King of Iſrael, and that ſpiritually.</note> 
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. Did not the <hi>Angel</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to <hi>Mary,</hi> that he ſhould be the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and ſhould ſit on the Throne of his Father <hi>David,</hi> (which yet he never did literally?) <hi>Luke</hi> 1. Was he not ſaluted by his followers, Thou art the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Iſrael, Iohn</hi> 1. And was it not for this very cauſe, <hi>viz</hi> [that he was the <hi>King</hi> of the <hi>Iewes,</hi>] that he was Arraigned, Condemned, and Executed, and the crime pretended, fixed on his <hi>Gibbet,</hi> in <hi>Hebrew, Greek,</hi> and <hi>Latin; Ieſus of Nazareth King of the Iews?</hi> All which he was, not in any temporal or worldly reſpect (for he diſclaimed and refuſed the offer of a temporal <hi>Crown</hi>) but in an abſolute ſpiritual con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, reſpecting the ſouls and conſciences, the <hi>Religions</hi> and <hi>Worſhips</hi> of the children of men.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I ask, Whether the <hi>Lord Ieſus</hi> except not expreſly againſt the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> in matters of <hi>Religion,</hi> in that ſo famous Diſtinction between <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars</hi> right and <hi>Gods;</hi> give unto <hi>Ceſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Ceſars,</hi> and unto God the things that are <hi>Gods?</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:118103:23"/>More particularly and conciſely, I ask,<note place="margin">Caeſars due is Gods due, and yet Gods due diſtinct from Caeſars.</note> Whether <hi>Ceſars Sword</hi> was not <hi>Gods Sword? Rom.</hi> 13. And Whether by giving unto <hi>Ceſar</hi> his <hi>Submiſſion, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Tribute,</hi> &amp;c. was not a giving <hi>God</hi> his due (in a true ſenſe) by giving this his due to <hi>Ceſar?</hi> And if ſo, then what ſingular and diſtinct Character is this, which gives unto <hi>God</hi> his due, diſtinct from <hi>Ceſar?</hi> And Whether there can be any other Characte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtical difference imagined, but onely that of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>conſcience, ſpiritual</hi> and Religious, which <hi>Ceſar</hi> himſelf (as the old Martyrs witneſs of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> were wont to ſay) had no power over?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, As to the Apoſtles, I ask,<note place="margin">The Apoſtles were the higheſt and next to Chriſt Ieſus, in matters of the chriſtian name and Worſhip.</note> If the book of the <hi>Acts,</hi> and the <hi>Epiſtles,</hi> &amp;c. breathe not forth the moſt abſolute <hi>Independency</hi> of their Miniſtery and Apoſtleſhip, from the higheſt <hi>civil</hi> powers in the World?</p>
            <p>Tis true, <hi>Paul</hi> makes an humble <hi>Appeal</hi> (againſt the Perſecuters of his life) to the higheſt <hi>Magiſtrate Ceſar:</hi> But as to the matters of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity,</hi> was not the <hi>Church</hi> built upon the Foundation of the Apoſtles and Prophets? (<hi>Eph.</hi> 2) Were not their Commands, in ſpiritual things, the command of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> (1 Cor. 14.) even to the higheſt <hi>Kings,</hi> and <hi>Keyſars?</hi> Was not that an Apoſtles voice (in caſe of <hi>Religion</hi>) Ye are bought with a price, (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7) let no man (conſequently not the higheſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) <hi>judge</hi> you in reſpect of meats and drinks, or an holy day? And what can be more expreſs, then ſuch peremptory, not onely refuſalls to obey ungodly and unchriſtian commands (<hi>Act.</hi> 4.5.) but even to own the very Courts and Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catures of the higheſt in the matters of the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>Lords, Christ Ieſus?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:118103:24"/>
            <p>Laſtly, Since the <hi>Magiſtrates Authority</hi> in queſtioning matter of <hi>Religion,</hi> may be taken two waies:</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">Twofold queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous matters.</note> For demanding a <hi>private</hi> reaſon of a <hi>Chriſtians Faith</hi> or <hi>Practice;</hi> ſo here it cannot be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended: for there is no queſtion, but that every Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> ought to be ready, to give a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to every one, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>Secondly, For <hi>Authoritative</hi> queſtioning ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by inferiour <hi>Magiſtrates Executive,</hi> or <hi>Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour, Legiſtative:</hi> and if <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> had been ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, and bound to anſwer any <hi>Authority</hi> queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning him, or his Apoſtles, as to matter of his <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> or <hi>Chriſtian Worſhip,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chriſt Jeſus the he moſt abſolute Monarck.</note> if himſelf and his Apoſtles and followers, had or ſhould owne any Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal in Spirituals but his owne, they ſhould have pluckt up the roots of his moſt glorious and moſt abſolute <hi>Government</hi> and <hi>Headſhip.</hi> And if ſo, what kinde of <hi>Hereſie</hi> and <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> againſt <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> this is, let the <hi>Heaven</hi> and the <hi>Earth</hi> be Judges.</p>
            <p>The ſum of the ninth Queſtion.</p>
            <p>Whether the <hi>Examiner</hi> have cauſe to ſay, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>9</label> that the Believing <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> giving wholeſome Food, and forbidding of Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, be a ground for a <hi>Magistrate</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand Poyſon? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Unto which may be added, the ſum of the tenth Queſtion. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>10</label>
            </p>
            <p>Whether <hi>Aſa</hi>'s Authority from God to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:118103:24"/>advance the true Religion, were a ground for <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> to ſet up <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Perſecution, to kill thoſe that would not worſhip his Idols?</p>
            <p>As alſo the ſum of the Eleventh.</p>
            <p>Whether Gods Law, puniſhing <hi>Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> unto death, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>11</label> laid a principle for <hi>Jeza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel</hi> to kill <hi>Naboth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And of the Twelfth.</p>
            <p>Whether <hi>Paul</hi> commanding Parents to bring up their Children in the <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Admonition</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>12</label> laies a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for Children to be brought up in <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ask, Whether the propoſer of the Queſtions <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> do indeed think the <hi>Examiner</hi> ſo void of Zeal and Reaſon, as to imagine that <hi>Corruption</hi> and <hi>Abuſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">All Gods works and Inſtitutions, and God eimſelf obuſed by man.</note> are ſufficient ground to overthrow a truly-<hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> yea or the leaſt <hi>natural</hi> or <hi>Civil Conſtitution</hi> and <hi>Appointment?</hi> Or rather that he grants all <hi>Natural</hi> Bodies, both <hi>Caeleſtial</hi> and <hi>Terreſtrial,</hi> yea all <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Civil Conſtitutions</hi> from <hi>God</hi> or <hi>Men,</hi> are <hi>Gods</hi> works, and excellent in their kinde, although by man abuſed to <hi>Idolatry, Superſtition, Oppreſſion, Glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony, Drunkenneſs, Whoredome, Pride, Ambition, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:118103:25"/>
            <p>Secondly, I ask, Whether all the <hi>Queſtions</hi> are not built upon theſe <hi>Principles,</hi> which are not one-in <hi>Diſpute,</hi> and not granted, but now at this time of the day, they do moſt ſhamefully beg of <hi>Moſes,</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> of theſe late <hi>Times,</hi> and mercifull diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries of the true principles, both of <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Civil Government;</hi> I ſay, beg for that which can never more be granted, without horrible <hi>Oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and <hi>Tyranny,</hi> over the ſouls and bodies of all the ſons of men? <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To particularize:<note place="margin">Foundations out of courſe.</note> Firſt, That Civil <hi>Magiſtracy</hi> is not meerly a Civil <hi>Thing,</hi> in the very nature and eſſential <hi>Qualities</hi> and beings thereof; but rather ſome <hi>Divinum quid,</hi> and that <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Queens</hi> and <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> are <hi>Gods</hi> (not onely by way of <hi>Alluſion</hi> and <hi>Conſimilitude,</hi> and in a reſpect, but really they are <hi>Sacred</hi> (or holy) perſons, their <hi>Majeſties Sacred,</hi> their <hi>Crownes Sacred,</hi> their <hi>Thrones Sacred,</hi> and their very <hi>Kingdomes</hi> and <hi>Empires Sacred.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Kings Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Hence that moſt horrid Blaſphemous Character, on the Forehead of the <hi>Whore</hi> and of the <hi>Beaſt, Sacrum Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manum Imperium,</hi> that <hi>Sacred</hi> or holy <hi>Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, That the People and Inhabitants of the Nations of the Earth, are borne <hi>Slaves,</hi> and <hi>Villaines,</hi> and are not the <hi>Original</hi> and <hi>Fountain</hi> both of their Offices, Officers, and of the <hi>Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> committed to them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That no <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> in the whole world, are lawful <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> but <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly none but the <hi>Proteſtant;</hi> and among them, none but of ſuch a <hi>Sect</hi> or <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, That the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> (that Land
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:118103:25"/>of Ceremonies, Types, and Miracles was a Land of <hi>patterne</hi> and <hi>example,</hi> for all Lands, all Nations, all Magiſtrates, and that not in matters of <hi>Morality, Civility,</hi> and <hi>Humanity</hi> onely (which is not contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted) but even in the matters of <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Covenant,</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> in <hi>Gods Worſhip,</hi> &amp;c. If theſe Queſtions are built upon theſe grounds, I ask, if theſe <hi>Roots</hi> be found rotten and withered, what can be lookt for on the <hi>Branches?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, I ask, How can it be avoided, but that one of theſe two Conſequences muſt be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? Either,</p>
            <p>Firſt, If Magiſtrates, as Magiſtrates,<note place="margin">The dangerous hanging or ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates.</note> be keepers of both Tables, then muſt they keep them and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret them, and determine Controverſies about <hi>Religion</hi> by thoſe Eyes, and by that <hi>Eye-ſight,</hi> which they have in <hi>Religions</hi> and heavenly things (be it <hi>Pagan,</hi> or <hi>Turkiſh,</hi> or <hi>Popiſh,</hi> or <hi>Proteſtant.</hi>)</p>
            <p>Or elſe, ſecondly, they muſt flie to Maſter <hi>Cottons</hi> refuge of <hi>ſuſpending</hi> (or hanging up) all the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates in the <hi>World</hi> from acting in Spirituals,<note place="margin">The rooting up of all Societies out of the World.</note> if they ſee not the true and onely way of <hi>Worſhip;</hi> and that for all the daies of their life, except <hi>God</hi> give them <hi>Repentance,</hi> and reveal the true and onely way un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them.</p>
            <p>And I add, and ask, Whether this <hi>Doctrine</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline not ſtrongly, to theſe two more (juſtly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploded) dangerous <hi>Conſequences?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, That as no <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> muſt act in Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, but ſuch as are of the pretended true (which every <hi>Sect</hi> is prone to plead to be his) and <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates</hi> (many thouſands and ten thouſands, muſt be hanged up as above ſaid) yea and hanged outright,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:118103:26"/>for want of thoſe <hi>Eſſential</hi> and <hi>Fundamental Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications,</hi> which may inable him to diſcharge the principal end of his Office; ſo, neither may the People, which are the <hi>Original</hi> and <hi>Fountain</hi> of <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verment,</hi> lawfully combine and live in civil Coha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation, or Societies, but muſt live <hi>Barbarians</hi> or worſe, ſince that all the People and <hi>Nations</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> in this depraved ſtate of mankinde, are wholly void of heavenly underſtanding, and can no more convey to their <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> any ſpiritual <hi>Authority</hi> or <hi>Power,</hi> then a <hi>Dead</hi> man can appoint his <hi>Officers, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">Proteſtant Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits.</note> If ſuch Orthodox, ſound and right (<hi>Magiſtrates</hi> choſen by the People, come to be of another conſcience, perſwaſion and <hi>Worſhip</hi> (true or or falſe) ought they to be <hi>depoſed? &amp;c.</hi> and may not that <hi>Oxford</hi> Author, who put forth that Book, called the <hi>Puritan</hi> turn'd <hi>Jeſuite,</hi> and all that hold that principle of <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> being <hi>Cuſtodes utrinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Tabulae,</hi> be forced to ſay, that (in this reſpect) the <hi>Biſhops</hi> were <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> the <hi>Preſbyterians</hi> are <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> the <hi>Inderendants</hi> are <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and hold that dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>Doctrine</hi> of depoſing <hi>haeretical Magiſtrates?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Laſtly,<note place="margin">Strange violence to childrens and Parents conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences.</note> As to the Queſtion from the <hi>New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> (<hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.4. <hi>Fathers, provoke not your children in wrath, but bring them up in the Inſtruction and admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of the Lord</hi>) may not he do this, except he force them to his owne <hi>conſcience</hi> and <hi>Worſhip?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I ask further, if it followes not, that if the child by ſome providence of <hi>God</hi> (as ſometimes it falls out) become Superiour and <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> to the Parent, The child now being <hi>Father,</hi> muſt force
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:118103:26"/>his Fathers Conſcience, according to that typical Example of <hi>Aſa</hi> (puniſhing his Mother <hi>Maachah</hi> for her Conſcience?) Yea I ask, how could it be avoided, that by this Rule <hi>King Edward</hi> did well, in forbidding his Siſter <hi>Mary</hi> the uſe of her Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, when he (though younger) was her <hi>Head;</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> (though a woman, yet now <hi>Head</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi>) could not do other, but forbid her Siſter <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the uſe of her <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Prayers and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience alſo? And therefore I ask, Whether it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes not by this Rule, that all Conſcience and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in the whole world, be not (except we grant the monſtrous ſuſpenſion of almoſt all the <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates</hi> and <hi>Fathers</hi> in the world) be not, I ſay, to be meaſured by the accidental turns of <hi>Superiority,</hi> and the Civil Sword?</p>
            <p>The ſum of the thirtenth Queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether ſince <hi>Idolatry</hi> was puniſhed by the light of Nature (as <hi>Job</hi> acknowledged, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>13</label> 
               <hi>Job</hi> 31.28.) the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> ought not much more to puniſh it in the <hi>Goſpel</hi>-light? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Firſt, I ask, As to that place in <hi>Iob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 31.28. <hi>Examined.</hi>
               </note> Whether there be not many various <hi>Tranſlations</hi> and <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations</hi> of this Scripture? Doth not the <hi>Septua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gint,</hi> (the Seventy) interpret thoſe words [that were an Iniquity (as we turn it) to be puniſhed by the Iudges] I ſay, the Seventh turn it thus: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>For this would have been accounted,</hi> judged or eſteemed, <hi>the greateſt,</hi> or a very great <hi>iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:118103:27"/>
            <p>Others, <hi>Quae eſt Iniquitas maxima,</hi> which is the greateſt, or a very great Iniquity.</p>
            <p>Others, <hi>Etiam hoc futſſet Iniquitas judicata;</hi> For this had been a plain condemned or judged Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For <hi>Interpretation,</hi> ſome interpret thoſe words <hi>(If I behold the ſun when it ſhined, or the moon walking in brightneſs)</hi> to imply <hi>Iobs</hi> denying of his worſhipping the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon,</hi> &amp;c. Some Metaphorically, for being puft up with proſperity and ſucceſs, which tempts all men,<note place="margin">Gods people moſt apt in proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity to deny him.</note> and even <hi>Gods</hi> People themſelves, (as <hi>Agur</hi> confeſſeth) to ſay unto <hi>God</hi> when they are full, who is the <hi>Lord?</hi> and to deny Him who is the <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> the <hi>Author</hi> and <hi>Fountain</hi> &amp;c. of all their mercies. And therefore I ask, If it be not probable, that <hi>Iob</hi> might ſooner be tempted to that ſo pleaſing a ſin of applauding himſelf in the ſhining of the <hi>ſun</hi> (Heavenly (and right-hand) mercies) and the brightneſs of the <hi>Moon</hi> (left-hand, and inferiour mercies) then to be inticed to that groſs and ſo palpable an <hi>Idolatry,</hi> of worſhiping the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>moon? &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Grant that the beholding of the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon</hi> by <hi>Iob,</hi> and the ſecret inticement of his <hi>Heart,</hi> and the kiſſing of his mouth, &amp;c. relates to <hi>Idolatry,</hi> in the very real and literal <hi>Worſhiping</hi> of thoſe Creatures; grant that was <hi>Iniquity</hi> to be puniſhed by the <hi>Iudges:</hi> As alſo that <hi>Iob</hi> lived be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Moſes,</hi> and acknowledged the Juſtice of ſuch puniſhments (all which particulars can be but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably diſputed, <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con;</hi> and therefore is not ſuch a Building and Fabrick, to be laid upon ſo uncertain a <hi>Groundſel</hi> and <hi>Foundation.</hi>) But admit all,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:118103:27"/>yea and further [that the <hi>Goſpel</hi> gives more light for the Diſcovery of the ſinfulneſs and guilt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f <hi>Idolatry</hi>] Yet,<note place="margin">The diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of God, both before and after Moſes.</note> ſince both <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Iob</hi> alſo lived un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch diſpenſations of <hi>National Covenants</hi> and Worſhips, and before them of the <hi>Family-Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants</hi> and <hi>Worſhips,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Abrahams, Iſaacks, Iaccbs,</hi> and the <hi>Patriarchs,</hi> wherein the <hi>Fathers</hi> of <hi>Families,</hi> and the elder brothers (in a figurative <hi>Birthright</hi> of the firſt born) carried on the figure <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> to come,<note place="margin">The Land of Canaan a none-ſuch, and typical</note> as ſupream <hi>Heads</hi> and <hi>Governours</hi> in all cauſes, as well <hi>eccleſiaſtical</hi> as <hi>Civil;</hi> ſhall we now then, in the bright light of the <hi>Sun</hi> of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the true King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> &amp;c. erect new Lands of <hi>Canaan</hi> in all the <hi>Nations</hi> of the World? Will they not be meer Skeletons, Shadowes and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſes, without thoſe living <hi>Demonſtrations,</hi> and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous appearances of <hi>God,</hi> from firſt to laſt with that wonderful and typical People? Shall we ſtill take the <hi>Lord Ieſus</hi> by force to make him a temporal <hi>King,</hi> and a temporal <hi>Iudge;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chriſt Jeſus not a temporal King.</note> when he peremptorily refuſeth, and proclaimes that his <hi>Kingdome</hi> is not of this World? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Will not this be as <hi>Iob</hi> there ſaith, to deny the <hi>God</hi> that is above, or (as the Word ſeems to cary it) the <hi>God</hi> deſcending? who hath aſcended, but firſt deſcended God in <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and dwelt in <hi>Fleſh</hi> of the <hi>Lord Ieſus</hi> Bodily, and eſtabliſhed a ſpiritual <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> in the Conſciences, and Worſhips, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations of Men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And however the <hi>Devil</hi> (deſpairing to deſtroy the appearance of <hi>God</hi> in Fleſh, either in the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Christs humane</hi> body, or in his <hi>mystical Body</hi> his Saints, by three hundred years perſecution)
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:118103:28"/>hath taken the advantage, by the ſhining of Peace and Favour to the Saints by <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> to turn the very World it ſelf <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> deſigning, under the Masks and Flag of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> name, to conceal his Serpentine malice to pure and true <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> and to effect that by the <hi>Roman Popes,</hi> the <hi>Foxes,</hi> which he could never do by the <hi>Roman</hi> Lyons, the <hi>Emperours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet (I ask) Shall <hi>Gods</hi> people ſtill inhabit <hi>Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> (or confuſion) and darkly confound all the moſt holy,<note place="margin">Gods people commanded to diſobey the civil power in Sptrituals.</note> moſt wiſe, diſtinct appearances of God toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? and not rather liſten to the holy Spirit of <hi>God,</hi> in that abſolute prohibition (<hi>Col.</hi> 2) Let no man judge you in meats and drinks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that is, upon any <hi>Spiritual</hi> account and <hi>Conſideration,</hi> albeit in Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil affaires, we ought to be judged, and ſubmit to every <hi>Ordinance</hi> (or Creation) of man, for the <hi>Lords</hi> ſake? 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">Two kinder of Idolatry.</note> I ask (as before) Whether the <hi>Goſpel</hi>-light hath not diſcovered unto us (more clearly at leaſt, then ever the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> did) at twofold <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Religious, which is (in a word) the fearing or Worſhipping of falſe <hi>Deities,</hi> or <hi>Gods,</hi> or <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads,</hi> which all the Nations, all the World over, live in.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Moral <hi>Idolatry,</hi> which is <hi>Idolatry</hi> in the Hearts and Lives of all mankinde, according to that of <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Epheſians:</hi> and Covetouſneſs, which is <hi>Idolatry,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>According to this Diſtinction, how are all the <hi>Nations</hi> of the World (even that which is called <hi>Chriſtian</hi> alſo) or'e-ſpread with theſe <hi>Idolatries?</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:118103:28"/>Yea and (in lamentably too great a meaſure) how are <hi>Gods</hi> owne people reported (at leaſt in the moral ſence) to be <hi>Idolatrous?</hi> &amp;c. For,</p>
            <p>If Coveting of <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Silver, Houſe</hi> and <hi>Lands,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The over-ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Idolatry in England, and all Nations.</note> be <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and conſequently, all covetous actions (ſuch as raking, lying, ſtealing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) are acts of <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry</hi> in a <hi>Goſpel</hi>-ſenſe: Then conſequently the goings out of the heart in other Sins, <hi>Pride, Self-love, Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Whoredom,</hi> are <hi>Idolatry</hi> alſo, and all the Acts at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending ſuch motions and deſires, <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Idolatry</hi> alſo in all the Inhabitants of the World, and then eſpecially and more eminently (or rather odiouſly) in ſuch as profeſs the name of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> Oh what an object of the <hi>Iealouſie</hi> of the moſt <hi>High,</hi> is this <hi>Idolatrous Ball</hi> of the Earth, and even that part above all others, which pretends the name of the Son of <hi>God,</hi> and which (yet above all others) cries out againſt Idolaters? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, As to the Light of Nature, diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Idolatry,</hi> I ask,</p>
            <p>Firſt, If there be not a wonderful miſtake, a fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacie and ſnare in the term of expreſſion, <hi>Light</hi> of <hi>Nature?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true, The <hi>Nature</hi> of <hi>Gods Children</hi> is <hi>Light,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gods people in a glorious ſtate of Light.</note> 
               <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. <hi>Ye are light in the Lord;</hi> and <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. They ſhin as <hi>Lights:</hi> God is a <hi>Sun</hi> and ſhield unto them; Chriſt Jeſus is a <hi>Sun</hi> of Righteouſneſs ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning on them; The holy Scripture is a <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Lanterne</hi> to them; The words of the <hi>Prophets,</hi> as a <hi>Light</hi> ſhining in a dark place, until the Day-ſtar <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> ariſe ſpiritually in their hearts: They have glorious promiſes, that the <hi>Light</hi> of the <hi>Moon</hi> ſhall be as the <hi>Light</hi> of the <hi>Sun,</hi> and the <hi>Light</hi> of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:118103:29"/>the <hi>Sun</hi> ſeven times brighter: They expect that time, when they ſhall need no more <hi>Candle</hi> nor <hi>Sun,</hi> but the <hi>Lord God</hi> and the <hi>Lamb</hi> will be their <hi>Light:</hi> and knowing that <hi>Light</hi> is ſown for the Righteous, they expect and ſhall aſſuredly reap the <hi>Harveſt</hi> of <hi>Light</hi> to all <hi>Eternity.</hi> But what is this to corrupt Nature,<note place="margin">Light of Nature in ſpiritual things but darkneſs.</note> to dark Nature? <hi>You were not onely in darkneſs and children of the night, but dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs it ſelf</hi> (Epheſ. 5.) And if that which we call <hi>Light</hi> in men, be <hi>Darkneſs</hi> (as the <hi>Lord Ieſus</hi> ſpeaks) how great is that <hi>Darkneſs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if it be ſaid, that <hi>Iob</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> ſay, that the <hi>Light</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> diſcovers <hi>Idolatry;</hi> I ask, Whether <hi>Iob</hi> ſay ſo expreſly, or by any conſequence, which may not rather be counterbalanced another way? Or if <hi>Iob</hi> ſhould ſay ſo, whether upon an equal diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation? when in thoſe times <hi>corporal</hi> Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and in <hi>Goſpel</hi>-times <hi>ſpiritual</hi> Judgements are proper; as in this very <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. is abundantly teſtified.</p>
            <p>It is true, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, The Spirit of a man is the <hi>Candle</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> ſearching all the inward parts of the Belly: It is an <hi>Excuſer</hi> and an <hi>Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer;</hi> a <hi>Secretary,</hi> a <hi>Sergeant,</hi> an <hi>Adverſary,</hi> a <hi>Iudge,</hi> an <hi>Executioner,</hi> within the boſome of all mankinde: But yet I ask,<note place="margin">What knowledg of God, corrupt Nature may attain unto.</note> how far this Spirit of Man, this <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle</hi> of <hi>Jehovah</hi> hath ſearched, and doth, or poſſibly may ſearch, into all the inward parts of the <hi>Belly,</hi> or Hearts of man, as touching this great myſtery of true of falſe <hi>Deities,</hi> and their reſpective <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips?</hi> And</p>
            <p>I ask, Where lies the <hi>Harmonie</hi> between theſe two Scriptures, this of <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. When they knew
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:118103:29"/>
               <hi>God,</hi> they glorified him not as <hi>God:</hi> and that of 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. The World by Wiſdome knew not <hi>God.</hi> And</p>
            <p>I ask, If natural wiſdome (that Candle or Light remaining in man) be not twofold?<note place="margin">Natural light twofold.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, That which is <hi>Common</hi> to all mankinde in general; to the people, the loweſt, the vulgar?</p>
            <p>Secondly, That which is more <hi>Noble</hi> and High,<note place="margin">The higheſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments of the higheſt ſons of nature, in ſpirituals.</note> (in degrees) refined and elevated by finer <hi>Animal Spirits,</hi> by <hi>Education,</hi> by <hi>Study,</hi> by <hi>Obſervation,</hi> by <hi>Experience.</hi> And</p>
            <p>I ask, Whether theſe higheſt <hi>Lights,</hi> and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Candles</hi> can attaine, by their utmoſt <hi>Activity,</hi> to a true, and ſaving, and <hi>Goſpel</hi>-knowledge, even of <hi>God</hi> himſelfe? And therefore, whether the place of <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. They knew <hi>God,</hi> can amount unto more, even in the <hi>Princes</hi> of natural knowledge, <hi>Plato, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca, Ariſtotle,</hi> &amp;c. but unto a confeſſion of a <hi>Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> a <hi>Godhead</hi> above us, in us, about us; an Inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble mighty power, <hi>Creating, Ruling, Ordering</hi> all things; as alſo, a <hi>Conviction</hi> of <hi>Bleſſedneſs</hi> in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of this <hi>Deity,</hi> and of <hi>Curſedneſs</hi> in <hi>Diſunion</hi> from it?</p>
            <p>But now let's deſcend to <hi>Cultus Inſtitutus</hi> and <hi>Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Naturalis,</hi> an <hi>Inſtituted,</hi> and a natural <hi>Worſhip.</hi> Come to the light of nature worſhipping this <hi>Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:</hi> Come to the ſeven precepts of <hi>Noah,</hi> which ſome, both <hi>Jewes,</hi> and other ancients, talk of; and then I ask, if it be not a downright Doctrine of <hi>Free-will,</hi> in depraved nature?<note place="margin">No ſpirituat object ſeen with a natural eye.</note> If it be not to run point-blank againſt all the <hi>Hiſtories</hi> of the <hi>Nations,</hi> and all preſent <hi>Experience</hi> of mankind, in all known parts of the World, to attribute ſo much <hi>light</hi> to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:118103:30"/>any of the <hi>Eldeſt</hi> and <hi>Gallanteſt</hi> ſons of Nature, as to attain a <hi>ſpiritual</hi> and ſaving knowledge of <hi>God,</hi> to attain a love unto <hi>God,</hi> in all their knowledge; to attain the myſtery of the <hi>Father</hi> and of the <hi>Son, God</hi> manifeſted in Fleſh, by whom <hi>Creation</hi> and <hi>Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption</hi> are wrought; to the matter of true worſhip, or to any thing but <hi>Splendidum Peccatum,</hi> without the Revelation of the <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> out of his abſolute, free, and peculiar Grace and Mercy in Chriſt Jeſus?</p>
            <p>Hence I ask,<note place="margin">The monſtrous opinions of the Nations, as to Dieties and their worſhips.</note> If from this <hi>Corruption</hi> of Nature it have not ſprung, that the wiſeſt <hi>Nations, Councels, Parliaments,</hi> have run into ſuch monſtrous opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons about the <hi>Gods,</hi> and the number of them; and ſo many monſtrous and horrible, and ſome ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous kindes and waies of worſhip? Thus did the <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> the <hi>Perſians,</hi> the <hi>Greeks,</hi> the <hi>Romans,</hi> and all the Generations and Nations of men, unto this day.</p>
            <p>It is true, It is charged upon the wiſeſt of the Sons of men, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. They glorified not <hi>God,</hi> as <hi>God,</hi> that they were not thankful; that they gave the glory of the <hi>Creator</hi> to the <hi>Creature;</hi> and that therefore <hi>God</hi> delivered them up to thoſe moral fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſes and defilements.</p>
            <p>It is true,<note place="margin">Two deep dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons of moral wickedneſs, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which the conſcience of ſome in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping have tumbled.</note> That becauſe men received not the Truth in the Love of it, <hi>God</hi> delivered them up to ſtrong Deluſions, to believe lyes. And alſo theſe Spiritual Judgements have proceeded ſo far, that the poor deluded Generations of men, have tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled down millions of millions, one upon the neck of another, into theſe two deep and doleful <hi>Dungeons.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:118103:30"/>
            <p>The firſt,<note place="margin">Whoredom and Murder.</note> Of practiſing uncleanneſs and <hi>Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> practiſed by ſome Nations, even upon the very account of Religion and Conſcience.</p>
            <p>The ſecond, Of Cruelty and Murder, as of <hi>Baals Prieſts,</hi> cutting and launcing themſelves, and of many <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Sects,</hi> afflicting themſelves in ſome Nations, with many Torments; and above all, that of the abominable and moſt inhumane Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficing mankind: In which horrid <hi>Worſhip,</hi> not onely the <hi>Mexicans</hi> did abound,<note place="margin">The Sacrificing of mankind out of conſcience.</note> in their Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing yearly many thouſands <hi>Infants</hi> to their bloody <hi>Dieties,</hi> before the coming of <hi>Pizarro</hi> amongſt them; but alſo Gods owne people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and none of the very Kings of <hi>Iudah</hi> (before repentance) fell into this bloody pit, of offering up their Children through the fire to <hi>Molech.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I readily acknowledge, that in theſe caſes men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned,<note place="margin">The Civil Sword must cut off all Inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilities, though under Religions pretences mask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and covered.</note> and in all other caſes wherein Civility is wronged, in the <hi>Bodies</hi> or <hi>goods</hi> of any, the Civil Sword is <hi>Gods</hi> Sword, as well as mans, for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing of ſuch Practices and Appearances, yea and the very <hi>Principles</hi> of them; and for the Incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement and applauſe of the contrary, <hi>Chaſtity, Humanity,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Hence, I honour that noble act of the <hi>Emperour</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> who cenſured that famous <hi>Ovid,</hi> for that wanton <hi>Book</hi> of his <hi>De Arte amandi,</hi> as a ſparke to immodeſty and uncleanneſs: and doubtleſs it is the the duty of the <hi>civil ſword,</hi> to cut off the <hi>Incivilities</hi> of our times; as the monſtrous haire of women, up-the heads of ſome men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet I ask, Whether <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeak ought, in the firſt of the <hi>Romans,</hi> of any humane Iudge or Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:118103:31"/>upon the <hi>Nations</hi> of the World, for their meer <hi>Idolatries,</hi> thus moſt dreadfully plagued alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, by the moſt righteous <hi>Iudge</hi> of the whole World, in thoſe ſtrong <hi>Deluſions</hi> and <hi>Lyes,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liveries up to ſo many <hi>Luſts</hi> and <hi>Sins,</hi> which alſo run upon the Civil Sword of <hi>God</hi> and man, for their uncivil and unrighteous practices?</p>
            <p>I ask further,<note place="margin">All ſeeming in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civilities, not to be lookt upon with one eye.</note> Whether or no ſome ſeeming <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civilities,</hi> which the <hi>Light</hi> of Nature more fairly may condemn, and hale before the <hi>Civil Tribunal,</hi> yet may not be ſuch; and ſo Circumſtantiated with <hi>Impreſſions</hi> from <hi>Heaven,</hi> that they ought not ſo ſuddenly and eaſily to be condemned and <hi>pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhed,</hi> but, with a more tender and obſervant Eye, be <hi>diſtinguiſhed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For (not to inſtance in any diſputable Acts which the holy <hi>Scripture</hi> and <hi>experience</hi> preſents us with) what ſhall be ſaid to that very common and conſtant <hi>practise</hi> of <hi>Circumciſion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The practice of Circumciſion, a ſeeming Incivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</note> commanded by <hi>God</hi> himſelf to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and now entertained by one of the greateſt <hi>Empires</hi> of the World, the <hi>Turks?</hi> may not it be (with faire probability) argued to be againſt the light of <hi>Nature?</hi> For, Although the <hi>Iewes</hi> might plead, The <hi>Inſtitution</hi> of this <hi>Ordinance</hi> was from <hi>Heaven,</hi> and the <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> That it was done in ſo ſolemn and <hi>Religîous</hi> a way, that it was not performed with any laſcivious or uncleane obſervations or geſtures, but with <hi>Horror,</hi> and <hi>Pain,</hi> and <hi>Bloodſhedding,</hi> and great <hi>Affliction</hi> of the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man (as we ſee in the <hi>Shechemites</hi>) And laſtly, That it was attended with heavenly and myſtical <hi>ſignifications,</hi> as a <hi>Type</hi> and <hi>Figure,</hi> &amp;. Yet not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, how was it branded and blackr with the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:118103:31"/>Scorned and Jeers of the <hi>Nations?</hi> inſomuch that the very <hi>Sabbath</hi> (the ſolemn worſhipping of <hi>God</hi> one day in ſeven, in a moſt religious acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his moſt glorious Creating of this won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful frame of the <hi>World</hi> in ſix) was jeered, from this very ſeeming Incivility of <hi>Circumciſion: Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titaque Sabbata,</hi> &amp;c. the Circumciſed Sabbaths, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If <hi>Abraham</hi> had lived now in <hi>England</hi> (one of the moſt zealous Nations of the <hi>World,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Abrahams Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificing of Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ak a ſeeming in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civility.</note> for inflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing torments on others, and being tormented for <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi>) what would our raſh <hi>Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots</hi> have done with <hi>Abraham,</hi> in caſe he had Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed his ſon <hi>Iſaac?</hi> &amp;c. would they have exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the <hi>miraculous</hi> conception of the Child a s from Heaven, and the reaſon that that moſt holy and moſt glorious hand, that ſo <hi>miraculouſly</hi> and <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturally</hi> gave him, now call'd againe for him, by a Voice <hi>miraculous</hi> from Heaven? alſo, would they have obſerved the Man, ſo <hi>Holy,</hi> and ſo <hi>Faithful,</hi> his <hi>Addreſſes</hi> to the Act to <hi>Holy,</hi> and ſo free from <hi>Paſſion,</hi> from <hi>Deſigne?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Or if the Mother of the <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> had brought forth her Son amongſt us,<note place="margin">So <hi>Maries</hi> bringing forth of Christ Ieſus.</note> and (it ſhould have been acknowledged) without the company of her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band; Yet who can be ſo impious againſt <hi>God,</hi> and ſo unchriſtian and blaſphemous againſt <hi>Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> as to queſtion, but that the moſt Civil, and the ſevereſt <hi>Judge,</hi> upon due <hi>Examination</hi> of the whole matter, might rationally and judicionally have pronounced to have found no violence of <hi>Civility,</hi> no wrong to the Bodies or Goods of any (the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per object and cauſe of all Civil <hi>Officers</hi>) but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:118103:32"/>a moſt holy and glorious appearance of the living <hi>God,</hi> and gloriouſly free from ſuch <hi>Impuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> with which even the <hi>Religion</hi> of whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are defiled?</p>
            <p>But,<note place="margin">The Extreme madneſs of the Religious zeal of men, ſeldome but in extreams.</note> oh the madneſs of the <hi>Children</hi> of <hi>Men</hi> (ſaid I?) yea the precious Children of the very <hi>God</hi> of Heaven! Into what furious <hi>Extremes</hi> do we leap and run into, without the <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Lanterne</hi> of the holy Spirit and Word of <hi>God;</hi> not withſtanding our great pretences of ſuch pure <hi>Natures light?</hi> For how fiery would we be to condemn ſuch a <hi>Birth</hi> as <hi>ſpurious,</hi> the <hi>Parents</hi> and the <hi>child</hi> unclean (Bring her forth and burn her, as <hi>Judah</hi> ſaid of <hi>Thamar</hi>) until we owne the Child (in Religion) ours, the Mothers ours? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And therefore againe, how rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſheath our <hi>ſwords</hi> in the bowels of the poor <hi>Iew</hi> or <hi>Gentile,</hi> which cannot ſee with our <hi>Eyes</hi> and <hi>ſpectacles,</hi> and believe this Child to be <hi>the Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>true Meſſiah?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I profeſs my ſelf unſatisfied, as to the <hi>Baptiſme</hi> and <hi>Dipping</hi> now uſed; I abhor the debauchedneſs of thoſe poor deluded high <hi>Attainers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Incivilities of the Ranters.</note> the <hi>Mad Folks</hi> (as Maſter <hi>Pennington</hi> well calls them) the <hi>Ranters:</hi> And I praiſe <hi>God,</hi> for the height and prudence of the <hi>State,</hi> to prevent and puniſh the <hi>Practices</hi> and <hi>Doctrines</hi> of ſuch <hi>Abominations,</hi> &amp;c. But, are there but one ſort of <hi>(Religious) Mad Folks, Ranters?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>What is it but <hi>Ranting,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuters and Ranting, more ſores them one.</note> to call <hi>Fire</hi> from <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> (as the gratious <hi>Diſciples</hi> of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> did and may do) becauſe (as they think) men practice Inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilities (againſt the light of <hi>Nature</hi>) refuſing to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain the Son of <hi>God</hi> Chriſt Jeſus?</p>
            <p>What is it but <hi>Ranting,</hi> to forbid the very caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:118103:32"/>out of <hi>Devils</hi> (as done by Conjuration, <hi>Hereſie Blaſphemy,</hi> &amp;c.) becauſe theſe Exorciſts, theſe Caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters out, they follow not <hi>us, our</hi> Way, <hi>our</hi> Church, <hi>our</hi> Faith; <hi>our</hi> Worſhip? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea what is it but <hi>Rantiſme,</hi>
               <note place="margin">May Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences differing about the blood of Chriſt.</note> to ſling ſtones at the <hi>Conſcience</hi> of any, perſwaded to finde out the Blood of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in the way of dipping into Water; or at the Conſcience of the poor <hi>Iew,</hi> accounting of that blood as falſe and Counterfeit? or of the <hi>Papiſt,</hi> perſwaded that the <hi>Iewes</hi> are wanderers; but that there's need of <hi>Maries</hi> Milk to her Sons blood? or at the Conſciences of the <hi>Turkes,</hi> the <hi>Perſians,</hi> the <hi>Pagans,</hi> the millions of millions of millions of poor deluded Conſciences, whoſe oppoſitions the meek <hi>Lamb</hi> of <hi>God</hi> commandeth gently to be born, and his Servants patiently to wait, if yet it might pleaſe the <hi>God</hi> of Heaven to give <hi>Repentance,</hi> and a <hi>Reſcue</hi> from the ſnares and chaines of <hi>Satan</hi> and <hi>Deſtruction?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, If ever there was <hi>Ranting</hi> in this World, what is it, but the mad flinging about of <hi>Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brands, Arrows,</hi> and <hi>Death,</hi> (which <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks of) to fling all the World topſi-turvy, and to Fire the Nations with uncivil and irreligious <hi>Heats, Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults, Plundrings, Raviſhings, Slaughters,</hi> about the <hi>Hereticks,</hi> the <hi>Blaſphemers,</hi> the <hi>Diablo's?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And therefore (laſtly) I ask the <hi>Propoſer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in caſe the Old were not.</note> of theſe Queſtions, Whether in caſe it had pleaſed the <hi>Lord</hi> to conceal the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> from us, or that of the <hi>New</hi> bound up alone (as it is frequently) ſhould fall into the hands of ſome people in the World; I ask (I ſay) Whether, therein, <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> hath not left his Followers full, and compleat, and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:118103:33"/>abſolute Directions in all Caſes? I ask, then, in what part of his <hi>Teſtament,</hi> hath he given the leaſt <hi>Direction,</hi> for the Civil Sword to be drawn in his <hi>Quarrel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chriſt Jeſus no Author of civil force, againſt the higheſt of his oppoſites and Blaſphemers.</note> for the <hi>Body</hi> of any man to be afflicted for his <hi>ſake?</hi> and therefore in this caſe proclaims to his zealous <hi>Followers</hi> (who in this caſe did not know of what Spirits they were) that he came not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy mens <hi>Bodies,</hi> no not for the higheſt <hi>Oppoſition</hi> made againſt him; no not that of calling him <hi>Beel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zebub,</hi> and charging him with Sorcery, and caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of <hi>Devils</hi> by the <hi>Devil</hi> himſelf.</p>
            <p>Yet I ask, Whether in the very <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> it ſelf, ſuch <hi>Perſons,</hi> ſuch <hi>Nations</hi> aw were wholly Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, where puniſhed even by <hi>David</hi> himſelf; as the <hi>Moabites,</hi> the <hi>Ammonites,</hi> &amp;c. when they were ſubdued under him; although in the Land of <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> (the onely Church in Covenant with <hi>God</hi>) there were juſt Lawes in force againſt ſuch ſins and practices?</p>
            <p>I therefore conclude with this <hi>Queſtion,</hi> Whe-(notwithſtanding the <hi>Propoſers</hi> plea, of the qurity of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> diſcovering <hi>Idolatry</hi> more clearly) whether the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and <hi>Covenant</hi> it ſelf, Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, have not expreſly lockt up the hands of all that call his <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Maſter,</hi> ſaying, Let the <hi>Tares</hi> alone until the <hi>Harveſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſum of the fourteenth Queſtion.</p>
            <p>Whether, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>14</label> ſince <hi>Idolatry</hi> brings plagues upon the people, the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> ought not to deliver the people from thoſe plagues, by removing <hi>Idolatry?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:118103:33"/>
            <p>I ask, Firſt, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> ſince <hi>Idolatry</hi> is twofold (as before) Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and <hi>Moral;</hi> And making the <hi>Belly</hi> a <hi>God,</hi> or <hi>Gold</hi> a <hi>God,</hi> is as real <hi>Idolatry,</hi> as the making of the <hi>ſun</hi> a <hi>God;</hi> and the honouring, and loving, and ſerving them before the true <hi>God,</hi> is as real <hi>Idolatry,</hi> as the worſhipping of the <hi>ſun,</hi> or a <hi>Golden Image:</hi> As alſo, ſince <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> commands his people to ſeparate from a Covetous perſon, profeſſing to be a brother in <hi>Christ Ieſus,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5;</p>
            <p>With what face then, before the flaming Eyes of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> can we cry out ſo much againſt <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry</hi> in <hi>Worſhipping,</hi> and raiſe ſuch Sormes and Tempeſts in the World about <hi>Idolatry?</hi> &amp;c. When the whole World, and each Nation, and our Selves, lie in the ſecond kind of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> of many ſorts;<note place="margin">The World lies in Idolatry and this Nation, and People.</note> Worſhipping (according to the ſeveral Luſts of the <hi>Eye,</hi> the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and the <hi>Pride</hi> of Life) ſeveral ſorts of Creatures, before the Creator, <hi>God</hi> bleſſed for evermore. This kinde of <hi>Idolatry</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in <hi>Gods</hi> people, and eſpecially after ſo much light and experience from <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> abhors as much (having commanded it not to be named a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Saints) yea, and in ſome reſpect, above the groſſeſt <hi>Idolatry</hi> of all the World beſide. What <hi>Antichriſtian Blindneſs</hi> and <hi>Madneſs</hi> is it therefore to cry out, like the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Portugals,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The greater Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, cry out againſt the leſs.</note> againſt the poor <hi>Indians Idolatry;</hi> when beſides their owne <hi>Images</hi> and <hi>Superſtitions,</hi> they were notorious wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers of, and bowed down to the <hi>Indians Gold,</hi> which, to their aſtoniſhment, the <hi>Indians</hi> beheld and ſtumbled at?</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ask, Doth <hi>Idolatry</hi> alone, without a ripeneſs in other ſins, bring Plagues and Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:118103:34"/>upon Lands and Peoples?<note place="margin">Sodome,</note> Were not other fins al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged the cauſe of <hi>Sodoms</hi> deſtruction (one of the moſt fearful and moſt famous Deſtructions, ſince the beginning of the World) and among other ſins, that of oppreſſing the poor? and <hi>ſoul-oppreſſion</hi> is ſtill the higheſt.</p>
            <p>Was not <hi>Egypt</hi> the wonder of the World for Plagues?<note place="margin">and Egypt,</note> and though moſt in famous for <hi>Idolatry,</hi> yet was there not one Sin, which eſpecially unſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Vials of Plagues and Vengeance on them, to wit, their <hi>Oppreſſions,</hi> indeed their <hi>Soul-oppreſſions,</hi> on the Iſrael and people of <hi>God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is true,<note place="margin">and Iſrael,</note> 
               <hi>Gods</hi> people were guilty of <hi>Religious Idolatry,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36. but yet there was a <hi>remedy,</hi> until they mocked, and deſpiled, and miſuſed the Meſſengers from <hi>God,</hi> ſent unto them.</p>
            <p>Hence,<note place="margin">and Jeruſalem, deſtroyed for op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, and Soul-oppreſſion chiefly.</note> What was the complaint of the <hi>Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> againſt <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> when he wept over it, foreſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Deſtruction</hi> of it ſhortly after his death (in which Eleven hundred thouſand <hi>Iewes,</hi> Men, Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Children periſhed, and were captivated) What was his great complaint, but this, <hi>O Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, Ieruſalem, Thou which killest the Prophets, and ſtoneſt them which are ſent unto thee!</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And if that ſecond Wo (<hi>Rev.</hi> 9.) be the Plague of the <hi>Turks,</hi> upon the <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> World, beſide their <hi>Idolatries,</hi> read we not (verſe the laſt) <hi>That neither repented they of their. Murders, nor of their Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceries, nor of their Fornications, nor of their Thefts?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And when we read of the <hi>great Whore</hi> (common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly interpreted the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Reme,</hi> the greateſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed State of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> though moſt <hi>Whoriſh,</hi> in all abominable worſhips and practices, under the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:118103:34"/>pretence of being the moſt chaſt, and onely Spouſe of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi>) read we not alſo,<note place="margin">Oppreſſion and Bloudy Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, one chief cauſe of the downfall of the bloodie Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </note> before the <hi>tearing</hi> of her Fleſh, and <hi>burning</hi> of her, That ſhe is a <hi>Where;</hi> drunk with the blood of the <hi>Saints,</hi> and the <hi>Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> of <hi>Ieſus? Rev.</hi> 17. And when (<hi>Re.</hi> 18.) three fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous cauſes are aſſigned, of her moſt famous <hi>down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fal,</hi> is not this among the reſt, a principal one, that in her is found <hi>Bloody Oppreſſions,</hi> to wit, (verſe the laſt) the blood of the <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Saints,</hi> and of all that were ſlain upon the earth?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I ask, Whether that place of <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 1. ſpeak not there onely of <hi>ſpiritual plagues,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Spiritual plagues follow abuſe of light.</note> and not of Gods puniſhing ſins with <hi>temporal plagues;</hi> but of puniſhing <hi>ſin</hi> with <hi>ſin;</hi> and implies no more; but that God <hi>juſtly</hi> puniſheth mankinde, for his abuſe of, and not improving of all his Light, (though but <hi>moral, civil, natural</hi>) with a ſpirit and conſcience <hi>hardned,</hi> and delivered up to <hi>further alienation</hi> from him, into ſeveral degrees and ſorts of ſin and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs?</p>
            <p>What hinders this, but that ſuch as have ſome <hi>convictions</hi> of a <hi>Deity,</hi> and yet improve not theſe <hi>convictions</hi> to the higheſt, but worſhip that <hi>Deity</hi> corruptly, That ſuch (I ſay) yet ought to be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to live, and are not to be deſtroyed as <hi>Idolaters</hi> and <hi>Blaſphemers,</hi> yea and with meekneſs ought to be inſtructed, if peradventure it may pleaſe God to give them <hi>repentance,</hi> that they may recover them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves out of the ſnare of the devil, whereby they are taken captive as his will: <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>Yea, I pray leave humbly to ask, without of offence, What if ſome <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. or <hi>Her.</hi> 5. ſhould riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and that in a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> profeſſion, and conquer
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:118103:35"/>
               <hi>France,</hi> as thoſe Kings did; yea, ſuppoſe that <hi>France</hi> ſhould conquer <hi>England,</hi> What ſhould the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like conqueror</hi> do with ſo many thouſand <hi>Proteſtant Hereticks,</hi> ſo accounted? And what ſhould the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant conqueror</hi> do with ſo many hundred thouſand <hi>Popiſh Idolaters</hi> in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> yea ſuppoſe all the world over?</p>
            <p>I know what ſome furious <hi>Zelots</hi> would ſay, on either ſide; I know what <hi>Superſtition,</hi> what <hi>ſelf-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt,</hi> what intemperate and unbridled <hi>Zeal,</hi> heath done in former and and preſent times: But I ask, what <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> would do, what the meek <hi>Lamb</hi> of <hi>God</hi> would do, who tells his fiery Diſciples in ſuch caſes, <hi>Luke</hi> 9. you know not what <hi>Spirit</hi> you are of; <hi>I came not to deſtroy mens lives, but to ſave them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">The Land of Canaan a figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative Land, it and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple attended with miracles.</note> As to that particular cafe of the <hi>Land</hi> of <hi>Canaan,</hi> I ask, whether that <hi>Land</hi> and <hi>Nation,</hi> the people of it, whom the Land ſpued out, and the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> whom the Land recieved, were not all of them <hi>typical</hi> and <hi>figurative,</hi> and attended with <hi>extracrdinary, ſupernatural,</hi> and <hi>miraculouus</hi> Conſiderations? Further, may we not as well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, to paſs over to <hi>Ireland, France,</hi> or <hi>Holland,</hi> on dry land (as <hi>Iſrael</hi> from <hi>Egypt</hi> toward <hi>Canaan</hi>-land) and to tumble down City Wals and Caſtles, with the ſound of <hi>Rams-hornes,</hi> &amp;c. at to think of a material or literal <hi>Antitype</hi> or parallel, now in theſe Goſpel-daies?</p>
            <p>Hath not the irreconcileable <hi>Diſproportion</hi> and <hi>Diſſimilitude,</hi> between that Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and all others, been alleadged by ſome, againſt the moſt conſcientious and able in this Controverſie, Maſter <hi>Cotton,</hi> and that without any reply of his, or any
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:118103:35"/>man elſe, as unto that great Argument, of the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and all other Lands that are, or ever have been, or ſhall be?</p>
            <p>And ſince the Propoſer of this Queſtion is pleaſed to mention <hi>Lev.</hi> 20. I ask, Is not this the Ground, even of <hi>Iſraels ceremonial</hi> and <hi>typical</hi> holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, touching their not eating of Swines Fleſh,<note place="margin">Iſrael a Nation ſeparated from all Lands to God.</note> and all unclean Beaſts and Fowl? verſe 25. I am <hi>Iehovah</hi> you <hi>God,</hi> who have ſeparated you from other people: and verſe 25. Therefore I have ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated theſe unclean Beaſts and Fowle from you, as unclean: and verſe 26. You ſhall be holy unto me, for I <hi>Iehovah</hi> am holy, and have ſevered you from other People, that you ſhould be mine.</p>
            <p>Did not all theſe unclean Beaſts and Birds, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie men in <hi>Goſpel</hi>-times, from whom we ought not to ſeparate in civil converſe, as the <hi>Iews</hi> did, <hi>Act.</hi> 10. for then we muſt go out of the World, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. but in ſpiritual communion and Worſhipping of <hi>God,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. Come out from among them, and be ye ſeparated, and touch no unclean thing, and I Will recieve you, and be a <hi>Father</hi> unto you, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Iſrael and people of God, the onely type of Gods Iſrael in Canaan.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Doth not Maſter <hi>Cotton</hi> himſelf acknowledge, that this puniſhing of the <hi>Idolater,</hi> in the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> was <hi>typical,</hi> and that the <hi>Antitype</hi> is onely the <hi>Church</hi> of Chriſt, which ought not to purge out <hi>Idolaters:</hi> which Church (whether Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, as Maſter <hi>Cotton</hi> holds) or National, as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; Yet I ask, what weapons hath either the one or the other, as Chriſts Church, or Wiſe, but Spiritual? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> what can be then the Reſult from this, <hi>Lev.</hi> 20. but that the <hi>Iſrael</hi> and people of <hi>God,</hi> who are (<hi>Nazarites,</hi> or) ſeparated unto him, from
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:118103:36"/>all the people of the World, ought to touch no uncleanneſs; and not onely to ſeparate from <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Idolatry,</hi>
               <note place="margin">All Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</note> but even to ſeparate from, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor that <hi>Moral Idolatry, Covetouſneſs,</hi> and to hold no Spiritual Society with that man, being calld a Saint or Brother, who covets this Worlds goods? which thing, is not to be once named, among the Saints, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>But fifthly, I ask, What is this to all the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <hi>World,</hi> who, as <hi>Nations,</hi> are all parts of the <hi>World,</hi> and lie (faith <hi>Iohn</hi>) in wickedneſs, in Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries and Superſtitions, rolling and changing as Waves of the Sea, in reſtleſs Luſts, and Paſſions of all ſorts? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Did not <hi>God</hi> wink at the Nations, <hi>Act.</hi> 17. and is he not ſtill pleaſed to wink at thoſe numberleſs Nations of the <hi>World,</hi> unto whom the ſound of a <hi>Saviour</hi> reacheth not?<note place="margin">The State of all the numberleſs numbers of the Sons of men, without Chriſt in the world.</note> How wonderful are the Dominions of the <hi>Grand Seigniour</hi> (the <hi>Turkiſh Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour</hi>) and the mighty Empire of the <hi>Perſians,</hi> the great <hi>Mogul,</hi> the <hi>Chinois,</hi> the <hi>Tartars,</hi> and the many millions of millions of the Sons and Daughters of Men, who in all Ages and Nations paſs on in outward Peace, Proſperity and Glory, amongſt ſome of whom, <hi>God</hi> may call ſome to fear him, and love the <hi>Lord Ieſus?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But for any of theſe whole Nations to be become <hi>Chriſtians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A National Church a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and not found in Chriſts Testament.</note> that is, to be anointed with Chriſts Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits; I ask, Whether ſuch a thing be found in <hi>Chriſts Teſtament,</hi> or be in experience true, of the Body of this, or any other Nation?</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Whatever be the <hi>pretence</hi> and <hi>miſt,</hi> which Satan caſteth, I ask (with a famous obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:118103:36"/>once <hi>Lord Chancellour</hi> of <hi>England</hi>) Whether all <hi>Violence</hi> in <hi>Religion,</hi> be not for ſome ſiniſter cauſe and <hi>Intereſt? Jehu</hi> pretends and boaſts, Come, ſee my zeal for the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> &amp;c. He acted glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly,<note place="margin">Magistrates act zealouſly for an Interest.</note> with wonderful <hi>Activity, Impartiality,</hi> and <hi>(ſeeming) Piety;</hi> And yet I will viſit the blood of <hi>Jehu,</hi> ſaith the Lord (<hi>Hoſ.</hi> 1.) for, he took not heed with all his Heart, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For, having got the Throne of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> to maintain that <hi>Throne</hi> and <hi>Crown,</hi> he goes on in the ſins of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> and kept up ſtill the worſhip of the Calves, which <hi>Jeroboam</hi> had ſet up.</p>
            <p>What a wonderful noyſe an ſound have thoſe three Greek names, <hi>Idolatry, Hereſie, Blaſphemy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The World ſcar'd by ſtrange names.</note> made in the world, to the ſcaring and affrightment of poor people, in both <hi>Popiſh</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries? But let the Zeal of the moſt Zealous out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cries be examined in <hi>plain Engliſh,</hi> and let the Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous (even ſuch as make profeſſion of the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed National Miniſteries, in the moſt Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Churches</hi>) I ſay, lot the moſt Zealous impartially Examine; and it ſhall be found, that the <hi>Bottome</hi> and <hi>Root</hi> of the matter, is a plain Merchandizing with the word of <hi>God,</hi> and as it, was in <hi>Rome,</hi> and is (<hi>Omnia Roma, cum precis,</hi> &amp;c) a very Sale of <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Goſpel, Moſes</hi> and <hi>Chriſt, Heaven</hi> and <hi>Hell, God</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and the Soules of men.</p>
            <p>I truely honour the many excellent <hi>Perſons,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ministers pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend zealouſly but for an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt.</note> and the excellent <hi>Abilities,</hi> both humane and <hi>Divine,</hi> of many, that have profeſt, and do, the Nations <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery</hi> or <hi>Service.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I confeſs, there is a due of <hi>Temporals,</hi> to ſuch as Miniſter <hi>Spirituals;</hi> but withall I ask, What is it
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:118103:37"/>but a <hi>Trade</hi> and <hi>Living,</hi> but a <hi>Merchandiſing</hi> for <hi>gain,</hi> when men profeſs they cannot, without ſo much or ſo much, preach Chriſt Jeſus?</p>
            <p>Surely the <hi>Apoſtacia</hi> hath been moſt wonderful and dreadful.<note place="margin">The mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Chriſts true Miniſters.</note> None can ſay but that the Lord Jeſus did ſend out ſuch Preachers of his Truth, as did <hi>truſt him,</hi> and <hi>Lacked nothing;</hi> who did as <hi>freely give,</hi> as <hi>freely</hi> they had <hi>received;</hi> who did labour <hi>ſpiritually,</hi> and, upon defect of ſupplies (through the <hi>poverty</hi> or <hi>coldneſs</hi> of the Saints) did labour with their own hands: and other courſe for his <hi>Meſſengers</hi> (in moſt infinite wiſdom) took he none, nor will his <hi>true Miniſters</hi> and <hi>Prophets</hi> deſire he ſhould: and whatever other <hi>Prudential</hi> Images and Inventions are ſet up, will he diſclaim and judge, when he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in flaming fire, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſhould be ſo free in the world,<note place="margin">What more free, and yet what more bought and ſold then light?</note> as <hi>divine</hi> and <hi>heavenly light?</hi> and yet what is ſo frequently and ſo dearly ſold, as <hi>that Light?</hi> (I ſpeak as to the <hi>external</hi> preaching of many holy Truths.)</p>
            <p>I ſhall deſire to be <hi>corrected,</hi> if <hi>Ierre</hi> in the <hi>Piety</hi> or <hi>Charity</hi> of the <hi>Queſtion;</hi> and ask, If any man can poſſibly, by <hi>rules</hi> of Chriſt Jeſus, profeſs a <hi>Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> to him and his? Yea, although he have ſo much <hi>Civility,</hi> as not to make a <hi>Bargain,</hi> for ſo much or ſo much; yet if there be an implicite Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation or Dependance, upon ſuch a Service or <hi>Miniſtery,</hi> for a <hi>Salary,</hi> maintenance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ask, (Whatever the <hi>Perſon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mercenary light</note> his <hi>Gifts, Experiences, Light</hi> be) whether is Calling and Standing be not as truely <hi>Mercenary</hi> and <hi>Unchriſtian,</hi> as his that ſtands at the Corners of the Streets in dark <hi>Nights,</hi> with
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:118103:37"/>ready lights and linkes, offering to go with any call (preſuming on a pay) and therefor his word is to every <hi>likely</hi> paſſenger, Will you have a light Sir?</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I ask, Whether (as the <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> ſpeaks of falſe <hi>Prophets</hi>) we any not diſcern falſe Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines,<note place="margin">Bloody fruits of a (pretended) holy Root.</note> Tenents, and Opinions, by the horrible fruits, which this bitter <hi>Root</hi> hath brought forth, to the ſlaughter of ſo many thouſands, and ten thouſand times then thouſand of mankinde, Religiouſly and Zealouſly (as it pretended) hunting one another, as wild <hi>Beaſts, Monſters, Idolaters, Hereticks Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Yea, And which may cauſe a Soul, truly in love with <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> to tremble; this above all other, hath been that bloody Knife, that hath ſo many thouſand and then thouſand times ſtab'd the <hi>Lord Ieſus</hi> to the Heart, in the bloody <hi>hunting</hi> of ſo many his Servants and Followers, as the greateſt <hi>Hereticks, Blaſphemers,</hi> &amp;c. both in this and other Nations.</p>
            <p>The ſum of the fifteenth Queſtion.</p>
            <p>Whether the Examiner hath not ſet himſelf to confute <hi>Paul,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>15</label> ſaying it is not eaſie to finde, that the <hi>Heathen</hi> ſhould not make a <hi>Graven Image;</hi> nor any marvel, that they ſhould by the forme of ſome Creature, repreſent him, &amp;c. Whereas <hi>Paul</hi> proves, that the Eternal power and <hi>Godhead,</hi> are ſo manifeſt, that they are without excuſe,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:118103:38"/>who knowing God, do not glorifie him as God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but change the glory of God into an <hi>Image? &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">Andſw.</note> I ask, Whether the <hi>Propoſer</hi> of theſe Queſtions expreſſeth not very little of that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <hi>Moderation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Examiner unchriſtianly dealt with.</note> and <hi>Equity,</hi> and <hi>Equanimity</hi> of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which a Follower of Chriſt Jeſus pretends to, in ſetting the words (which bear a better ſence) yea and the Heart of the <hi>Examiner</hi> upon the Rack, by infinuating little leſs, then that he hath ſet himſelf to contradict and fight againſt <hi>God</hi> himſelf, and his moſt holy Spirit in <hi>Paul,</hi> his Servant and Penman? Whereas a more ſober and Dove-like <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Eye will read no more, but a faithful and <hi>Chriſtian</hi> plea, for moderate and <hi>Chriſtian</hi> thoughts, to all the Nations and Generations of the World; who although by the hightned power of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> they may poſſibly attaine to (as above hath been diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed, by the light of <hi>Nature</hi>) many Convictions and Confeſſions of a <hi>Godhead;</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Natural e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtute of all and the very best of mankind.</note> Yet is it not ſo facile and eaſie for them (having ſo many thouſand clogs and chaines, of barbarous Ignorance, and <hi>Education,</hi> and <hi>Luſts</hi> hanging on them) to ſoare ſo high, with the wings of meer <hi>Natural</hi> corrupted Reaſon, as to to finde the true <hi>God,</hi> and the true <hi>Way</hi> of glorify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>God</hi> acceptably in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> Yea I ask, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this is poſſible to be attained unto (as above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid?) But rather that this place of <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 1. implies, that the wiſeſt and moſt induſtrious of the Sons of Men, will be found guilty of groſs Negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and undervaluing of <hi>God,</hi> and of being inſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by many corrupt <hi>Luſts, Examples, Cuſtomes,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:118103:38"/>Fear</hi> of men, <hi>Tradition</hi> of Fathers, and of not improv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and underſtanding in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo far, and ſo high, as they ought and might alſo do?</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ask, If it be eaſie for the Nations of the <hi>World</hi> to eſcape and miſs theſe Rocks of <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,<note place="margin">All the Nations of the World, wandring in I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition.</note> Superſtition, Will-worſhip,</hi> &amp;c. how comes it to paſs, that all the <hi>Generations</hi> of mankinde, from the firſt <hi>Creation</hi> and <hi>Fall</hi> of Man to this day (the <hi>Phoeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians,</hi> the <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> the <hi>Perſians,</hi> the <hi>Grecians,</hi> the <hi>Romans,</hi> and the many millions of mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of wiſe and underſtanding men, not onely the <hi>Pagans,</hi> but the <hi>Turks,</hi> the <hi>Iewes,</hi> the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and carnal <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> ſhould ſo ſtupendiouſly and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly wander from the glorifying of <hi>God,</hi> as <hi>God,</hi> but by invented <hi>Images,</hi> and <hi>Repreſentations</hi> of <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, Will-worſhip,</hi> darken his <hi>Glory?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If it be ſo eaſie to eſcape <hi>Idolatry, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition: Will-worſhip,</hi> &amp;c. How is it that the holy Spirit record, how eaſily, how wonderfully,<note place="margin">Gods owne peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and choiceſt Servants hardly kept from Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition and Will-worſhip, &amp;c.</note> and fearfully, <hi>Gods</hi> owne people (<hi>Aaron</hi> the Leader, and all <hi>Iſrael</hi> with him) ſlipt into the <hi>Idolatry</hi> of the <hi>Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Calf?</hi> yea and afterwards, the whole ten Tribes of twelve (Gods owne people) apoſtate to the <hi>Calves</hi> (againe) of <hi>Jeroboam?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How is it, that not onely the Godly <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Iudah,</hi> neglected the demoliſhing of the high pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and the reforming of what was notoriouſly Superſtitious, and that not onely <hi>Solomon</hi> built houſes for the gods of his Wives, but even <hi>David,</hi> and thirty thouſand of <hi>Iſrael</hi> with him, brings up the Arke of <hi>God</hi> (the ſigne of <hi>Gods</hi> preſence) with wonderfull Solemnities ſhootings and rejoycings,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:118103:39"/>until they met with <hi>Perez-Uzzah,</hi> the <hi>Breach</hi> of <hi>Uz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zah,</hi> the ſignal of <hi>Gods</hi> diſpleaſure?</p>
            <p>How is it, that not onely many ſhall ſeek to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſhall not be able;<note place="margin">Chriſt Ieſus not eaſily found of, not onely preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, but Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial Intenders.</note> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> obtained not that which they ſought for, as it is written, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. But even the tender <hi>Love,</hi> and <hi>Dove,</hi> and undefiled of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> (<hi>Cant.</hi> 5.) riſing up to open to her <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved,</hi> ſhe findes him agrieved at her unkindneſs, and gone; ſhe ſought him, but ſhe found him not; ſhe called him, but he gave no anſwer?</p>
            <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">The diviſions of Reuben, yea e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of Iudah.</note> How is it, that not onely <hi>God</hi> ſendeth <hi>Antichriſtians</hi> ſtrong <hi>Deluſions,</hi> which ſo hold their <hi>Understanding, Conſcience, Iudgement, and Affections,</hi> that they really belive <hi>Lyes,</hi> notorious and great <hi>Lyes;</hi> but even at this <hi>Day</hi> among our ſelves, the Conſciences of <hi>Gods</hi> children and people (in whom the bleſſed fear and love of <hi>God</hi> hath ſhined) how are they (I ſay) divided each from other, not onely <hi>Ephraim</hi> againſt <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> and <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> againſt <hi>Ephraim,</hi> and both againſt <hi>Iudah,</hi> but even <hi>Iudah</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Iudah,</hi> Inſomuch that <hi>Gods</hi> people at this day have not onely occaſioned that reproachfull terme of <hi>Sectaries;</hi> becauſe of their <hi>ſeparation</hi> from the <hi>National Churches,</hi> gathering themſelves into <hi>ſeparate</hi> Congregations, but even from their <hi>Sects</hi> and <hi>Diviſions</hi> among themſelves? And I ask, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this ſhall not be, and muſt continue, until the bleſſed time of <hi>one</hi> Heart, and <hi>one</hi> Spirit, and <hi>one</hi> Lip, which <hi>God</hi> will vouchſafe to all his people?</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Since every Way, <hi>Manner</hi> or <hi>Form</hi> of <hi>Worſhip,</hi> of <hi>Church,</hi> of <hi>Miniſtery,</hi> of <hi>Prayer,</hi> of <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme,</hi> &amp;c. (that onely excepted which the <hi>Lord Ieſus</hi> appointed) is an Invention, an <hi>Image,</hi> a molten
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:118103:39"/>or <hi>carved Image;</hi> And conſequently,<note place="margin">Gods people full of Images, how much more the Nations.</note> the many ſtrange waies, and kindes, and formes of <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Churches, <hi>National, Provincial, Dioceſan, Parochi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, Preſbyterian, Independent, Separated, Half-ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, Baptized</hi> one way, a <hi>ſecond,</hi> a <hi>third</hi> way (as to their various Formes and Conſtitutions) are but <hi>Images</hi> and <hi>Pictures,</hi> and none but one of them (if any of them be yet) according to the firſt pattern; And ſince Gods own people, have had a great ſhare and hand in ſuch framings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> both in <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, France, Low-Countries,</hi> &amp;c. I ask, If it be not much more eaſie for the poor <hi>Nations</hi> of the World, who ſit in darkneſs (as of old) to erect Images of <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Silver, Wood, Stone,</hi> &amp;c. and of late, <hi>Waies</hi> and <hi>Manners</hi> of <hi>Worſhip</hi> (though more ſubtle and myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, yet) as real <hi>Images,</hi> as thoſe of the groſſeſt Compoſition?</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I ask, If there be not a deep and heaven-deſigne,<note place="margin">Gods deſigne to ſuffer the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and his own people, to wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and feel the want of his holy Spirit, in the uſe of all means.</note> of the moſt holy and onely wiſe <hi>God,</hi> thus to ſuffer the world and his people alſo, to divide and ſcatter, and diſſipate themſelves; Thus to cauſe the holy <hi>Scriptures,</hi> amongſt both <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> (the pretended Rule of <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Light</hi> unto all their waies and Conſciences) to be ſo Pen'd, ſo Written, ſo tranſlated, that as it was ſaid of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> he was given for a ſtumbling <hi>Block,</hi> and <hi>Rock</hi> of offence, as well as for a <hi>Rock</hi> and <hi>Foundation</hi> to his people: So, may it not alſo be ſaid of the holy <hi>Scripture,</hi> and the texts and writings thereof, from whence ſo many, and ſo wonderfully different per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions and Conſciences are riſen?</p>
            <p>In particular, I ask, If it have not been wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully eaſie, from the ſeeming light of <hi>Nature</hi> and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:118103:40"/>
               <hi>Scripture</hi> too, to ſlide into the many <hi>wandrings</hi> and <hi>Labyrinths</hi> of conſciences now extant, which though but <hi>Threds</hi> and <hi>Strawes,</hi> yet do hold the conſcience as with Chaines of <hi>Adamant,</hi> until the holy and bleſſed Spirit of <hi>God</hi> diſcover and diſſolve? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If there be any Bowells (therefore) of pity in us, toward poor ſinners, like our ſelves; If any ſence of the mercies and pitie of Chriſt Ieſus to our ſelves, How ſhould we compaſſionate the Captiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and (ſometimes) the ſtriving and relucting ſouls of thouſands, about theſe and the like Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons?</p>
            <p>How many thouſands and ten thouſands of <hi>Gods</hi> ancient Friends and Acquaintance,<note place="margin">The Iewes Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious plea from Scripture.</note> the <hi>Iewes,</hi> will ſay unto us, How can that <hi>Ieſus</hi> whom you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, be the true <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> the anointed of <hi>God,</hi> he whom all the <hi>Prophets</hi> told of, whom all the Fathers lookt for? How did he deliver us from the <hi>Roman</hi> yoakes? how hath he redeemed us, theſe 1600 years ſince, from all our Enemies, in the Lands of our Diſperſions and Scatterings?</p>
            <p>How many thouſand <hi>Papiſts</hi> will tell us, that <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> the Son of <hi>Mary,</hi> he is the bleſſed <hi>Meſſiah</hi> that was to come? and why ſhould we not believe him, that plainly ſaid, This is my <hi>Body?</hi> Is he not able to make good his word, in a real and corporal pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence? Did he not ſay to <hi>Peter,</hi> thou art <hi>Peter,</hi> and upon this <hi>Rock</hi> will I build my <hi>Church;</hi> To thee will I give the <hi>Keys</hi> of the kingdom of heaven?</p>
            <p>How many thouſand will tell us, that the great and wonderful <hi>myſtery</hi> of the <hi>holy Trinity</hi> is beyond their underſtanding and reach; and they cannot <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve</hi> and <hi>die for</hi> that which paſſeth their compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion;
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:118103:40"/>as alſo, that the <hi>knots</hi> of <hi>holy Scripture</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thoſe of <hi>Reaſon</hi>) are very great and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful?</p>
            <p>How many thouſands are perſwaded that the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>Orders</hi> in the government of Chriſts <hi>Houſe</hi> and <hi>Kingdom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The ſeveral conſcientious pleas of the more knowing and most godly perſons in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note> are not manifeſted in vain unto us, in the Word of God, &amp; in particular, the order of <hi>Biſhops?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor are there thouſands and then thouſands want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, who will (triumphantly) ask us, What that <hi>lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the hands of the Presbytery</hi> was?</p>
            <p>How many Conſciences will ask how we can dare to ſay, that Chriſt Jeſus <hi>died not for all,</hi> when ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Scriptures ſpeak of the <hi>propitiation</hi> for the ſins of the <hi>whole world?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And why (ſay they) ſhall the power of <hi>Nature</hi> be ſo ſlighted, when Chriſt Jeſus tells us, that <hi>he would,</hi> but <hi>Jeruſalem would not?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And how is <hi>that doctrine</hi> (ſay they) ſo infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, of the <hi>impoſsibility</hi> of a <hi>final breach</hi> between <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> and <hi>Believers;</hi> when ſo many <hi>Caveats, Warnings, Items,</hi> are given us nor to fall; and ſo many <hi>dreadful examples</hi> (eſpecially in theſe times) of the departure of ſo many from <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> to the <hi>world</hi> with <hi>Demas</hi> and <hi>Judas,</hi> to <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> with <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> to <hi>luſts,</hi> and <hi>pleaſures,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>abominations,</hi> with the <hi>ſtony ground?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How many are aſſaulted by Satan, to queſtion the <hi>Godhead</hi> of the Son of God, and of the Holy Spirit, and of the <hi>truth</hi> of the holy Scriptures; Whether there are <hi>no more</hi> holy Scriptures but theſe; and whether the <hi>Tranſlations</hi> and infallible, and which are to be <hi>reſted</hi> or <hi>relied on?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh how <hi>merciful,</hi> how <hi>pitiful</hi> are the bowels of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:118103:41"/>the <hi>Lamb</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> to poor wandring ſinners? And how <hi>ſierce,</hi> how <hi>cruel</hi> are the thoughts of his <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival Antichrist,</hi> who makes it ſo caſie to be born againe, to have Gods Spirit, to the Orthodox, to be truely Zealous againſt <hi>Idolaters, Blaſphemers, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks? &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſum of the ſixteenth Queſtion.</p>
            <p>Whether <hi>Idolaters</hi> may not be puniſhed, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>16</label> becauſe the Magiſtrate doth not know the heart of the <hi>Idolaters;</hi> and whether this op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth not the word of God by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the puniſhment of the worſhippers of the <hi>Calfe,</hi> and <hi>Baal,</hi> and the Prophets of <hi>Baal?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Unto which may be added the ſeventeenth Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <hi>viz:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVhether <hi>Idolaters</hi> may not be convinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Acts, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>17</label> as well as a <hi>Murtherer,</hi> and thereby the heart of the <hi>Idolater</hi> is diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red? for the <hi>Murtherer</hi> is diſcovered guilty, becauſe of Malice in his heart.</p>
            <p>As alſo the eighteenth.</p>
            <p>VVhether of two ſins, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>18</label> that which is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned ought not to be puniſhed; becauſe the other is not puniſhed, for want of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning?</p>
            <p>Firſt, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Not to reſpect what hath been ſaid, as
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:118103:41"/>to the Diſtinction of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> as to the nature of ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil <hi>Magiſtracie</hi> and its power, the different diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations of <hi>God,</hi> divers times, and divers waies, and at laſt by his Son; To the Fathers in familes, to <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets</hi> in the typical Land of <hi>Ganaan,</hi> and at laſt all the world over, by his moſt glorious and dear Son, <hi>God</hi> bleſſed for ever!</p>
            <p>I ask, firſt, Whether the <hi>Examiner</hi> can be fairly charged, to bring it in as a reaſon, that <hi>Idolatry</hi> ſhould not be puniſhed, becauſe the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> doth not know the heart of the <hi>Idolater?</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Spaniards ſacrificing mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of mtn to that grand Ido! of the world, the Indian gold</note> And will all that the Examiner ſpeaks there of the heart, be fairly caſt up and amount to more, then the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned diſtinction of <hi>Religious</hi> and moral <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> and that opened by that ſo famous inſtance of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> in the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> who cryed out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the poor <hi>Indians, Idolaters, Idolaters, Heathens,</hi> worſhippers of the <hi>Sun;</hi> and yet themſelves did moſt notoriouſly bow down to the Golden <hi>God,</hi> the Indians <hi>Gold</hi> (as all <hi>Europes</hi> Nations, and <hi>England</hi> more or leſs) and in a ſordid and bloody devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, did ſacrifice to that Golden <hi>Images,</hi> ſo many thouſands, yea millions of the Inhabitants? It is incredible how many millions of mankind were there deſtroyed (as their own <hi>Cardinal</hi> — wrote to the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth) as <hi>Idolaters, Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemers,</hi> &amp;<hi>c.</hi> But it is very credible and eaſie to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, what ſtumbling blocks, ſuch their <hi>Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>Cruelties</hi> were, to the poor <hi>Indians,</hi> inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that they abhorr'd to hear the <hi>Spaniſh Prieſts</hi> to talk of Heaven, whither the <hi>Spaniards</hi> were ſaid to go; whoſe Covetouſneſs and Cruelties they thought would never ſend them to a place of Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:118103:42"/>
            <p>Secondly, I ask, Whether thoſe Examples of puniſhing the <hi>Worſhippers</hi> of the <hi>Calfe,</hi> and of <hi>Baal,</hi> and of <hi>Baals Prieſts,</hi> are preſidential and binding unto all the Nations of the World? And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Paralleling of all Times, to that ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Time,<note place="margin">The new piecing up of the vaile of the temple.</note> and all places to that typical and ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al place, be not indeed (upon the point) a new piecing up of the vaile of the <hi>Temple,</hi> which the right hand of the <hi>God</hi> of Heaven hath rent, and a preferring of <hi>Moſes</hi> the Servant, before the <hi>Lerd Feſus</hi> the Son, yea and (conſequently) a denying of the <hi>Lord Ieſus,</hi> the great Meſſiah, to be yet come?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I ask, If theſe Examples be now pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidential,<note place="margin">The Biſhops root and branch, and all faiſe Miniſters ought to be put to death.</note> Whether if there were ſuch Civil <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates Monarchs</hi> of the world as formerly (yea and however) whether it be not the duty of all the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> in the World, to deſtroy (even beyond all compare and Imagination) the greateſt part, if not almoſt all the Inhabitants of the whole World, for ſome falſe Worſhip, <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and one Golden <hi>Calf</hi> or another?</p>
            <p>Yea I ask, Whether by this rule, the State of <hi>England,,</hi> then favouring the <hi>Nonconformitant</hi> and <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> ought not onely to have aboliſhed <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy</hi> (branch and root) but alſo to have ſlain the Biſhops by the ſword? And by this rule, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all falſe and <hi>Antichriſtian Miniſters,</hi> whether <hi>Biſhops, Prieſts, Monks, Friers, Parſons, Vicars, Curates, Deanes, Doctors, Chaplains,</hi> &amp;<hi>c.</hi> yea and all ſeveral <hi>Prieſts</hi> in the World, ought not without mercy to be put to death?</p>
            <p>Yea, I ask, If this State of <hi>England</hi> ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:118103:42"/>the <hi>Presbytery</hi> of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> &amp;<hi>c.</hi> as falſe:<note place="margin">Presbyterian and Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Miniſters put to death.</note> And if another <hi>Power</hi> or <hi>Parliament</hi> ſhould revolve, in the conſtant turning of the Wheeles of <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi>) and ſhould condemn the Independent <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> to be as falſe as <hi>Presbyters;</hi> Where will this bloody Iſſue ſtop? What Heaps upon Heaps? How would (by this Doctrine) not onely this hopeful <hi>Commonweal,</hi> but alſo the whole world, be turned to <hi>Shambles,</hi> and <hi>Akeldama's,</hi> Fields of blood? for muſt we not ſlay the worſhippers of <hi>Calves</hi> as <hi>Baal,</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> did?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, As to the inſtance of Murther, I ask, If there be not three apparent differences between <hi>civil</hi> crimes againſt the State, and thoſe of <hi>ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi> nature againſt God, his worſhip? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, There are no generations of men, nor ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver were in the world, but by the dark light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, have condemned theſe four ſins, <hi>viz. Murther,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Four ſins which all mankinde have agreed to condemn not ſo about Religion.</note> 
               <hi>Adultery, Theſt, Lying,</hi> as inconſiſtent to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe of man with man: But all the Generations and Nations of men, have moſt conſtantly differed, and varied into many thouſand differences about the true <hi>God,</hi> and his waies of worſhip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Thoſe four ſorts of Sinners, <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers, Adulterers, Thieves</hi> and <hi>Lyers,</hi> are eaſily convinced and aſhamed (<hi>Ier.</hi> 6.) they cannot but confeſs themſelves ſinners, and juſtly puniſhed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But <hi>Idolaters</hi> all the world over are ready to cry out (houres, and yeares,<note place="margin">Civil tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernable them, Spirituals.</note> and ages together) Great is our <hi>Diana.</hi> And however (<hi>Tit.</hi> 3.) an <hi>Heretick</hi> or obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, withdrawn from <hi>Chriſts</hi> admonition, hath ſome checkings and convincings in his owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; yet both <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and <hi>Turkes,</hi> and <hi>Iews,</hi> and
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:118103:43"/>
               <hi>Pagans</hi> that are ſerious, have trampled over Poſts and Priſons, Torments and Deaths, to keep their Conſciences.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">Without Civil Order, no Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; without ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, no Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity.</note> Without ſome Order of <hi>Civiltie</hi> (more or leſs) ſome civil Officers of <hi>Iuſtice</hi> to puniſh thoſe four ſins (eſpecially) it is impoſſible that men can live (as men, and not as Beaſts or worſe) together, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But notwithſtanding ſeveral <hi>Religions</hi> in one <hi>Nation,</hi> in one <hi>Shire,</hi> yea in one <hi>Family;</hi> if men be either truly <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> like unto <hi>Chriſt. Feſus,</hi> whom they pretend to follow, or but truly <hi>Civil,</hi> and walk but by the rules of <hi>Humanity</hi> and <hi>Civility;</hi> Families, Townes, Cities, and Commonweals (in the midſt of <hi>Spiritual Differences</hi>) may flouriſh.</p>
            <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">Spiritual plagues the ſoreſt.</note> I ask, As to the puniſhing of the <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> and all other tranſgreſſions of Spiritual account, Are, the wounds and deaths of the two edged ſword, proceeding from the mouth of <hi>Chriſt Feſus,</hi> little, and of no eſtimation with us? Are <hi>Levi</hi>'s impartiall ſlayings of <hi>Brethren, Siſters, Fathers, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> &amp;<hi>c.</hi> (<hi>Deut.</hi> 33.) Is the delivering up of the Nations of the world (<hi>Rom.</hi> 1.) to ſuch unnatural and monſtrous <hi>Luſts,</hi> And the Chaines of ſtrong <hi>Lyes</hi> and <hi>Deluſions</hi> upon all the <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> World, no dread nor terrour with us? <hi>Ephraim</hi> is joyned to Idols, let him alone (eſpecially now in more ſpiritual and Goſpel-times) is far more dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and horrible ten thouſand ſold, then cutting off for murther, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I end this Queſtion,<note place="margin">A fourth plague added to the three of Davids choice.</note> with this <hi>Quere:</hi> If it had pleaſed the moſt holy and onely wiſe, to have added one Judgement more to <hi>Davids</hi> choice of the three ſore plagues, <hi>Sword, Famine,</hi> and <hi>Peſtilence;</hi> I ſay
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:118103:43"/>If he had been pleaſed to add a fourth, to wit, a giving up to the leaſt of ſins, the leaſt hiding of his holy <hi>Countenance,</hi> &amp;<hi>c.</hi> would not <hi>David,</hi> yea our ſelves (if our Hearts be after <hi>Gods</hi> and <hi>Davids</hi>) chuſe ten thouſand times all the firſt three, then the leaſt Spiritual ſtroke of Blindneſs, Hardneſs from the ſear of <hi>God? Iſa.</hi> 63.</p>
            <p>The nineteenth Queſtion.</p>
            <p>Whether <hi>Aſa</hi> did well in bringing the the people into Covenant, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>19</label> ſince as the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miner ſaith, he might thereby have made many turn <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> whereas the people ſwore with all their heart? &amp;<hi>c.</hi> And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> do follow, yet this flows from the Corruption of the hypocrite, and not from the holineſs of the command.</p>
            <p>I have before, and it is elſe where diſcovered, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> the figurative Nature of this Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> that people miraculouſly caſt out, and the ſeed of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> miraculouſly brought in; their Kings &amp; Judges immediately deſigned and ſtirred up by <hi>God,</hi> as the Saviours, and types of the great Saviour to come: theſe were anointed, as alſo were their Prophets and <hi>Prieſts,</hi> in figure of that great <hi>King, Prophet,</hi> and <hi>Prieſt, Chriſt Feſus:</hi> All which, with all thoſe figurative <hi>Ceremonies</hi> and miraculous goings of <hi>God</hi> with that people, is acknowledged by ſo many of <hi>Gods</hi> people, and by Maſter <hi>Cotton</hi> in
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:118103:44"/>this Controverſie; and that the people of <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> is the onely <hi>Antitype;</hi> as alſo that there is no Footſtep nor Colour, in the <hi>New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of <hi>Chriſt Feſus,</hi> for a <hi>National Church</hi> or <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant:</hi> And therefore,</p>
            <p>I ask, Firſt, Whether this be not an overthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the whole deſigne of <hi>God</hi> concerning <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> and a denying of him yet to be come; and to have fulfilled the <hi>National</hi> and <hi>Ceremonial</hi> figures? But ſince we ſay he is come,<note place="margin">Chriſt Feſus his Teſtament e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, although we had never heard of Moſes.</note> and hath brought the diſcovery of his Fathers diſpleaſure, otherwiſe diſpenſed then was in former times, to the Fathers and the Prophets; Is not his <hi>Teſtament</hi> compleat, and the <hi>Revelation</hi> of his Fathers minde full in all matters, as to his Servants and Followers, although we had never heard of <hi>Meſes,</hi> and although it ſhould have pleaſed <hi>God</hi> to have concealed the whole <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> from us?</p>
            <p>I Further ask,<note place="margin">The difference between Iſrael and other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> Whether <hi>Aſa</hi> did compel any Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that had not been ſo miraculouſly bought and brought by <hi>God</hi> as <hi>Iſrael</hi> was, into Covenant with him? And may indeed a <hi>King</hi> now, if he conquer all <hi>Nations,</hi> compel and force them all to ſwear to ſerve his <hi>God,</hi> to make a Covenant and Contract with him, and this under pain of death, as <hi>Aſa</hi> did? Did or might <hi>Aſa,</hi> or any of the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> or <hi>Iudah,</hi> ſo compel other Nations, which they did or might have conquered, and that under pain of death?</p>
            <p>Is not <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> the truly and onely King of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael?</hi> And is not his ſword, his two-edged ſword, and his mighty weapons, ſpiritual (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering into the very <hi>Hears,</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> and <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and thoughts of the Heart?</p>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:118103:44"/>
            <p>Secondly, I ask, If this poor <hi>Nation</hi> of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> &amp;<hi>c.</hi> have not heard the voice of the <hi>God</hi> of heaven out of the whirlwind (as in <hi>Iob</hi>) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring himſelf in thundring language, and dialects of <hi>Blood, Diſtractions,</hi> and <hi>Deſtructions,</hi> about this National League and Covenant?<note place="margin">The wonderful Character of Gods jealouſie upon the Scoriſh National Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</note> Were ever two Nations ſo ſolemnly, and with ſuch ſeeming glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Holineſs,</hi> united, to make this <hi>Iſland</hi> an holy Land, and to purge out, as out of an holy Land and Aire (as <hi>Canan</hi> was) all <hi>Idolatry, Schiſme,</hi> and <hi>Hereticks?</hi> And were there ever more evident Characters of the <hi>Iealouſie</hi> and <hi>diſpleaſure</hi> of the moſt <hi>High,</hi> written upon ſuch Covenants, ſuch Conjunctions?</p>
            <p>Or was there ever (almoſt) ſuch a miraculous <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion</hi> of the controverſie, between the <hi>Covenanters</hi> themſelves, about the Interpretations of it?</p>
            <p>And hath not the moſt holy and inviſible <hi>God</hi> made bare his holy Arme, and written it in <hi>Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> letters of blood, that he that runs may read it, That this <hi>National</hi> Covenanting, and <hi>National</hi> Churching, and <hi>National</hi> compelling, and <hi>National</hi> conforming (as to the Soules and Conſciences of men, and as to the worſhip of the <hi>God</hi> of heaven) is but <hi>Levitical</hi> and <hi>Ceremonial,</hi> but <hi>Moſaical</hi> and <hi>Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh,</hi> but <hi>Unchriſtian</hi> and deſtructive to the <hi>New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to the <hi>freedome</hi> of the ſoul and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, to the gratious free breathings of the moſt holy <hi>Spirit</hi> of God, perſwading and ſpiritually compelling, the <hi>Spirits</hi> and <hi>Souls</hi> of men, to knit the onely true <hi>Lovers Knot</hi> and Covenant, that Death and Hell, and all the powers of Earth and Hell, Men and Devils, ſhall never be able to untie?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It was no guilt of <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> in <hi>Aſa,</hi> to
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:118103:45"/>compel that whole Nation, which, according to thoſe figurative times and old <hi>Covenant,</hi> were mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly brought and kept in Covenant with <hi>God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Hypocriſie of Nationall Covenants.</note> upon which the <hi>Examiner</hi> doth not fix the leaſt charge of <hi>Hypocriſie:</hi> but now he may (and all men may) ask, why other whole Nations, and all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhould be forced (like Cattel) by thouſands and ten thouſands, <hi>Cities, Nations,</hi> &amp;<hi>c.</hi> to a <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>Covenant,</hi> and <hi>Worſhip,</hi> which their Forefathers knew not, which their Souls owne not, and their Conſciences ſecretly diſclaim as falſe? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Doth not this, as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> tels us, fill a Nation with <hi>Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie?</hi> And hath not this <hi>Doctrine</hi> filled this Nation (if ever any) with wonderful <hi>Hipocriſies,</hi> as the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Sword and power of compulſion hath fallen by <hi>Gods</hi> moſt holy providence, into the hands of <hi>Pagan,</hi> or <hi>Popiſh,</hi> or <hi>Protestant,</hi> or <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> or <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent,</hi> (if perſe cuting) Conſciences?</p>
            <p>I ask further, Is there not a two fold <hi>Hypocriſie,</hi> Firſt,<note place="margin">A tu of old Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie amongſt Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="7 letters">
                     <desc>〈7 letters〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that which is more hidden and ſecret, ſuch as <hi>Achitophels</hi> with <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>Fudas</hi> with <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> Thieves and Traytors in the Boſome, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet outwardly true, faithful, holy, Cordial? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, That which is more open, evident and plauſible, ſuch as that of the ten <hi>Tribes,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>feſſing</hi> the name of the <hi>God of Iſrael,</hi> and yet with-all, the Worſhip of the <hi>Calves;</hi> and <hi>Ieroboams Feaſts</hi> and <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and other his Inventions; and moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, living without the life of the true <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the late Wars, ſome that profeſſed to ſide with the Parliament, voted in the <hi>Houſe,</hi> ſat in <hi>Committees;</hi> yea fought for the <hi>Parliament, Lawes,</hi>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:118103:45"/>and <hi>Liherties,</hi> &amp;<hi>c.</hi> yet lay they like <hi>Traitours</hi> in the <hi>Boſome,</hi> as after was diſcovered. Others fought for the Parliament, <hi>Lawes</hi> and <hi>Liberties,</hi> and yet joyn'd openly with the <hi>King,</hi> fought under his Colours, and pretended onely the name of that (to wit, holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and the Love of <hi>God</hi>) which they hated more then <hi>Sin,</hi> and <hi>Hell,</hi> and <hi>Damning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or as in our Streets dayly, we finde two ſorts of <hi>Beggers,</hi> one ſpeaks ſuch wants,<note place="margin">Antichriſtian hypocriſie ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated.</note> ſo predicates <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> ſo prayes for you, that many are taken &amp; mov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to real pity and compaſſion, and yet deceived. A ſecond ſort, profeſs the Trade of <hi>Begging,</hi> they keep open thoſe Sores, which they will not have heal'd; they ſteal or get Children to beg with, they abhor to <hi>labour,</hi> and make a <hi>Trade</hi> of <hi>Hypocriſie:</hi> Tis true, that they crie up the name of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> too, and pray for you; but if you put not into their mouth, how ſoon fall they from <hi>bleſſing</hi> to <hi>curſing!</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Of this ſecond ſort,<note place="margin">The pretended Chriſtian Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons found An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian.</note> are not the Chriſtian <hi>Nations</hi> (ſo call'd) made up and conſtituted, whether <hi>Eaſt</hi> or <hi>Weſt, Greek</hi> or <hi>Latine,</hi> the <hi>Popiſh</hi> or <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Churches, who like the ten Tribes, and (many of them) like the ſtrange <hi>Nations,</hi> brought in after the Captivity by <hi>Salmanaſſer,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 17. They feared the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and ſerved him, and their owne Gods too; and the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God</hi> concludes of them, that they ſerved their owne <hi>Gods,</hi> and ſerved not the true <hi>God</hi> at all?</p>
            <p>Is not this apparently the ſtate of thouſands and ten thouſands and millions of (named) <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> profeſſing Chriſt in Word, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. but in works de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying of him, overſpread with the Abominations of <hi>Religious</hi> and moral <hi>Idolatries,</hi> ſpiritual and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:118103:46"/>
               <hi>Murthers, Whoredomes, Oppreſſions, Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> &amp;<hi>c.</hi> either as the great <hi>Whore</hi> (probably the <hi>Whore</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi>) actually drunk with the blood of the <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Prophets</hi> of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> or elſe thirſting af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the day of their bloody fils? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">Religious Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhments and horrid Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations.</note> I ask, Whether as to force the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of the <hi>Unwilling</hi> is a Soul-<hi>Rape,</hi> ſo to force the (Ignorant, prophane, and unregenerate) <hi>Nations,</hi> into a pretended holy fellowſhip and Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with <hi>God,</hi> be not ten thouſand fold more unho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and unrighteous, then to force into the Beds of any <hi>Men</hi> of <hi>Honour, ugly</hi> and <hi>deformed</hi> ſtrangers, yea enemies, yea and impudent Whores and Strumpets? Would the <hi>Propoſer</hi> ſtile their commands holy, juſt, good, did the matter concerne but his owne <hi>Bed?</hi> as who can but know the matter in queſtion ſo neerly concernes the <hi>Lord,</hi> being communion, which (<hi>Cant.</hi> 1.) is no other then the myſtical and ſpiritual <hi>Bed</hi> of the <hi>Lord Ieſus?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Did ever <hi>God</hi> or Man command to do well,<note place="margin">The methods of Friendſhip with God and men.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a ceaſing from <hi>Evil?</hi> Doth <hi>God</hi> or man ever ſtrike up Covenants of <hi>Love,</hi> Leagues of <hi>Amisy,</hi> yea or admit a <hi>treaty,</hi> before <hi>Repentance</hi> and <hi>Satisfaction</hi> for former Injuries, before the Removeall of <hi>Force,</hi> the laying down of <hi>Armes,</hi> and the acknowledging the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>State</hi> of ſuch with whom they treat? If theſe be waies of <hi>civility, rightecuſneſs, order, pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> what commands ſhall they be call'd, what <hi>holineſs</hi> and <hi>goodneſs</hi> ſhall be found in them, which carry written (like the <hi>Whores forehead, Rev.</hi> 18.) <hi>Myſteries, Babylon, Hypocriſies, Diſſimulations?</hi> &amp;<hi>c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore (laſtly) I ask, how much infinitely ſweeter are <hi>Gods</hi> Methods, delighting onely in a
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:118103:46"/>
               <hi>willing</hi> people? how ſweet are the paths of the <hi>Lamb</hi> of <hi>God</hi> Chriſt Jeſus, whoſe true Meſſengers are <hi>Maidens</hi> (<hi>Pro.</hi> 9.) who with <hi>Virgin</hi>-Chaſtity and Modeſty, invite poor ſinners to the heavenly <hi>Feaſt</hi> and <hi>Banquet?</hi> And becauſe three are not onely Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of pleaſures at the right hand of <hi>God,</hi> but Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of <hi>Fire</hi> and Brimſtone for the obſtinate, they knowing theſe Terrours of <hi>God,</hi> perſwade, and pull, and compel poor ſinners as <hi>Brands</hi> from the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Burnings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſum of the twentieth Queſtion.</p>
            <p>Whether thoſe portions of Scripture, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>20</label> that contain principles neceſſary to Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, deſerve to be call'd and deſpiſed by the name of Forms; and whether the Examiner think fit upon the title of formes, to deſpiſe the Principles of the Doctrine of Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 2. Whether if the Examiner were ready to ſtarve, or ſick neer Death, he would refuſe Bread or Phyſick, becauſe they came in Formes?</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ask, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Whether the <hi>Propoſer</hi> of theſe Queſtions have fairly collected from any words of the <hi>Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miner</hi> in the quoted ninth <hi>Section,</hi> that the <hi>Examiner</hi> doth call any Principle, neceſſary to Salvation, or deſpiſe them under the name of <hi>Formes;</hi> or doth deſpiſe thoſe Principles of the Doctrine of Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. under the title of <hi>Formes?</hi> or whether he do
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:118103:47"/>ſimply, or without all due conſideration, contend againſt the Title, or the ſubſtance of a <hi>Forme?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For can it be ſuppoſed,<note place="margin">Of outward Forms of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</note> that the <hi>Examiner</hi> ſhould plead ſo much for the <hi>Light</hi> of the holy <hi>Scripture</hi> and the <hi>holy Spirit</hi> of God, and yet to want that light of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> as not to know that <hi>form a dat eſſe;</hi> and (although there are very intricate Diſputes <hi>de formie internis &amp; externis,</hi> and whence the <hi>forms</hi> of creatures are produced) to imagine that any thing in the world ſhould have a <hi>being</hi> (much leſs the <hi>best</hi> and <hi>perfectest,</hi> ſpiritual and heavenly things) and be <hi>formleſs?</hi> or that there ſhould be ſo much viſible <hi>Acknowledgements, ſervice</hi> or <hi>Worſhip</hi> of God left in the world, as of the <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> (which the <hi>Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miner</hi> is known to approve and practiſe) without ſome <hi>form</hi> and <hi>order,</hi> without which it muſt prove a <hi>Chaos,</hi> a <hi>Babel</hi> and <hi>confuſion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides,<note place="margin">Several ſorts of Forms pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all to be Chriſts</note> are not theſe his very words excepted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, [Do yet make ſo much of outward Forms, as to <hi>force</hi> men to bow down to them?]</p>
            <p>In which, doth there not fairly ſeem to be couch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this double Aſſertion,</p>
            <p>Firſt, That there are many ſorts of <hi>outward forms,</hi> Forms of <hi>Confeſsions,</hi> Forms of <hi>Prayers,</hi> Formes of Churches, Formes of <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> Formes of <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> &amp;<hi>c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, That every Sect and Sort are wofully apt to force one another to bow down unto their owne moſt excellent waies and manners, of which they ſeverally and reſpectively are ſo and ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded: And is not this moſt wofully and lamentably true, in all Nations, in all Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in all Sects of all ſorts, now extant among
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:118103:47"/>our ſelves, and upon all the Face of the whole Earth?</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ask,<note place="margin">Of doctr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> neceſſary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</note> If the <hi>Propoſer</hi> walk not upon a moſt dangerous <hi>Bridge,</hi> whiles he diſputes of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples neceſſary to <hi>Salvation?</hi> And indeed, whether both <hi>Papiſt</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant</hi> are not both in the woods, while they force whole Nations to believe many Doctrines neceſſary to <hi>Salvation,</hi> and yet wind up all in one, <hi>viz.</hi> to believe as the <hi>Church</hi> believes? For if they prove but obedient Sons to the doctrine of their Mother the <hi>Church</hi> (although they wholly want the <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> of God their (pretended) <hi>Father,</hi> yet how have ſuch Children been ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times more accepted, then ſuch who cannot ſee nor live, but by their owne Eyes and Faith, and deſire to taſte, to examine and try all things, and to hold faſt that onely which they are perſwaded comes from <hi>God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe,<note place="margin">Fundamentals of Religon.</note> notwithſtanding ſeveral numbers of Fundamentals, which others both <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> are pleaſed to aſſert: Yet I ask, what we think of the ſhort word of the <hi>Lord Ieſus, Mark</hi> 16. 16. He that <hi>Believeth</hi> and is <hi>Baptized,</hi> ſhall be ſaved? yea whether upon the point, the firſt of theſe two be not abſolutely neceſſary; becauſe he pincheth onely upon not <hi>Believing</hi> as <hi>Damnable;</hi> He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth not, ſhall be damned?</p>
            <p>And howſoever ſome grant that as to the viſible profeſſion of the <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">It is danger<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> to ſay, with how little faith God will ſave.</note> a diſtinct know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt Jeſus is neceſſary, Yet we know what is extant abroad of a poſſibility of Salvation, without an expreſs and diſtinct knowledge of the name of Chriſt, according to that of <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. He that
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:118103:48"/>comes to <hi>God,</hi> muſt believe that <hi>God</hi> is, and that he is a <hi>Rewarder</hi> of them that diligently ſeek him. And I ask, Whether (although it be a duty to work out Salvation with fear and trembling, and to grow in the <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Knowledge</hi> of the <hi>Lord Ieſus</hi>) yet is it not very preſumptuous and dangerous to ſet a <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus infra,</hi> a <hi>ſtint</hi> and <hi>bound</hi> of ſo much <hi>Knowledge,</hi> and ſo much grace of Chriſt (as to the degrees of it) without which there is no Salvation.</p>
            <p>I ask,<note place="margin">Two of the Principles Heb. <hi>6.</hi> of great controverſie.</note> once more, from that <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. VVhether (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I queſtion not but that both the <hi>Propoſer</hi> and <hi>Examiner</hi> believe four of theſe Principles, <hi>viz. Repentance, Faith,</hi> the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> and <hi>Iudgement,</hi> yet) whether the <hi>Propoſer</hi> be able to diſſolve the doubts of thouſands, as to thoſe other two, the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of Baptiſmes, and the Laying on of hands; concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which, the more Conſcientious and tender the People of <hi>God</hi> are, about the true worſhip of God and Chriſt Jeſus, the more they finde their loſs, about the holy waies and means of it?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I ask, What have been moſt of all the Forms, and Preſcripts of Doctrine and worſhip (ſince the great <hi>Apoſtacie</hi> and falling away) but <hi>meer</hi> Formes and Pictures, without the power and life of <hi>Godlineſs?</hi> In which reſpect, may I not ſay in the Language of <hi>Iames,</hi> As the Body without the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and Faith without works is dead; So, what have been the ſeveral National Models, Platforms, Frames and Forms,<note place="margin">The meer For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malities of State-Forms of worſhip.</note> of the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments (which the <hi>Fathers</hi> have built, and the <hi>Children</hi> have broke) either in the <hi>Eaſt</hi> or <hi>Weſtern</hi> Churches, even to the laſt, and <hi>Youngeſt,</hi> and <hi>Faireſt</hi> of the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, but Pictures drawn to the Life, and yet but liveleſs Pictures and <hi>Proforma?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:118103:48"/>
            <p>I moſt humbly and thankfully acknowledge the Heavenly diſcoveries of many Truths of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> wrapt up confuſedly even in <hi>Babylon</hi> it ſelfe and the people of the <hi>God</hi> of heaven with them; from whence he hath, and will gloriouſly redeem them both: I acknowledge the ſeveral bleſſed degrees,<note place="margin">Gods light and Gods people wrapt up in the National Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations.</note> and increaſings of <hi>Light,</hi> wrapt up in ſeveral <hi>Clouds</hi> of Reformations (ſo call'd) in our owne and other Nations: I am far from imagining that people ſhould hold nothing, do nothing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for I unfeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly deſire (as the Scripture ſpeaks) in a Scripture<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, that all men might be ſaved; That every Man were a <hi>Noble</hi> Man, an ingenious <hi>Berean,</hi> Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining by the Scriptures, and holding faſt to the Death, what he believes he hath received from the <hi>Father</hi> of Lights.</p>
            <p>And yet, <hi>better ſit ſtill, then ſtill riſe and fall:</hi> Have all the <hi>Spirit,</hi> the <hi>Calling,</hi> the <hi>Gifts,</hi> the <hi>Life</hi> and the preſence of <hi>God</hi> with them; as thoſe firſt Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> whoſe Succeſſours Men yet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be?</p>
            <p>Were it not better for us to acknowledge,<note place="margin">The danger of our own Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly matters.</note> how <hi>poor,</hi> how <hi>naked,</hi> how <hi>blind,</hi> how <hi>miſerable</hi> we are, and to liſten to the holy Counſel of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> &amp;c. to buy of him, that bleſſed <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Eye-ſalve,</hi> that white Rayment and fine Linnen, that we may truely <hi>ſee,</hi> and be truely <hi>rich,</hi> and be truely <hi>glorious</hi> and <hi>beautiful;</hi> then boaſting of our <hi>Knowledge,</hi> and <hi>Abundance,</hi> and want of nothing; we prove ſo grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous to the ſtomach of Chriſt Jeſus, that he vomit us with loathing out of his mouth?</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I ask, In caſe we had for unqueſtionable <hi>Fundamentals,</hi> a <hi>Creed</hi> compoſed by the twelve <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:118103:49"/>of the <hi>Lamb:</hi> That a <hi>Synod</hi> of heavenly <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> aſſembled and concluded of Fundamentals, of Forms of Worſhip,<note place="margin">External force in Spirituals can onely pierce the outſide.</note> Ordinations, Miniſteries, Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (and all without the reach of a Curſe, for another <hi>Goſpel, Gal.</hi> 1.) Yet I ask, what rule can be produced from the Teſtament of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> that theſe Forms, theſe Preſcripts muſt be impoſed, and beaten into (not the Braines and Hearts of men, which is impoſſible) but into the outſides and knees of men, with Swords and Staves, that (as Chriſt Jeſus ſaid of the <hi>Samaritans</hi>) they might worſhip they know not what? What reaſon of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or Civility, that the <hi>Talmud</hi> of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> the <hi>Alcaron</hi> of the <hi>Turks,</hi> and the <hi>Canons</hi> of all ſorts of <hi>Popes</hi> muſt not be queſtioned? What <hi>Scripture</hi> or <hi>Reaſon</hi> ſhall force a man to be a <hi>Scholar</hi> to a <hi>Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> and force him to pay for his <hi>Teaching;</hi> To truſt his <hi>Ship</hi> with a Pilot, and to pay him for his Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loting; to truſt himſelf with a <hi>Guide,</hi> and to pay him for his Conduct, when he believes that <hi>Teacher,</hi> that <hi>Pilot,</hi> are dangerouſly ignorant, that <hi>Guide</hi> is blind? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The myſtery and and tyranny of perſecuting Teachers.</note> Yea further, from whom he muſt receive all upon Truſt, and not dare (in the very place and time of <hi>Teaching</hi>) to propoſe his <hi>Doubt,</hi> his <hi>Queſtion,</hi> his <hi>Objection,</hi> or deſire <hi>Explanation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I add, What <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> is that, which commands that no Churches be gathered, no Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters choſen, no Doctrine preached, but what the civil <hi>Sword</hi> ſhall ſay is true and Orthodox? Nay no <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> himſelf choſen, nor any Civil <hi>Officer,</hi> except he be of our Church, our Way and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as ſome ſay is the <hi>Myſtery</hi> and <hi>Tyranny</hi> of <hi>New-Englands</hi> practice?</p>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:118103:49"/>
            <p>The two and twentieth Queſtion.</p>
            <p>If God was to be bleſſed for putting it into the Heart of a <hi>Heathen</hi> Magiſtrate to make Lawes for Religion (<hi>Iſa.</hi> 7.27.) Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he comes not neer to a curſe, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>22</label> that would take out of the heart of a Chriſtian Magiſtrate the advancement of true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and perſwade him to give a Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to the chieſe Enemies of Religion, <hi>Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Hereſie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sure the Propoſer highly eſteems this <hi>Example</hi> of <hi>Erra</hi> 7. for, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> not content to mention it in the ſeventh Queſtion, he attempts to win it by <hi>Force</hi> and <hi>Storming</hi> (indeed in a very ſtormy <hi>Language</hi>) in this laſt Queſtion.</p>
            <p>To many Branches of the ſame hath been ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: As to the nature of Civil <hi>Magiſtracie,</hi> eſſential<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Civil all the world over: As to the power of the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> or <hi>Officers</hi> deſigned unto them by the people, as but their <hi>Deputies,</hi> either <hi>Legiſlative</hi> or <hi>Executive:</hi> As to the perfection of Civil <hi>Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie</hi> in its ſelf and in its kind, not capable of <hi>Dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution</hi> or <hi>Addition,</hi> by the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> change of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> to or from <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> or any other <hi>Religion</hi> in the world: As to <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> his fact,<note place="margin">Artaxerxes his favour to the Iewes.</note> not being moved out of any heart to the true <hi>Religion;</hi> for neither did he, or his people, forſake their owne; but out of a Conquering <hi>Terrour</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> he ſhews, juſt <hi>mercy</hi> to his captives and people; he feares
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:118103:50"/>
               <hi>wrath</hi> to himſelf and his Sons from that <hi>God,</hi> whoſe love and acquaintance he cared not for. But I ſhall add (with Chriſts help) theſe few <hi>Queries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Whether this Suppoſition of making Laws to advance <hi>Religion,</hi> and eſpecially in a National way, doth not overthrow and <hi>Evacuate</hi> one great end of the comming of the <hi>Lord Jeſus,</hi> which was to fulfil all thoſe former ſhadowes of <hi>Temple, Altar, Prieſts, Sacrifice, &amp;c.</hi> to tear the <hi>veil,</hi> to break downe the <hi>partition Wall,</hi> and with the two edged Sword of his Spirit, (his Word) to conquer poor ſinners in a way of love?<note place="margin">National holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, &amp;c. abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by Chriſt Ieſus the body and ſubſtance.</note> For if <hi>Ezra's</hi> pattern of carrying Lawes and Authority from this <hi>King,</hi> to force men to keep the Law of <hi>God,</hi> in this <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Religion, <hi>Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh</hi> Nation, be a preſident for all <hi>Nations,</hi> where is the aboliſhing of the holy <hi>Nation,</hi> holy <hi>Cities,</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Temples, Altars, Prieſts?</hi> &amp;c. Or ought we not (if <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> be not come) to have the Officers commanded by the King to be Tole free, verſe 24. the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> the <hi>Levites,</hi> the <hi>Singers,</hi> the <hi>Porters,</hi> the <hi>Nethinims,</hi> or <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the houſe of <hi>God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it be ſaid, The <hi>Morality</hi> of ſuch a Law remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, I ask, Whether according to <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. there being a neceſſity of the change of the Prieſthood, there is not a neceſſity of the change of the Law alſo, of that Law of Shadows, the holy Land, holy Temples, holy Prieſts, holy Swords? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I further ask, If that people of <hi>God</hi> (the figure of <hi>Gods Iſrael</hi> in after-Ages to ariſe, in all Nations of the world) if they had not been Captivated, but had been in their owne Land, and not reſtrained by force; whether they ought not to have builded the <hi>Altar</hi> and <hi>Temple,</hi> without the Kings command,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:118103:50"/>yea and againſt it? Yea it is expreſly ſaid, <hi>chap.</hi> 4.<note place="margin">Gods people in Spirituals know no Caeſar but himſelf, and dear Son.</note> they were made to ceaſe the building by power and Force; yet they went on, <hi>chap.</hi> 5. to build again, at the inſtigation of <hi>Haggai</hi> and <hi>Zachary,</hi> notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the prohibition of the King, yet lying in force againſt them.</p>
            <p>And laſtly I ask, If theſe things were not <hi>Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.) or Types, figuring out the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of <hi>Gods</hi> people, who if not hindred by actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Force and Power, ought onely to regard (in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituals) the Scepter, and Sword, and Crown of the <hi>Lord Ieſus Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, I ask, What Lawes this <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> made for the advancement of <hi>Religion?</hi> Is not the firſt of abſolute Freedome and Toleration to theſe poor captive <hi>Iewes?</hi> Was there any <hi>Babylonian</hi> or <hi>Perſian</hi> command to go up to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to pay, or to offer a peny toward this <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition?</hi> Yea were not the <hi>Iewes</hi> themſelves abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely free, whether to go up to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> or ſtay in <hi>Babel;</hi> whether to offer to this work one peny, or not, as appeares both by the <hi>Decrees</hi> of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> in the firſt Chapter; of <hi>Darius,</hi> in the ſixth; and of <hi>Artax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erxes,</hi> in the ſeventh? Secondly, he decreed bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful <hi>Aſſiſtance</hi> out of his owne <hi>Treaſury,</hi> toward the building of the <hi>Temple,</hi> the <hi>Sacrifices,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, a <hi>Decree</hi> againſt any that ſhould oppoſe, or hinder the building of this <hi>Houſe;</hi> and therefore (accordingly) whoſoever would not do the Law of <hi>God,</hi> and of the <hi>King,</hi> judgement muſt be executed ſpeedily, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And <hi>chap.</hi> 6.11. whoſoever ſhould alter <hi>Darius</hi> his decree, Timber ſhould be pull'd downe from his houſe, and being ſet up, he muſt be
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:118103:51"/>hanged thereon, and his houſe made a dunghil.</p>
            <p>If any ſhall ſay, The command of <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> here mentioned, was a command and Law in Spirituals, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ask, What Law was the Law of <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> the <hi>King?</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Law of Artaxerxes, was an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Law of Toleration of the Iews Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, vaſtly differing from, and oppoſite to his.</note> was it of commanding the <hi>Iewes</hi> to his <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> and <hi>Conſcience,</hi> in an <hi>Uniformity</hi> of <hi>Worſhip</hi> to the <hi>Nation</hi> wherein they were captive? Yea, was it a commanding of the <hi>Iewes</hi> to their owne <hi>Religion,</hi> or onely (on his part) a Law of <hi>Toleration</hi> and <hi>Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> to practiſe their owne <hi>Religion, Conſcience,</hi> and <hi>Worſhip,</hi> and that with favourable <hi>Incouragement</hi> from himſelf?</p>
            <p>For (as before) if the force were removed, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> ſhould have given them no Countenance nor Incouragement; Yet I ask, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as <hi>Iewes</hi> (Gods people and ſubjects) they ought not of themſelves to have departed from <hi>Babylor,</hi> and from all parts of the World, and to have aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended to <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> (as the <hi>Iews</hi> literally dream) to their holy City, and there have built the <hi>Temple,</hi> and preſented their Sacrifices? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Further,<note place="margin">The literal and Spiritual Iew.</note> I ask, As <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> made not one Law either how or when the <hi>Iewes</hi> ſhould pray, or faſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but left them free to their owne Conſcience, to go up, or not to go up to <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> ſo when theſe Kings did makes Lawes in Spirituals (as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning prayer) whether <hi>Daniel</hi> did not well, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to ceaſe praying, or by ſhutting of his win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow to give appearance of obedience, though to the extream ruine of life? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And conſequently. Whether as the <hi>Iewes</hi> refuſed to be ſubject to any Judicature but <hi>Gods</hi> alone re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:118103:51"/>by <hi>Moſes;</hi> So whether <hi>Chriſtian Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Iews</hi> ought to acknowledge any Tribunal but <hi>Gods?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, I ask, Whether the plain <hi>Engliſh</hi> of not tolerating the <hi>Idolater</hi> and <hi>Heretick,</hi> hath not been in all Ages ſince <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> the not tolerating in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus, God</hi> manifeſted in fleſh, and both in his owne <hi>Perſon,</hi> and in his <hi>Followers,</hi> the hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or perſecuting of him out of the world?</p>
            <p>Was there ever any of the <hi>Prophets</hi> eſteemed ſo great an <hi>Heretick</hi> from the <hi>Iewiſh Religion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chriſt Ieſus ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted and hanged as the greateſt Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer and Heretick that was.</note> as <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> was? was there ever ſuch a <hi>Blaſphemer</hi> of <hi>God</hi> (as the <hi>High Prieſt</hi> eſteemed him) as the bleſſed Son of <hi>God; God</hi> himſelf; <hi>Chriſt Ieſus?</hi> And doth not the many Books of <hi>Martyrs,</hi> in our owne and other Languages ſet forth, that under this <hi>Hood</hi> and <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard,</hi> the Devil hath caſt the Saints into <hi>Priſon, Rev.</hi> 2. He hath watched to devour the <hi>Man-child, Rev.</hi> 12. and hunted the Woman the Spouſe of <hi>Christ Jeſus,</hi> and her ſeed: And the great <hi>Whore</hi> pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that ſhe drinks the blood of <hi>Hereticks,</hi> &amp;c. hath been drunk with the blood of the Saints, and Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of <hi>Ieſus? Rev.</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>Hence will not Reaſon ſuſpect a Murtherous ſnare in the Law pretended againſt <hi>Thieves, Robbers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">True grounds of ſuſpition, in Spirituals.</note> 
               <hi>Whores,</hi> &amp;c. and yet moſt commonly falling upon none but <hi>honeſt</hi> and <hi>faithful, chaſt,</hi> and modeſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons?</p>
            <p>Are not theſe <hi>Engines</hi> worthily to be queſtioned, which pretending to take none but <hi>Birds</hi> of prey, and <hi>Wolves,</hi> &amp;c. and yet ordinarily catch nothing but harmeleſs <hi>Doves,</hi> the <hi>Sheep</hi> and <hi>Lambs?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>If it be ſaid, <hi>Idolatry, Hereſie,</hi> &amp;c. are the chiefeſt Enemies in <hi>Religion,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:118103:52"/>
            <p>I ask, Firſt, If thoſe very famous Religions, which have pretended themſelves the trueſt in the World, have not been found the greateſt <hi>Idols?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">Chriſt Ieſus his Spiritual provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, againſt Spiritual Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries.</note> Grant them to be the greateſt Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, yet ſince Enemies are of two ſorts, Spiritual and Corporal, I ask, Whether as Corporal wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon are proper againſt Corporal, ſo whether Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual weapons are not only proper againſt (meerly) Spiritual Adverſaries?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Could <hi>Christ Ieſus</hi> ſo forget himſelfe, as not to take ſufficient order for Spiritual weapons againſt all his Spiritual enemies? In a <hi>Battel</hi> or <hi>Fight,</hi> by Sea or Land, how apt are men to charge <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals</hi> and <hi>Commanders,</hi> if <hi>Ammunition</hi> be wanting, &amp;c. Yea in that caſe, how juſtly may men complain (as in 88) that <hi>Powder</hi> was ſaid to be wanting in our own Ships, at our owne doores? And ſhall i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be imagined that the <hi>Laſt Will</hi> and <hi>Teſtament</hi> of the Son of God, his whole Life, his 40 daies after his Reſurrection, and thoſe Gifts, which upon his <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph</hi> in Heaven he ſent upon men, ſhould leave his <hi>Army,</hi> his <hi>Family,</hi> his <hi>Kingdome,</hi> his <hi>Wife,</hi> unprovi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo that in the very day of the <hi>Battel,</hi> they muſt be forced to the Forge of the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> to bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Swords, Halberts, Guns, Pikes, Priſons, Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, againſt <hi>Idolaters, Hereticks?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, I may end and ask, in the Propoſers owne words (whether he be not neer a Curſe, that would change the two-edged Sword of <hi>Gods Spirit,</hi> the word of <hi>God,</hi> for a Sword of ſteel, in the hand of <hi>Civil Officers;</hi> and the <hi>Arme</hi> of the eternal Spirit of <hi>God,</hi> for an arme of <hi>Fleſh?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:118103:52"/>
            <p>And if bleſſed are Chriſts peace-makers,<note place="margin">Chriſts Curſings and Bleſſings.</note> and Chriſts perſecuted (<hi>Matth.</hi> 5.) how neer to a curſe doth he come, that brings not Buckets to quench, but Bellowes to kindle the <hi>Fire</hi> of Gods Jealouſie againſt State Inventions; the Fires of perſecutions and hunting of Chriſts Saints, the Fires of devour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Wars</hi> amongſt the Nations, for their reſpective Religions and Conſciences? How neer to a curſe doth he come, who under a Cloak of <hi>Chriſtian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate,</hi> True Religion, Zeal againſt <hi>Idolaters, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> &amp;c. ſhall conceal a <hi>Dagger</hi> (which yet, I hope this <hi>Propoſer</hi> knowingly doth not) ſtabbing at the heart of <hi>God,</hi> his Chriſt, his Spirit, his Saints, his pure Worſhip, yea and at the Heart of all <hi>Civil peace</hi> and <hi>Civil Magiſtracie,</hi> and <hi>Civility</hi> it ſelf throughout the whole World?</p>
            <p>And therefore laſtly, I ask, Whether theſe two Examining <hi>Worthies</hi> ſhall not be wrapt up in the everlaſting Armes of <hi>Bleſſedneſs</hi> it ſelf, while they improve their <hi>Talents</hi> uprightly, and impartially, in the further Examination of this <hi>Fire</hi> of <hi>Zeal</hi> in queſtion? Yea and whether not onely theſe two honourable Senatours, but the moſt renowned Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate of the world (the Parliament it ſelf) ſhall not be truly crowned with the Lawrells of true Nobility, as the <hi>Bereans</hi> were, while they Candid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Impartially Examine whether theſe things are ſo or no?</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
